<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "..\..\support\dtd\v3m.dtd">
<spec>
	<header ballotStatus="Draft" ballotNumber="2">
		<title>HL7 Version 3 Standard: Transport Specifications Overview</title>
		<version>1</version>
		<ballot type="Draft" number="2"/>
		<date>20050318</date>
		<authlist>
			<author>
				<role>Control Query Co-Chair</role>
				<name>Grahame Grieve</name>
				<affiliation>Kestral Computing</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Control Query Co-Chair</role>
				<name>Anthony Julian</name>
				<affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Primary Contributor</role>
				<name>Paul Knapp</name>
				<affiliation>Continovation Services</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Control Query Co-Chair</role>
				<name>Joann Larson</name>
				<affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Control Query Co-Chair</role>
				<name>Douglas Pratt</name>
				<affiliation>Siemens</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Control Query Co-Chair</role>
				<name>Rene Spronk</name>
				<affiliation>Ringholm</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authlist>
		<!--	<legalese copyRightDate="2004" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 2.8.61" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to: Paul Knapp"/> -->
	</header>
	<body>
		<div1 id="transports" ballotStatus="Draft" ballotNumber="2">
			<head>HL7 Message Transport Specifications</head>
			<div2 id="messageOverview">
				<head>Overview</head>
				<p>
					The HL7 Message Transport Specifications documents provide details as to the usage of a variety of communication transports for the exchange of HL7 based content, messages and documents.  Currently specification documents for MLLP,  SOAP-Web Services and ebXML are included in the package for separate review or separate balloting.  Specification documents for other transports may be included as they are available.
				</p>
				<p>These Transport Specifications are not to be confused with the content of Transmission Infrastructure.  Transmission infrastructure describes the information model, messages and interactions related to the assembly of an HL7 v3 composite message.  The Transport Specifications address moving the message payload (the HL7 v3 composite message and/or HL7 v2 composite message) from sender to receiver.  These transports are all capable of moving HL7 v3 composite messages and may also support moving HL7 v2 and CDA composite messages.

In general, HL7 v3 is agnostic to the use of specific technologies, whether in terms of implementation or transport.  The existence of these three Transport Specifications is not a specific endorsement of these particular technologies, or a rejection of other possible technologies.  These transport specifications merely recognize that these technologies are either well established or of specific interest within the HL7 community.  There is no requirement that all, or any, of these technologies be implemented.
				</p>
				<p> The specifications in the current document are: </p>
				<list role="unordered">
					<item>Transport Specification - ebXML, Release 1  DSTU</item>
					<item>Transport Specification - Web Services Profile , Release 1 DSTU ( 2nd DSTU Update )</item>
					<item>Transport Specification - MLLP, Release 2  ( Normative )</item>
				</list>
				<p>Any of the listed transports may be used to exchange HL7 content.  It is the responsibility of trading partners to review the application of these transports, and their features and restrictions, to determine which transport(s) may be best suited for the particular needs of the trading partners.</p>
			</div2>
			<div2 id="transportebXML">
				<head>Transport Specification - ebXML, Release 1  DSTU</head>
				<p>The purpose of the ebXML message wrapper is to provide a secure, flexible transport for exchanging HL7 messages and other content, and potentially other message formats, between message handling interfaces or ebXML Message Service Handlers (ebXML MSH). The ebXML Transport supports reliable messaging, encryption, authenticaltion and digital signatures, and exchange of messages over a variety of lower level transports such as HTTP, SMTP and TCP/IP.</p>
			</div2>
			<div2 id="transportWebservices">
				<head>Transport Specification - Web Services Profile , Release 1 DSTU</head>
				<p>The purpose of the Web Services Profile (WSP) is to provide implementation guidelines to promote interoperability between implementers that want to exchange HL7 Version 3 messages using standards that fall under the general definition of Web Services. With the objective of leveraging the effort of the industry to promote interoperability, recommendations from organizations like WS-I, W3C and other will be taken into account. </p>
			</div2>
			<div2 id="transportMLLP">
				<head>Transport Specification - MLLP, Release 2</head>
				<p>The purpose of the MLLP Protocol (Minimum Lower Layer Protocol) is to provide both a minimalistic OSI-session layer framing protocol as well as a minimalistic reliable transport protocol. If security is an issue, additional protocols or technologies will have to be layered on top of MLLP to achieve these goals. </p>
			</div2>
		</div1>
		<div1 id="features">
			<head>Transports Features</head>
			<div2 id="featureIntro">
				<head>Overview</head>
				<p>The table below provides a comparison of the transport specifications with respect to the transport features documented in the Abstract Transport Specification document.  The table is based on the full features as described by a transport specification, inclusive of optional features contained therein. No guidance is provided here as to which features may be desireable in a given computing or message exchange environment.</p>
				<p/>
				<table>
					<thead>
						<tr>
							<th>
								<emph role="strong">Feature</emph>
							</th>
							<th>
								<emph role="strong">ebXML</emph>
							</th>
							<th>
								<emph role="strong">Web Services</emph>
							</th>
							<th>
								<emph role="strong">MLLP</emph>
							</th>
						</tr>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<emph role="strong">Addressing</emph>
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Routing
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<emph role="strong">Reliable Messaging</emph>
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								In-Order Delivery
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								At-Most-Once Delivery
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<emph role="strong">Security</emph>
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Integrity
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Confidentiality
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Non-Repudiation
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Authorization
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No?</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Authentication
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Auditing
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								Encryption
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<emph role="strong">HL7 v2 Support</emph>
							</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
							<td>No</td>
							<td>Yes</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
			</div2>
		</div1>
	</body>
</spec>

