<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/5/2008 10:36:28 AM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/5/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-POCG_DO000000UV"><head>POCG_DO000000UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="genotype" lastEdit="2006-03-12T11:52:17"><label>Genotype</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-12T11:52:17"><p>The genetic constitution of an organism or cell, as distinct from its expressed features or phenotype. In particular it is the allelic makeup of an organism with regard to an observed trait. In the HL7 models, the use of the Genotype term (and the root class - GeneticLocus) encompasses all genomic aspects related to a specific chromosomal or mitochondrial locus, including DNA sequence variations, gene expression and proteomics.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="clinical_phenotype" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:15"><label>Clinical Phenotype</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:15"><p>Phenotype is properties that are observed. In the case of clinical phenotype it is the clinical condition such as disease, sensitivity to a drug etc that are observed in an individual.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="individualallele" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:10:23"><label>IndividualAllele</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:10:23"><p>One of the different forms of a gene is called an Allele. In humans one allele comes from the paternal chromosome and another from the maternal chromosome. Different alleles bring about variation in inherited characteristics. By Individual we mean that it is possible to represent the actual sequence of an individual which might contain SNPs that are not part of the allele definition.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="mutation" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:11:02"><label>Mutation</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:11:02"><p>Heritable change in the DNA sequence. A mutation - or alteration - in a particular gene-DNA often results in a certain disease.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="snp" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:21"><label>SNP</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:21"><p>A variation that occurs in human DNA which is common and minute. These variations are usually inherited in families or might be idiosyncratic.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="polypeptide" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:01:59"><label>Polypeptide</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:01:59"><p>A peptide is composed of a chain that may be considered as derived from linking amino acids by forming peptide bonds.  Polypeptides are long stretches of such peptide chains.  A protein is made up of a polypeptide chain plus other chemical groups.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="gene_expression" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:57:46"><label>Gene Expression</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:57:46"><p>Gene Expression is the cellular process that starts with the production of messenger RNA (mRNA) by chromosomal DNA in a process called transcription.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="down's_syndrome" lastEdit="2005-03-16T08:10:48"><label>Down's syndrome</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T08:10:48"><p>This syndrome is associated with a chromosomal condition where the individual has 47 instead of 46 chromosomes.  This syndrome is associated with mental retardation.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="haplotype" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:00:08"><label>Haplotype</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:00:08"><p>The particular combination of alleles in a defined region of some chromosome.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="snp-haplotype" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:42"><label>SNP-Haplotype</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:42"><p>Patterns of SNPs on a block of DNA.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="determinant_peptide" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:33"><label>Determinant Peptide</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:33"><p>A conserved region of a protein responsible for the certain function of the protein.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="donor" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:54"><label>Donor</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:56:54"><p>An individual from whom an organ or tissue is removed for transplantation.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="antigen" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:54:03"><label>Antigen</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:54:03"><p>A foreign substance, such as a transplanted organ, that triggers the body to try to destroy it. This response may be the production of antibodies, which try to destroy the antigen (the transplanted organ).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="hla" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:00:28"><label>HLA</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:00:28"><p>Human Leukocyte Antigens (HLA): Molecule found on cells in the body that characterize each person as unique. These antigens are inherited from your parents. In donor-recipient matching, HLA determines whether someone will accept an organ from a donor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="tissuetypingfacility" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:03:38"><label>TissueTypingFacility</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:03:38"><p>The examination of human leukocyte antigens (HLA) in a patient. Tissue typing is done for all donors and recipients in organ transplantation to help match the donor and recipient.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="tissue-typing" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:57"><label>Tissue-Typing</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:02:57"><p>Tissue Typing/HLA-typing: A blood test that helps evaluates how closely the tissues of the donor match those of the recipient.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="class_i_antigens" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:55:28"><label>Class I Antigens</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:55:28"><p>There are two classes of MHC antigens, Class I and Class II. Class I antigens alert killer T-cells (T-8 or CD-8 protein) to the presence of body cells that have been invaded by bacteria or viruses, or changed by cancer or disease.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="class_ii_antigens" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:09:18"><label>Class II Antigens</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:09:18"><p>Class II antigens, located on B-cells and other immune cells, can capture and break down antigens, making them more visible to the helper T-cells (T-4 or CD-4 protein). </p></def></gitem><gitem id="locusmatching" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:01:28"><label>LocusMatching</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:01:28"><p>Locus is a position in a chromosome of a particular gene or allele. LocusMatching is the similarity in the locus between the donor and recipient.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="bone_marrow" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:08:55"><label>Bone Marrow</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:08:55"><p>A spongy tissue inside large bones where the body blood cells (red blood cells, white blood cells and platelets) are made.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="bone_marrow_transplant" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:55:06"><label>Bone Marrow Transplant (BMT)</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T22:55:06"><p>Healthy bone marrow is given to patients whose marrow is damaged.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="allele" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:08:40"><label>Allele</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T23:08:40"><p>Mutually exclusive forms of the same gene, occupying the same locus on homologous chromosomes, and governing the same biochemical and developmental process. In the HL7 model we use the class name IndividualAllele to emphasize that even if it is a non-variant gene, it is expected that the individual sequencing of the patient gene will have DNA variations such as non-coding SNPs or SNPs with unknown significance.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="geneticlocus" lastEdit="2006-03-12T11:55:46"><label>GeneticLocus</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-12T11:55:46"><p>A genetic locus is a position in a genome (or linkage map) of a particular given sequence. The given sequence could be that of a gene, allele, marker, etc. An example of a locus is 6p21.3 in cytogenetic nomenclature. This locus is for chromosome 6, short arm (p), region 2, band 1, subband 3. This is a specification for a position on a chromosome, not for what is actually found at that position. Note that the HL7 specs recognize several nomenclatures for specifying a locus.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="proband" lastEdit="2006-11-11T23:39:35"><label>Proband</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-11-11T23:39:35"><p>First affected family member coming to medlcal attention.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="consultand" lastEdit="2006-11-11T23:40:24"><label>Consultand</label><def domainid="POCG_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-11-11T23:40:24"><p>Individual (s) seeking genetic counseling/tetsing.</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

