<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPOCG" lastEdit="6/5/2008 10:35:18 AM" rendered="6/5/2008 10:36:28 AM"><header><title>Domain: Clinical Genomics</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="1"/><date>6/5/2008</date><authlist><author><role>Co-Chair, Facilitator &amp; Primary Contributor</role><name key="a1">Amnon Shabo (Shvo), Ph.D.</name><affiliation>IBM Research Lab in Haifa</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="shabo@il.ibm.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">shabo@il.ibm.com</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a12">Kevin S. Hughes, M.D., FACS</name><affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital, Partners HealthCare</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="KSHUGHES@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">KSHUGHES@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a13">Mollie Ullman-Cullere</name><affiliation>Harvard-Partners Center for Genetics and Genomics</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="MULLMANCULLERE@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">MULLMANCULLERE@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a14">Scott Whyte</name><affiliation>CGEY Health</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="scott.whyte@capgemini.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">scott.whyte@capgemini.com</email></author><author><role>Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a5">Usha Reddy, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>IBM Life Sciences</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="ushareddy@us.ibm.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">ushareddy@us.ibm.com</email></author><author><role>Modeling &amp; Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a51">Shosh Israel, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>Hadassah University Hospital</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="israels@hadassah.org.il" show="embed" actuate="auto">israels@hadassah.org.il</email></author><author><role>Publishing Facilitator</role><name key="a521">Grant Wood</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare Clinical Genetics Institute</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="grant.wood@intermountainmail.org" show="embed" actuate="auto">grant.wood@intermountainmail.org</email></author><author><role>Contributor and RCRIM liaison</role><name key="a522">Phil Pochon</name><affiliation>Covance</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="Phil.Pochon@covance.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">Phil.Pochon@covance.com</email></author><author><role>Modeling and Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a523">Perry Mar</name><affiliation>Partners HealthCare - Clinical Informatics Research and Development</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="PMAR@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">PMAR@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Modeling &amp; Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a524">Chuanbo Xu</name><affiliation>Perlegen</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="Chuanbo_Xu@perlegen.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">Chuanbo_Xu@perlegen.com</email></author><author><role>MnM Facilitator (retired)</role><name key="a525">Charlie Mead, MD MSc</name><affiliation>Booz Allen Hamilton</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a53">Pravat Das</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a54">Jennifer Fostel, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>NIH - National Center for Toxicogenomics</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a55">Brent Gendleman</name><affiliation>5AM Solutions</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a6">Rick Haddorff</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a7">Jim Holeman</name><affiliation>HP Nonstop Enterprise Division</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a91">Anajane Smith</name><affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a92">Derek Walker</name><affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a93">Sue-Jane Wang, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>US. Food and Drug Administration</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a935">Mathieu Wiepert</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a94">Katie Wittrup</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="spec-preface"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>The Clinical Genomics SIG has developed two topics - the Pedigree Topic (Family History), and the Genotype topic. The Pedigree Topic was approved by the membership as normative during the May 2007 ballot cycle and the final version is included in this Normative Edition. The Genotype topic has been approved as a DSTU. The second update to this DSTU passed ballot in January 2007 and is included in his Normative Edition. The Clinical Genomics roadmap is to progress the DSTU to normative in a step-wise approach starting with an implementation guide for genetic variation. The latter can be found in the Clinical Genomics Domain currently under ballot. The reader is encouraged to use the implementation guide because it is a further constraining of the DSTU models and provide more elaborated and accurate description of how the models can be used to represent genetic variation data. </p><p>Since its formation, the Clinical Genomics SIG has been developing
HL7 V3 standards to enable the exchange of interrelated clinical and personalized genomic data between interested parties. In many cases the exchange of genomic data is done between disparate organizations (healthcare providers, genetic labs, research facilities, etc.) and acceptable standards are crucial for the usefulness of genomic data in healthcare practice. It is envisioned that the use of genomic data in healthcare practice will become ubiquitous. Today, there are already several examples of the use of genomic data in healthcare and a few of them are presented in detail in the specifications' storyboards (e.g., Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, Pharmacogenomics and others use cases are presented briefly in the strategic direction of the SIG). These storyboards, unlike other ballot packages, are considered informative serving the purpose of illustrating the use of the Genotype models as the basic units of genomic data encapsulation. Indeed, the Genotype models (GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci) can be utilized by any group in HL7 that needs to convey genomic data. </p><p>The core Genotype model is the GeneticLocus model. It consists of various types of genomic data relating to a specific DNA locus including sequencing, expression and proteomic data. Within the GeneticLocus model we have utilized existing bioinformatics markups to represent raw data received from genomic facilities. Examining and constraining these markups is a work in progress and thus this part of the GeneticLocus model is
considered informative as well.     </p><p>The FamilyHistory model is aimed at describing a patient's pedigree with genomic data. Note that this model utilizes the GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci models (as CMETs) to carry the genomic data for the patient's relatives. The requirement for an elaborated Clinical Genomic Family History model has been identified while working on the BRCA (Breast Cancer) Storyboard. The Family History storyboard includes parts of the full BRCA storyboard as examples of how one might use the Family History model and interaction set.     </p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000010UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="POCG_HD000010UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000010UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="POCG_MT000010UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000010UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000050UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="POCG_HD000050UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000050UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="POCG_MT000050UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000050UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Family History" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000040UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-03-10T15:55:37"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p>The Clinical Genomics domain addresses requirements for the interrelation of clinical and genomic data at the individual level. Much of the genomic data is still generic, for example the human genome is in fact the DNA sequences believed to be the common sequences in every human being. The vision of 'personalized medicine' is based on those correlations that make use of personal genomic data such as the SNPs (Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms) that differentiate any two persons and occur about every thousand bases. Beside normal differences, health conditions such as drug sensitivities, allergies and others could be attributed to the individual SNPs or to differences in gene expression and proteomics.</p><p>The emphases the Clinical Genomics domain are the personalization of the genomic data and the 'intelligent' linking to relevant clinical information. These links are probably the main source from which geneticists (genomicists?) and clinicians could benefit. The cases where genomic data are used in healthcare practice vary in complexity and extent of the data used, since the current testing methods are still very expensive and not widely used. We can see simple testing like identifying genes and mutations as well as full sequencing of alleles and the use of micro-arrays to identify the expression of vast number of genes in each individual. Naturally, the Clinical Genomics SIG has been focusing on tests that are routinely done in healthcare, while preparing the information infrastructure standard for more futuristic cases.</p><p>At a first sight it seems that genomic data sets are yet another type of observations. While this is true of course, there are a few characteristics that might distinguish it from typical observations such as blood pressure or potassium level: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The amount of data: potentially it could be the entire human genome</p></item><item><p>The personalization of the data is evolving as new discoveries are constantly made</p></item><item><p>The complexity of the data: not only the DNA sequences (...AGCT...) need to be represented, but also SNPs, annotations (automatic and manual), gene expression, protein translation, and more</p></item><item><p>The emerging standard formats being used by bioinformatics communities, for example: BSML (Bioinformatic Sequence Markup Language), MAGE-ML ( Microarray and GeneExpression Markup Language)</p></item><item><p>Various standard organizations and many stakeholders are involved</p></item><item><p>The clinical-genomic correlations are represented in variety of different ways depending on the point of view (clinical research, pharmaceutical or healthcare)</p></item></list><p>The Clinical-Genomics SIG develops HL7 standards to enable the exchange between interested parties of the clinical and personalized genomic data. In many case the exchange of genomic data is done between disparate organization (providers, labs, research facilities, etc.) and acceptable standards are crucial for the usefulness of the data in healthcare practice. </p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="dmims-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><dmim identifier="POCG_DM000023UV" name="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" familiarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|CLINICAL GENOMICS DOMAIN INFORMATION MODEL" class="changed" lastEdit="2008-06-05T10:35:18"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_DM000023UV" name="Description" parent="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" id="desc-POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" lastEdit="2008-06-05T10:35:18"><p>The Clinical Genomics DIM is the result of our effort to look for the commonalities in each genomic-oriented storyboard that we have been working on (i.e., Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, BRCA and Pharmacogenomics). The first model we developed was called the Genotype model and it described a single locus on chromosomal or mitochondrial DNA. We then developed a model to describe a set of genetic loci and we now have two core models within the Genotype Topic: GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci. In parallel, we developed a Clinical Genomics Family History model. The DIM is an integration of these three models. For deatiled description of each class in the DIM, please refer to the respective walk through of each of the above-mentioned models. The trial use of this draft standard by its early adopters will guide the crystallization of this DIM into a more generic model for this domain.</p><p>In this ballot cycle we present two new models <emph role="strong">for comments only</emph>: (1) a genetic test order model is introduced at the end of the GeneticLoci model description (since it uses the GeneticLoci model as a CMET) and (2) a query model which is presented below. </p><p><emph role="strong">The Clinical Genomics Query Model:</emph></p><p>General:</p><p>HL7 V3 has a framework for domain-specific query models described in the following path of the V3 ballot package: Specifications Infrastructure / Messaging / Query Infrastructure. It states that the Query Infrastructure domain specifies the formation of information queries and the responses to these queries to meet the needs of healthcare applications using the HL7 version 3 messaging standard. In addition, the Query Infrastructure domain asserts that the variety of potential queries is almost unlimited and HL7 does not try to cover every possible query. Rather, the Query Standard provides general methods by which to structure query/response pairs. The technical committees responsible for functional domains apply these methods to develop specific query/response pairs for those domains' needs.</p><p>The Clinical Genomics Query Model:</p><p>The Clinical Genomics SIG develops a Query model based on the Query Infrastructure described above. It model is presented for the first time in the January 2007 ballot cycle - for comments only. The model is based on a query-by-parameter approach where the domain groups pick attributes in their domain and declares them to be parameters of the domain query, while constraining them if necessary. We picked a few central attributed from the GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci models and placed them as parameters in the Clinical Genomics Query model. The development is done step-wise and in the future we'll add parameters from the GeneticTestOrder model as well as the FamilyHistory model. </p><p>Query Interaction:</p><p>The basic interaction where a query message could be used is as follows: an application sends a query message to another application where certain parameters have been populated with data values. The receiving application parses the query message and uses the parameters with their assigned values to query its repository of HL7 Clinical Genomics messages or any other repository where there is a clear mapping between its data model and the HL7 Clinical Genomics models. All messages that meet the criteria set by the parameters and values will be returned to the sending application. Thus, the response is always a set of zero to many valid HL7 instances.</p><p>Note that an HL7 interaction where this message can be used has not been developed yet. So the model presented here for comments only is a static model. Nevertheless, it's encouraged to experiment with this model and simulate a query scenario in clinical genomics and see if at all it can meet the requirements or perhaps this query paradigm is too simplistic for the clinical genomics domain. </p><p>The figure below shows the Query model. </p><p><graphic alt="Draft of the Clinical Genomics Query model" source="T-POCG_RM000090.gif"></graphic></p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_DM000023UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Genotype Topic" familiarName="Genotype" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="01" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1"><storydivn identifier="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Storyboards" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="POCG_ST000020UV01" name="Genotype Cystic Fibrosis" familiarName="Cystic Fibrosis Genetic Testing" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="POCG_ST000020UV01-str" sortPrefix="01|CYSTIC FIBROSIS" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:14"><descriptive identifier="purp-POCG_ST000020UV01" name="Purpose" parent="POCG_ST000020UV01-str" id="purp-POCG_ST000020UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:14"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the request and report messaging as well as documents related to Cystic Fibrosis testing.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POCG_SN000020UV01" name="Genotype Cystic Fibrosis" familiarName="Cystic Fibrosis" parent="POCG_ST000020UV01-str" id="POCG_ST000020UV01-POCG_SN000020UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|CYSTIC FIBROSIS" baseClass="Genotype" lastEdit="2008-06-04T16:31:09" class="changed"><p><emph role="strong">Summary:</emph></p><list role="ordered"><item><p>Patient meets criteria for Cystic Fibrosis (CF) testing.</p></item><item><p>Informed consent signed.</p></item><item><p>Tests ordered.</p></item><item><p>Results received.</p></item><item><p>Results explained.</p></item><item><p>Plan drafted.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Detail:</emph></p><p>The patient's ethnicity, medical history, and/or family history (as documented in chart ) trigger the consideration of  genetic testing for CF mutations.  The CF test is explained to the patient (documented), the patient's questions are  answered (documented), and the informed consent is signed.  The doctor uses an electronic order entry system (same as  for other lab tests) to order CF testing (documented).  The lab system receives the order and forwards it to the  Molecular Genetics System (MGS).  A blood sample is drawn and sent to the Molecular Genetics Laboratory.  The test is  performed and results are provided by a lab technologist on a "worksheet".  The Molecular Laboratory's Genetic Counselor  reviews the results and the pertinent history and then creates a report in MGS including the reason for referral,  testing method, results, and interpretation (documented).  The results and report are reviewed by the Molecular  Laboratory Consultant and released. The report is sent from MGS to the lab system and also to the EMR system for viewing  by the doctor. The physician and patient discuss the test results (documented), and appropriate plans are outlined ( documented). </p><p><emph role="strong">Presentation:</emph></p><p>Pat Patient is being seen at Care Clinic by Dr. Doorman.  Dr. Doorman reviews Pat's EHR, ethnicity, medical history, and  family history and determines that Pat should be screened for Cystic Fibrosis mutations.  Dr. Doorman answers Pat's  questions and Pat signs an informed consent form. </p><p>Dr. Doorman orders a Cystic Fibrosis test through Orders Plus (Electronic Order Entry System).  Lab Plus receives the  order and forwards it to Molecular Genetics Plus (Molecular Genetics System). </p><p>Anita Nurse takes a blood sample from Pat and sends it to Molecular Lab Plus (Molecular Genetics Lab). </p><p>Molly Molecular (Lab Technologist) receives the blood specimen and the test order and performs the Cystic Fibrosis test.   She records the results on a worksheet. </p><p>Carla Counselor (Molecular Genetics Counselor) reviews the results and Pat's history and creates a report in Molecular  Genetics Plus. </p><p>Cory Consultant reviews Carla's work, makes any necessary modifications, and releases the report to Molecular Genetics  Plus and Lab Plus. </p><p>Dr. Doorman looks at Pat's results in the EHR.  Dr. Doorman and Pat meet to discuss the results and appropriate next  steps. </p><p><emph role="strong">Triggers:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Family history</p></item><item><p>Patient has a suspected diagnosis</p></item><item><p>Carrier screening (routinely offered to all pregnant couples)</p></item><item><p>Male infertility (CBAVD - Congenital Bilateral Absence of the Vas Deferens)</p></item><item><p>Ethnicity</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Data:</emph></p><list role="ordered"><item><p>Ethnicity, Medical history, and Family history risk factors.  Examples: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Positive sweat chloride test</p></item><item><p>Pulmonary and/or pancreatic symptoms</p></item><item><p>European ancestry</p></item><item><p>Affected family member</p></item></list></item><item><p>Informed consent document. </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Supplementary educational materials</p></item><item><p>Electronic patient signature</p></item></list></item><item><p>Lab order </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Orderable in formulary</p></item><item><p>Test prerequisites</p></item><item><p>Protocol/workflow</p></item></list></item><item><p>Lab result </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>33 mutations (greater than 900 documented mutations in the CF gene)</p></item><item><p>mutation name</p></item><item><p>location (specific exon or intron)</p></item><item><p>Interpretation with explanation, considering</p></item><item><p>reason for referral</p></item><item><p>ethnicity</p></item><item><p>family history</p></item></list></item></list><p>This storyboard is also supported by the following Domain Analysis Model in UML. 	<graphic source="T-POCG_NA000021.gif" alt="Domain Analysis Model (UML)"></graphic></p><p>Messages in this storyboard will be derived from models that refine other balloted models, most likely the Lab model (the refinement process is still a work in progress). The following bird's eye view of such a model is meant for illustration purposes only <emph role="strong">and is not part of the normative ballot.</emph> It demonstrates how the Genotype model fits into that model at the genomic data level based on the storyboard requirements:</p><p><graphic source="t-POCG_GR000024.gif" alt="Cystic Fibrosis Testing RMIM"></graphic> describes the Cystic Fibrosis storyboard requirements via an HL7 model which utilizes the Genotype model to convey genomic data at any level of granularity needed. </p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_ST000020UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="POCG_ST000030UV01" name="Genotype Pharmacogenomics" familiarName="Pharmacogenomics-Based Clinical Trial &amp; Submission" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="POCG_ST000030UV01-str" sortPrefix="01|PHARMACOGENOMICS" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:19"><descriptive identifier="purp-POCG_ST000030UV01" name="Purpose" parent="POCG_ST000030UV01-str" id="purp-POCG_ST000030UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:19"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the request and report messaging as well as documents related to Pharmacogenomics-based Clinical Trial &amp; submission.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POCG_SN000030UV01" name="Genotype Pharmacogenomics" familiarName="Pharmacogenomics" parent="POCG_ST000030UV01-str" id="POCG_ST000030UV01-POCG_SN000030UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|PHARMACOGENOMICS" baseClass="Genotype" lastEdit="2008-06-04T16:31:49" class="changed"><p><emph role="strong">Scenario Summary</emph></p><list role="ordered"><item><p>Clinical trial designs with pharmacogenomics components.</p></item><item><p>IRB approval.</p></item><item><p>Patient case report form (CRF) and informed consent form design.</p></item><item><p>Patient recruitment and DNA or tissue sample receiving.</p></item><item><p>Gene selection and variation markers discovery.</p></item><item><p>Regulation compliant clinical genotyping.</p></item><item><p>Clinical demographic, clinical phenotype, and lab test results received.</p></item><item><p>Haplotype or other types of marker assignment to the patients.</p></item><item><p>Statistical analysis to establish the association of the genetic markers to the clinical outcomes.</p></item><item><p>Validation study.</p></item><item><p>Reports generation and communicated between pharmaceutical and biotechnology partners, or submission materials  compiled for regulatory agencies.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Workflow And Process</emph></p><p>Clinical trials with a therapeutic product or device targeting to the global or niche pharmaceutical industry  area requires the understanding of the genetic structure of the potential patient population and its interaction with  the drug or treatment. Therefore the design of the trial involves the pharmacogenomics component. For example, the trial  has to consider the patient population in terms of geo-ethno background recruited into the trial and the other  covariates that stems from the genomics science. The sample size needs to be determined based on the understanding or  estimate of the gene variation markers in terms of the allele frequency (common vs. rare), genetic model (recessive vs.  dominant), and strength of the marker prediction power.
</p><p>As with any traditional types of trials, the pharmacogenomics based trials also need to obtain the regulatory  approval and the patient enrollment needs to follow the standard and GCP (good clinical practice) procedures, such as  using IRB approval of the design, obtaining patient consent forms for the genomics work, etc. The approved clinical  research centers could be used to collect the patient clinical data during the dosage dependent trials and the other  monitoring and diagnostics lab testing will be performed at the accredited labs. 
</p><p>Patient DNA samples extracted from the relevant tissues will be sent to the clinical regulatory compliant  genotyping facilities. Genotyping work will be applied to these DNA sample using the pharmacogenomics markers selected  for the trials. The genotype results will be sent to the data management databases of the trial and statistical analysis  will be performed to discover the associations between the genetics markers and the clinical outcomes and endpoints.
</p><p>The discovery results will be then compiled into the clinical trial reports that can be used for further drug  development. It can also be integrated into the submission packages used for the product application and approval to the  regulatory bodies.
</p><p><emph role="strong">Trigger Events</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p>DNA Banking from the previous trials advocates the use of genomics technology to profile the compound and  population.</p></item><item><p>Previous trials or market information indicates the divided responses in the target population to the class of  drugs or treatments.</p></item><item><p>Characterization of the drug target(s) reveals prevalence of the genetic variation in the gene or pathways  involved in the mode of action (MOA) of the drug or disease susceptibility or progression.</p></item><item><p>Ab initio trial with pharmacogenomics design.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Data</emph></p><list role="ordered"><item><p>Patient demographic and clinical observations as reported in CRF (case report form):
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Age.</p></item><item><p>Gender.</p></item><item><p>Ethnicity.</p></item><item><p>Geographic origins.</p></item><item><p>Dosage.</p></item><item><p>Confounding disease or drug usage.</p></item><item><p>Clinic visit observations: BMI, blood pressure, etc. depending on the therapeutic areas.</p></item></list></item><item><p>Informed consent document.
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Genetic testing education materials.</p></item><item><p>Electronic patient signature.</p></item></list></item><item><p>Lab test
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Test prerequisites.</p></item><item><p>Protocol/workflow</p></item><item><p>Test result.</p></item></list></item><item><p>Genomics data
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Selected genes
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Functional annotation of the genes.</p></item><item><p>Genomic structure</p></item><item><p>Transcript structure (optional)</p></item><item><p>Protein structure (optional)</p></item><item><p>SNPs</p></item><item><p>Haplotypes</p></item></list></item><item><p>Genotyping data
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Minimal SNP selection</p></item><item><p>SNP marker assay design</p></item><item><p>Assay validation and production </p></item><item><p>HapLocus building and haplotype assignments</p></item><item><p>Allele frequencies.</p></item></list></item></list></item><item><p>Association Analysis:
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Hypothesis generation: marker model (dominant vs. recessive), gene model (mono vs. multiple)</p></item><item><p>Statistics generation: marker raw p values, adjusted p values, odds ratios; regression, multiple comparison,  and permutations.</p></item><item><p>Marker quality control</p></item><item><p>Biological story building</p></item></list></item><item><p>Reports</p></item><item><p>Validation</p></item><item><p>Submission</p></item></list><p>The following HL7 model was developed after the above UML activity diagram and utilizes the Genotype model: </p><p><emph role="strong">IMPORTANT NOTE: The bird's eye view of the model is presented for illustration purposes only and is not part of the normative ballot. Its main purpose is to illustarte how the Genotype model fits into higher level models such as this.</emph></p><graphic source="T-POCG_GR000031.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Model Walk-Through</emph></p><p>The model is focused on genomic data in the clinical trial arena. It is important to note at this point that all parts of this model that are not related to genomic data could be replaced by models developed by the HL7 RCRIM TC (Regulated Clinical Research Information Management) that focuses on clinical trials at large. The 'non-genomic' parts of this model were developed for the sake of better understanding of the genomic-based processes (e.g., gene selection and haplotype discovery), and for completeness of the model that might make it more convenient to read. Both HL7 groups hold joint meetings and try to harmonize their models. A dedicated mechanism in HL7 for sharing parts of models across different groups (domains) is the CMET mechanism (Common Message Element Type). A CMET model is an HL7 model that can be incorporated into another model in a modular way. The key for using CMETs effectively is clean modularity. In the HL7 CG group we have been trying to develop a Genotype CMET - an atomic unit that could be plugged into any model that needs to convey genomic data. So, the Pharmacogenomics DIM model introduced here is in fact a prototyping framework in which we use the HL7 CG Genotype CMET on the one hand and on the other hand we strive to harmonize it with the HL7 RCRIM models (CDISC-based). </p><p>Having said that, we could start the walk-through of the Pharmacogenomics model:  The left side of the model has the main participants in this model, i.e., the sponsor (Pharma), the CRO and the Patient. There are 3 more participants I the model (Device, Collaborator and regulator) and they will be described further on. </p><list role="unordered"><item>At the upper left corner we can see the patient object and its related information. Note that this model follows the HL7 V3 RIM (Reference Information Model) core classes and associations. For example, we have a Person entity (green box) who plays the role (yellow box) of a Patient with participation (cyan box) of being the subject of the PahrmacogenomicsClinicalTrial Act.</item><item>At the middle left we can see the CRO recruiting patients - a process represented by the receiving the consent form for which the patient has the participation of legalAuthenticator. </item><item>At the lower left we can see the Pharma entity taking the role of ClinicalResearchSponsor which has the participation of Performer of the PharmacogenomicsTrialDesign act. </item></list><p>On the right side of the model and continuing to the bottom we can find the analysis and reporting process starting from the Pharmacogenomics trial results and its analysis, on to the CRO, and further to the sponsor. From there we can see the beginning of the submission process to the regulator with the validation and other necessary actions.</p><p>At the heart of the model we find the genomic acts, starting from the top where we can see the main act - the PharmacogenomicsClinicalTrial, associated with the PharmacogenomicsTesting act (which is an attempt to generalize the storyboard UML class called "Genotyping"). The PharmacogenomicsTesting act can have any number of the Genotype module (supposed to be a CMET), in two modes: </p><list role="unordered"><item>downward PharmacogenomicsTesting we see the component association with the Genotype module, where the actual genomic result data reside;</item><item>to the left of PharmacogenomicsTesting we can see an association with the GeneSelection act which is a fundamental part of a Pharmacogenomics clinical trial. To represent the genes that were selected we also use the Genotype module, but populate only the gene identifiers, while in the trial-result-Genotype-modules we can populate any part of the Genotype model (e.g., sequencing, gene expression, SNPs, haplotypes, etc.). </item></list><p>The PharmacogenomicsTesting is performed by a DNALab which is a role played by the Collaborator entity (these objects are shown to the right of the act). </p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_ST000030UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="POCG_ST000010UV01" name="Genotype Tissue Typing" familiarName="Tissue Typing Genetic Testing" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="POCG_ST000010UV01-str" sortPrefix="01|TISSUE TYPING" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:22"><descriptive identifier="purp-POCG_ST000010UV01" name="Purpose" parent="POCG_ST000010UV01-str" id="purp-POCG_ST000010UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:22"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the request and report messaging as well as documents related to tissue typing testing.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POCG_SN000010UV01" name="Genotype Tissue Typing" familiarName="Tissue Typing" parent="POCG_ST000010UV01-str" id="POCG_ST000010UV01-POCG_SN000010UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|TISSUE TYPING" baseClass="Genotype" lastEdit="2008-06-04T16:32:56" class="changed"><p><emph role="strong">Overview</emph></p><p>Over the last decade there is a shift in the routine of typing testing laboratories, from serological based HLA typing  to molecular based DNA techniques. With a greater understanding of the extent and relevance of HLA variability, there  has been a move towards increasingly higher levels of resolution in the tissue typing laboratory. DNA Typing relates to  a number of lab methods whose results allow DNA similarities of donor-recipient, familial relationships or any two  persons to be established for the purpose of transplantation of bone-marrow and organs, or in forensic scenarios.  It is  done by comparing the characteristic polymorphic patterns in the Human Leucocytes Antigens (HLA). The main facility for  using such methods is a tissue typing laboratory. </p><p>In most HLA typing applications, it is useful to have allele identification at higher levels of resolution. For  example, donor-recipient typing in transplant procedures, disease association or anthropology studies should all be  performed at the highest level of resolution that is practical. In cases of finding a donor for a patient who needs to  go through bone-marrow transplantation, the DNA typing results provide with better matching accuracy and might support  the prediction of GVH (graft-versus-host) disease after transplantation or GVM (Graft Versus Malignancy) effect in the  new trend called 'mini-transplant'. In forensic scenarios it is used in paternity disputes or to check evidences from  the crime scene against suspects' DNA. In forensic scenarios even lower resolution methods were accepted so far, but  given the new methods accuracy it's likely to see increasing demand for DNA typing data that better eliminate any doubt. </p><p>The information generated with direct DNA sequencing of HLA genes is qualitatively different than with other DNA- based typing methods. Obtaining the complete sequence of a gene of interest at the nucleotide level provides the  opportunity to assign allele typing at higher resolution. Sequencing-based typing is one of the latest technologies  applied to histocompatibility testing providing the highest level of definition and resolution in class I and II HLA  typing. DNA sequencing is now used in routine HLA typing through recent advances in automated DNA sequencers and  simplified sequencing chemistry. These advances have allowed greater sample throughput, providing a realistic,  practical, and preferred alternative to other DNA methods, while offering a far higher level of resolution. </p><p><emph role="strong">Triggers</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Tissue Typing for Organ and Bone-Marrow Transplantation</p></item><item><p>Identify people who may be at risk for certain autoimmune diseases</p></item><item><p>Forensic triggers: crime suspects; paternity test; anthropology studies; ethnic crimes</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Presentation </emph></p><p>Tina Transplant is referred to BMT (Bone Marrow Transplant) Center for transplant workup. Blood samples are drawn from Tina and her first degree relatives.  The samples are forwarded to the Tissue Typing Lab with the order.</p><p>Tissue Typing Lab performs Class I HLA testing.  Matches at Class I are further typed for Class II.  A matching analysis is prepared and the results report is returned to the ordering Center.</p><p>BMT Center evaluates results: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Best Outcome:  Match with First-Degree Relative(s) </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Matching relative approached for consent and donation. </p></item></list></item><item><p>Alternate Outcome:  No Match with First-Degree Relative(s), Distant Relatives Available </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>BMT Center determines whether typing of more distant relatives should be considered.  If marriages between relatives occurred, or Tina has common haplotypes, distant relatives may be approached for consent and sample.  BMT Center sends blood sample from distant relative to Tissue Typing Lab for Class I testing.  </p></item><item><p>Tissue Typing Lab identifies matches at Class I.  These matches are further typed for Class II.  A matching analysis is prepared and the results report is returned to the BMT Center for evaluation.   If an acceptable match is identified, relative is approached for consent and donation. </p></item></list></item><item><p>Alternate Outcome:  No Match with Relative(s), Unrelated Donor Needed </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>BMT Center identifies candidate Donor Bank(s) and sends Tina's typing data to Donor Bank. </p></item><item><p>Donor Bank searches for Class I (low-resolution) matches and returns match(es) to BMT Center for evaluation.  </p></item><item><p>BMT Center identifies best class I matches and requests DNA for those matches from Donor Bank.  </p></item><item><p>Donor Bank retrieves DNA samples and forwards to Tissue Typing Lab. </p></item><item><p>Tissue Typing Lab performs Class II typing.  Results are returned to BMT Center for evaluation. </p></item><item><p>If a promising match is found, BMT Center requests confirmatory test. </p></item><item><p>Donor Bank obtains new blood samples from potential donor and forwards to Tissue Typing Lab. </p></item><item><p>Tissue Typing Lab performs high-resolution Class I and Class II typing, and returns results to BMT Center. </p></item><item><p>BMT Center evaluations results and determines if suitable unrelated match has been identified.  If an acceptable match is found, the unrelated donor is approached by the Donor Bank for consent and donation. </p></item></list></item></list><p>Once donor has been identified and consented, BMT Center initiates pre-transplant preparatory regimen for Tina, and obtains marrow from donor. </p><p><emph role="strong">Data (for transplant patients)</emph></p><list role="ordered"><item><p>Complete medical and family history for the patients; emphasis on patients with special problems or treatments  such as: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Patients who need repeating transplant</p></item><item><p>Patients who are candidates for bone-marrow "mini-transplant"</p></item><item><p>Patients with diseases associated with HLA (e.g., multiple sclerosis)</p></item></list></item><item><p>Informed consent document </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Supplementary educational materials</p></item><item><p>Electronic patient signature</p></item></list></item><item><p>Lab order </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Orderable in formulary</p></item><item><p>Test prerequisites</p></item><item><p>Protocol/workflow</p></item></list></item><item><p>Lab result (for patient, donor, patient's mother and father if available) </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Class I allele sequences: HLA-A, HLA-B, HLA-C</p></item><item><p>Class II allele sequences: HLA-DP, HLA-DQ, HLA-DR</p></item><item><p>Interpretation with explanation</p></item><item><p>The extent of donor-recipient matching</p></item><item><p>The appropriateness of the previous result to the intended treatment (e.g., the new "mini-transplant" might  better succeed without full matching)</p></item><item><p>Annotation of sequences with interpretation details</p></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">IMPORTANT NOTE: The following model is presented for illustration purposes only and is not part of the normative ballot. Its main purpose is to illustarte how the Genotype model fits into higher level models such as this.</emph></p><p>This storyboard is also supported by the following Domain Analysis Model in UML. 	<graphic source="T-POCG_NA000011.gif" alt="Domain Analysis Model (UML)"></graphic></p><p>Messages in this storyboard will be derived from models that refine other balloted models such as the Lab model (the refinement process is still a work in progress). The following bird's eye views of such models are meant for illustration purposes only <emph role="strong">and are not part of the normative ballot.</emph> They demonstrate the modularity of HL7 models and how the Genotype model fits them at the genomic data level based on the storyboard requirements:</p><p><graphic source="T-POCG_GR000015.gif" alt="Bone-Marrow transplantation Tissue Typing RMIM"></graphic> describes the use of tissue typing in bone-marrow transplantation, while <graphic source="T-POCG_GR000016.gif" alt="Tissue Typing Observation RMIM"></graphic> describes a tissue typing observation and matching, used by any tissue typing-related scenario (organ transplantation, fatherhood, forensic, etc.) and it is the level at which the Genotype model is being utilized. </p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_ST000010UV01.gif"/></story></storydivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="POCG_RM000010UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLocus" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-15T00:10:26"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_RM000010UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" id="desc-POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2006-03-15T00:10:26">The GeneticLocus model describes data relating to a genetic locus, which we propose to be the basic unit of genomic information exchange in healthcare. This model is not meant to be a biological model; rather it is aimed at the needs of healthcare with the vision of personalized medicine in mind. Also it could facilitate the needs of clinical research conducted within the healthcare enterprises. It is the result of our effort to look for the commonalities in each genomic-oriented storyboard that we have been working on (i.e., Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, BRCA and Pharmacogenomics). Thus, this model contains a subset of the overall Clinical Genomics DIM as it focuses on a single locus. It appears as a CMET in both the Clinical Genomics DSTU as well as in the HL7 Common Domains so that every HL7 group that needs to convey high-resolution genomic data could utilize it . The Genetic Locus might be derived and further constrained by its main subject (e.g., human, animal, and viral) or by type of genomic data (e.g., DNA, Expression and Proteomics). The trial use of this draft standard will guide the derivation process in a way that is most useful to its early adopters.<p><emph role="strong">Genotype Scope and Modularity</emph></p><p>The Genotype model evolved from the work on several storyboards that involve genomic data: Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, BRCA, and Pharmacogenomics. For example, in the BMT -tissue typing storyboard we have identified three modules of information: the first one is about the messages and documents being exchanged in the BMT tissue-typing use case. The second one zooms in and describes in more detail the unique observations used in tissue-typing, i.e., the individual tissue-typing observation and the matching observation which indicates the level of matching between two individual tissue-typing observations (e.g., patient and donor). The rationale for this modularity is that the tissue-typing observation could be used in other use cases such as fatherhood testing and forensic cases. The third zoom-in is about the individual genotype that describes a pair of alleles from the same chromosomal locus and is the center of this document.     </p><p>Figure 1 describes the containment of the above-mentioned modules. It is expected that the genotype module will be plugged into other use cases such as genetic diagnostic and clinical trials.    The same design analysis was conducted with the other storyboards with the focus on making the Genotype module a shared model that can be then used in different messages that will be created to serve the unique business logic of each of the genomic-orient storyboards.    </p><p><graphic alt="Figure 1: Modularity in using the Genotype models" source="POCG_GR000001.gif"></graphic></p><emph role="strong">Main characteristics:</emph><list role="unordered"><item><p>The entry point to this model is a GeneticLocus observation which could be associated with a pair of alleles on paternal and maternal homologous chromosomes.</p></item><item>Core observations associated directly with each allele are Sequence, Sequence Variation and Expression. These core classes are also the ones which encapsulate raw genomic data.</item><item>In addition, sequence, sequence variation and expression data could be associated directly with the GeneticLocus observation if data is not available at the allelic level granularity.</item><item>In addition to the core classes, other classes hold extracted and derived data such certain types of variations, expression main results, references to as set of loci (e.g., a haplotype that this gene belongs to), and proteomics data (e.g., determinant peptides).</item><item>Both the GeneticLocus and IndividualAllele observations can recurse to represent relationships to genes/alleles from other loci (e.g., in a biological pathway).</item><item>The Sequence class could recurse as well to allow the representation of the translational path, i.e., DNA, RNA and Protein sequences, derived from each other.</item></list><p>The following figure show a bird's eye view of the GeneticLocus model:</p><p><graphic alt="Figure 2: A bird's eye view of the GeneticLocus model." source="GenotypeFocalAreas.gif"></graphic></p><p><emph role="strong">Model Walk-Through:</emph></p><p>Notes:</p><p>* The Use of the 'id', 'code' and 'value' Attributes in the Genotype Model:  </p><p>The use of these attributes in the various Genotype classes depends on the extent to which the data has being personalized and how different are the results from the known genome. It is also different in those classes that encapsulate raw genomic data.     For example, in the IndividualAllele class, in the case that the patient's allele was fully sequenced and found to be slightly different than the one registered in GenBank or other reference databases, there is no external code to place in one of those attributes, rather the IndividualAllele class is associated with the Sequence class where the individual sequence could be placed in the value attribute.     If it is a new allele indeed, temporary identifiers could be placed in the id attribute until it is registered externally. If, however, that is a known allele, then the 'value' attribute can be populated with the appropriate code from GenBank for example. In this case there isn't much point in populating the Sequence class as it can be retrieved from GenBank, but for self-containment purposes in a specific implementation, it could be that the GenBank sequence will be copied and placed in the Sequence class.     Overall, the 'id' attribute should be used to uniquely identifying that specific instance (possibly using the LSID format). The 'code' attribute should identify the kind of data stored in the 'value' attribute, and the 'value' attribute should hold actual data, for example, a genotype characteristic (e.g., heterozygous) or an external gene code from GenBank, dbSNP. In the 'encapsulating' classes (e.g., Sequence, Expression, etc.) the 'value' attribute should hold the bioinformatics markup itself. In the latter case, the code should hold an indication of the exact bioinformatics format used to populate the 'value' attribute.  </p><p>* Vocabulries</p><p>All vocabularies presented in the model walk-through below should be considered informative part of the this ballot document.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Entry Point and Locus/Gene/Allele Classes:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLocus</emph></p><p>Important note: The name 'GeneticLocus' refers to ALL genomic data and aspects of a specific locus along a chromosomal or mitochondrial DNA.      </p><p>The GeneticLocus class is the entry point of the GeneticLocus model. A genotype commonly stands for an allele pair - from paternal and maternal homologous chromosomes. However, in this model it could be that (1) only one allele is associated with the locus (in cases of insufficient data or interest in one allele only); (2) no alleles are associated with the locus in cases where the locus' alleles have not been determined but there is a need to represent data related to the locus such as expression data, variations and even sequences; and (3) multiple allele are available (in case of tumor tissues where several acquired (somatic) variants are encountered).</p><p><emph role="strong">GenotypeLocus Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="GenotypeLocusAttr.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 1: GenotypeLocus.code</emph></p><graphic source="GenotypeLocus.code.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 2: GenotypeLocus.value</emph></p><graphic source="GenotypeLocus.value.gif" alt=""></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">refrence</emph></p><p>The reference class represents a related gene that is on a different locus, and still has significant interrelation with the source gene (this is a  recursive association of GeneticLocus).    Note that it is possible to either expand the associations of the referred allele, or just indicate its id, assuming that it is detailed elsewhere (and accessible using its id).     The association class called reference has a typeCode attribute currently set to REFR but we are developing a new vocabulary with codes like FUNCTIONAL, PHYSICAL, SIGNALING, and METABOLIC_PATHWAY that will be described in subsequent ballot cycles.    </p></item><item><emph role="strong">AssociatedObservation</emph><p>The AssociatedObservation class associated with GeneticLocus  is a place holder for various observations related to a locus, for example, a Copy Number value that represents the number of copies of this gene or allele. The class has a shadow associated with the IndividualAllele class (see below). Both classes share the same vocabulary at this point but might be separated in future versions.   The code attribute holds the type of Observation, e.g., COPY_NUMBER and the value holds the actual result. Another example would be code=ZYGOSITY and value could then be either HOMOZYGOTE or HETEROZYGOTE. See tables 3&amp;4 for more possible codes.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Table 3: AssociatedObservation.code</emph></p><graphic source="LocusAssociatedObservation.code.gif"></graphic><p>Table 4 lists the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the value attribute. The abstract codes in this vocabulary are the codes from table 3 and thus these two vocabularies will be maintained in synch. </p><p><emph role="strong">Table 4: AssociatedObservation.value</emph></p><graphic source="LocusAssociatedObservation.value.gif"></graphic></item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">IndividualAllele</emph><p>Important note: The term 'Individual Allele' doesn't refer necessarily to a known variant of the gene, rather it refers to the patient data regarding the locus that might well contain personal variations (e.g., SNPs w/unknown-significance).</p><p>The GenotypeLocus class is associated with 0 to many alleles represented by the IndividualAllele class. The IndividualAllele class identifies the specific allele instance (using the id attribute) and optionally specifies its external code (if known) and the method by which it was identified. </p><p><emph role="strong">IndividualAllele Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="IndividualAlleleAttr.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 5: IndividualAllele.value:</emph></p><graphic source="IndividualAllele.value.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 6: IndividualAllele.methodCode:</emph></p><graphic source="IndividualAllele.methodCode.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AssociatedObservation (SHADOW )</emph></p><p>This is a shadow of the AssociatedObservation class. Please refer to the description above for more details about the use of this class.    </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">reference</emph></p><p>The reference class represents a related allele of a different locus, and still has significant interrelation with the source allele (this is a  recursive association of IndividualAllele). See the equivalent class in association with Genetic Locus for more details.         </p></item></list></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Encapsulating Classes</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Sequence </emph></p><p>The Sequence class is a generalization of all types of bio sequences (i.e., DNA, RNA, Protein) encapsulating the raw sequencing results of the DNA, and the derived sequences of the resultant RNA and protein molecules.  The Sequence class has a recursive relation that makes it possible to nest an RNA sequence within a DNA sequence, and a protein sequence within an RNA sequence. The relationship type is DRIV (derivation) as the nested Sequence classes are meant to be placeholders for sequences that were computed from the first Sequence class which is the only "encapsulating" class in this path (by 'first' we mean the one that is associated directly with the IndividualAllele class).   </p><p><emph role="strong">Sequence Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceAttr.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 7: Sequence.methodCode</emph></p><graphic source="Sequence.methodCode.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AssociatedProperty</emph></p><p>The AssociatedProperty class is a placeholder for various properties that relate to the sequence data, which are supposed to be extracted (bubbled-up) from the raw expression data encapsulated in the Sequence class. This class is basically a code-value pair allowing the association of multiple properties with the core sequence class which sets the context of these property observations in terms of identification and time for example. See discussion about the differences between associated observations versus properties further on. Table 8 lists the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the code attribute while table 9 lists the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the value attribute. The two vocabularies are synchronized in the sense that table 8 codes are the abstract codes in table 9 and each of them defines the vocabulary (nested within the abstract code) used when that abstract code was selected to populate the code attribute.</p><p><emph role="strong">Table 8: SequenceProperty.code</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceProperty.code.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 9: SequenceProperty.value</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceProperty.value.gif"></graphic></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">SequenceVariation</emph></p><p>The class SequenceVariation is a generalization of all variation types, i.e., in all molecules (DNA, RNA, Protein) and of all types within each molecule (e.g., in DNA: SNP, Mutation, etc.). Note: This class replaces the Polymorphism hierarchy in previous versions.</p><p><emph role="strong">SequenceVariation Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceVariationAttr.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 10: SequenceVariation.interpretationCode</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceVariation.interpretationCode.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AssociateProperty</emph></p><p>The class AssociatedProperty is a place holder for various properties that relate to a sequence variation, for example, position, length, region, reference and more. It replaces the distinct observations we had in previous versions of the Genotype model. This class is basically a code-value pair allowing the association of multiple properties with the core variation class which sets the context of these property observations in terms of identification and time for example. See discussion about the differences between associated observations versus properties further on. Table 11 list the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the code attribute while table 12 lists the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the value attribute. The two vocabularies are synchronized in the sense that table 11 codes are the abstract codes in table 12 and each of them defines the vocabulary (nested within the abstract code) used when that abstract code was selected to populate the code attribute.</p><p><emph role="strong">Table 11: SequenceVariationProperty.code</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceVariationProperty.code.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 12: SequenceVariationProperty.value</emph></p><graphic source="SequenceVariationProperty.value.gif"></graphic></item><item><p><emph role="strong">TagSNP</emph></p><p>The characteristic of a SNP as a 'Tag SNP' is one of the SequenceVariation properties and thus was removed from this version of the model and was added to the vocabulary.</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Expression</emph></p><p>The class Expression is a generalization of all types of expression data (RNA and protein). Its code attribute identifies the type of expression data it carries. This class is one of the Genotype's encapsulating classes, that is, it holds in its value attribute portions of relevant bioinformatics markup (e.g., MAGE-ML for gene expression data), complying with constrained schemas of the full-fledged markups. In such a case, the code attribute holds the exact reference to the contained bioinformatics schema which the value's content should comply with. Note that the association cardinality between this class and its source class IndividualAllele is zero to many. The idea here is to be able to represent gene expression over multiple experiments for the same allele under perhaps differing clinical environments and with differing expression. If this association is traversed several times then it's important to populate the id &amp; effectiveTime attributes so that each object of that class will be distinguished clearly and identified uniquely. </p><p><emph role="strong">Expression Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="ExpressionAttr.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AssociatedProperty</emph></p><p>The AssociatedProperty class is a place holder for various properties that relate to expression data, for example, normalized intensity, qualitative indication, p-value and more, which are supposed to be extracted (bubbled-up) from the raw expression data encapsulated in the Expression class. The AssociatedProperty class replaces the distinct observations we had in previous versions of the model. This class is basically a code-value pair allowing the association of multiple properties with the core expression class which sets the context of these property observations in terms of identification and time for example. See discussion about the differences between associated observations versus properties further on. Table 13 list the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the code attribute while table 14 list the vocabulary from which codes are drawn to populate the value attribute. The two vocabularies are synchronized in the sense that table 13 codes are the abstract codes in table 14 and each of them defines the vocabulary (nested within the abstract code) used when that abstract code was selected to populate the code attribute.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Table 13: ExpressionProperty.code</emph></p><graphic source="ExpressionProperty.code.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 14: ExpressionProperty.value</emph></p><graphic source="ExpressionProperty.value.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Table 15: ExpressionProperty.methodCode</emph></p><graphic source="ExpressionProperty.methodCode.gif"></graphic></item></list></item></list></item><item><p>Other Classes and Proteomics</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLoci</emph></p><p>The Haplotype class was replaced by the GeneticLoci class which is a generalization of a haplotype and other sets of loci. The class could carry essential data about the loci or just hold an id of Genetic Loci instance complying with the HL7 Clinical Genomics Genetic Loci model (see further on in this document).</p><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLoci Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="HaplotypeAttr.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Translocation</emph></p><p>This class was removed and the term was added to the vocabulary of the AssociatedProperty class associated with the SequenceVariation class.</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Polypeptide and DeterminantPeptide</emph></p><p>The Sequence class could be associated with its resulted or corresponding polypeptides (represented by the Polypeptide class) as well as with the determinant peptides  (represented by the DeterminantPeptide class). Note that the Sequence class has a recursive relation and it is possible to nest an RNA sequence within a DNA sequence, and a protein sequence within an RNA sequence. The Polypeptide could then be associated with the protein sequences or directly with any of the above levels. Also, it is possible to associate the DeterminantPeptide with the Polypeptide class or directly with the Sequence class. Both classes (Polypeptide and DeterminantPeptide) could be associated with several instances of the ClinicalPhenotype classes.     </p><p>The proteomics classes in this model represent protein data that one is deriving from the sequences (by means of computational biology) and is not measuring directly in the subject. The latter could be represented as regular lab results (using the HL7 Lab specs), which could be referenced in the GeneticLocus instance as if they were phenotype observations.     </p><p>A common case for the use of proteomics in this model could be as follows: Checking whether an amino acid change would result from the variant; if so - whether the new amino acid change is to an amino acid of a different size or charge state that would likely change the shape of the active region of the protein; how far the change is from the active site; whether the change is in a regulator region, and so forth. These observations could then be associated to phenotypic data. </p><p>For example, consider the following case described in OMIM:  "Despite the dramatic responses to EGFR inhibitors in patients with non-small cell lung cancer, most patients ultimately have a relapse. Kobayashi et al. (2005) reported a patient with EGFR-mutant, gefitinib-responsive, advanced non-small cell lung cancer who had a relapse after 2 years of complete remission during treatment with gefitinib. The DNA sequence of the EGFR gene in his tumor biopsy specimen at relapse revealed the presence of a second mutation {131550.0006}. Structural modeling and biochemical studies showed that this second mutation led to the gefitinib resistance." (OMIM *131550)    </p><p><emph role="strong">Polypeptide and DeterminantPeptide Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="PolypeptideAttr.gif"></graphic></item></list></item><item><p>To Phenotype and Beyond...</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">ClinicalPhenotype</emph></p><p>The 'wrapper' class ClinicalPhenotype is associated with the SequenceVariation class and includes a choice of populating an ObservedClinicalPhenotype class internally (i.e., within the Genotype instance), externally (ExternalObservedClinicalPhenotype) or pointing to a KnownClinicalPhenotype. Note that this class is just a 'warpper' (i.e., classCode = "ActContainer") of the actual phenotypes and thus has no attributes of its own.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">ExternalObservedClinicalPhenotype</emph></p><p>The difference between ObservedClinicalPhenotype and ExternalObservedClinicalPhenotype is that the former represents a phenotype that the genomic data creator chose to include within the genotype instance itself, while the latter represents a phenotype that exists externally to the genotype instance, for example residing in the patient record's problem list. This class has an id  (mandatory attribute) that serves as a pointer to the target observation.  Note that the typeCode attribute is set to ActRelationshipExternalReference domain which is an "x_" value set  dedicated to representing types of external references. For example, it could be set to "XCRPT" which means that the source observation is an excerpt from the target observation. In our case, this could be used when you might want to refer to a clinical observation in a patient's medical record, but also would like to show a few of its essential data items in the GeneticLocus instance (in the ClinicalPhenotype object).</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">KnownClinicalPhenotype</emph></p><p>The difference between KnownClinicalPhenotype and ObservedClinicalPhenotype is that while observed phenotype means a phenotype that was observed in the patient, KnownClinicalPhenotype is in fact a piece od knowledge, i.e., it is known to be associated with the genomic data but not necessarily in this specifc patient to whom the genomic data belongs. The class KnownClinicalPhenotype has a definitional mood (i.e., taken from or pointing to a description of such a disease in some form of a master file, ontology, lookup table, etc., separated from the patient data) to reflect the difference from the event mood of the ObservedClinicalPhenotype class.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">pertinentInformation</emph></p><p>This ActRelationship class (named pertinentInformation) represents the association of a genomic observation with a number of phenotype (clinical) observations. Its mandatory attribute typeCode holds the semantics of what is the type of this association. It is defined as &lt;=PERT which means that any code in the PERT sub-hierarchy of the HL7 ActRelationshipType Vocabulary is permitted here. For a full list of these codes, please refer to the Vocabulary chapter in the HL7 V3 Ballot Package. Appendix E lists codes from all branches of the ActRelationshipType Vocabulary (PERT and others) that seem possible candidates for use in Clinical Genomics. This work is still under progress and we might propose this list as well as our own codes to be a new x_domain in ActRelationshipType Vocabulary. </p></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Miscellaneous Issues</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Association types: </emph></p><p>Association types (ActRelationship typeCode) are consistent with the following principles:</p><list role="unordered"><item>Encapsulating classes are components (COMP typeCode) of the IndividualAllele and GeneticLocus classes, while... </item><item>Bubbled-up classes are derivations (DRIV typeCode) of encapsulating classes; </item><item>Clinical phenotypes are pertinent to (PERT typeCode) genomic classes (Note: in previous versions this was fixed to "caused by" but it was too restricted. The code CAUS is part of the PERT sub-vocabulary and thus could be still used, but other codes are available as well)</item><item>Non patient-specific data items are defined (INST typeCode) by classes with mood code = DEF (definitional), that is, defined and described outside of the patient medical records, in some kind of master file, dictionary , ontology, etc.;   </item><item>Alleles in one GeneticLocus refer (REFR typeCode) to alleles in another locus. Nevertheless, we develop a vocabulary for such types of relationship, which will be proposed for RIM harmonization as a new domain in ActRelationshipType Vocabulary (see table 16 for a first draft).   </item></list><p><emph role="strong">Table 16: reference.typeCode</emph></p><graphic source="reference.typeCode.gif"></graphic></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Observation Interpretation vs. Observation Relationships:</emph></p><p>There is a subtle distinction between observation interpretation codes and ActRelationship types between genomic and clinical observations. The observation interpretation is in fact a piece of knowledge, not necessarily shown as phenotypes of that genotype in the patient. If the interpretation code is DELETERIOUS (see table 8) then the observation could be complemented by associating it to the KnownAssociatedDisease class which is also a non-patient specific data in DEF mood Code. In contrast, the phenotype is an actual observation valid for this patient, which is associated with a genomic observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Bioinformatics formats:</emph></p><p>In general, we use bioinformatics formats in the Genotype model to feature the encapsulation of raw genomic data such as sequencing, expression and proteomic data. To enable the embedding of such data accepted from labs that work with bioinformatics formats, it is possible to assign specific XML portions into the Sequence and Expression value attributes (as well as into SequenceVariation). This encapsulation of 'foreign' markup is made possible due to the use of the HL7 ED (Encapsulating Data) Data Type which is defined as follows:  "ED holds data that is primarily intended for human interpretation or for further machine processing which is outside the scope of HL7.  ED includes unformatted or formatted written language, multimedia data, or structured information as defined by a different standard (e.g., XML-signatures.)"    </p><p>The use of the XML bioinformatics markups is restricted, that is, not all tags are allowed, rather only a subset which relates to a specific patient and include the information pertinent to healthcare. The restrictions on those external XML standards are specified elsewhere but a draft of a constrained BSML schema for sequencing data is presented in Appendix C.  For more details about the rationale behind this mixture of HL7 and bioinformatics markup, see the section "Coexistence of HL7 Classes and Bioinformatics Markup".    </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Validation:</emph></p><p>The use of external markup in HL7 messages requires that a receiver of an HL7 instance that contains a Genotype instance, will carry out a 'double-validation' process: first step is to validate the instance against the HL7 message specification (of which the Genotype schema is part of) and the second phase is to validate the content of those value attributes against their respective content models. The valid content models of the Sequence and Expression value attributes will be an integral part of the entire Genotype specification, but at this point it is still considered informative. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Associated Properties / Observations and the Harmonization Proposals:</emph></p><p>In previous versions we have coped with the reluctance of both the HL7 RIM Harmonization process and the HL7 Clinical Genomics group to nail down common attributes of genomic observations by adding new classes and attributes to the RIM, by elaborating on the SequenceVariation and Expression properties and creating two new Observation classes (SequenceVariationProperty and ExpressionProperty) to be placeholders for each of theses properties. For example, the proposed 'length' property of a possible SequenceVariation new RIM class could be represented by an object of the SequenceVariationProperty class which only has code and value attributes. The code will indicate that this observation describes the position of the variation and the value attribute holds the position itself. The assumption is that this observation is an integral part of the parent observation with the same effective time. It could be identified only by going through the source variation object. In contrast, we also had the LocusAssociatedObservation class which is a place holder for associated observations such as copy number, zygosity, dominancy and gene family. These observations are independent observations that do have an id, effective time and method code.     </p><p>In this update #1 of the approved DSTU, the associated properties/observation classes were consolidated to two classes: AssociatedProperty and AssociatedObservation. Instead of having specific class names (e.g., SequenceVariationProperty), all core classes now have these two generic classes coming off them. It makes the model simpler (but put the burden on the parsing to understand the context of each associated property/observation).     The basic difference between associated properties and associated observations is that an associated property should have been (and eventually may be) part of the parent class attributes. It's an inherent part of the parent observation and thus doesn't have id, time stamp, method, performer, etc. They 'inherent' all these attributes from their parent. An associated observation, in contrast, is an independent observation and a component of its parent class.   </p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Coexistence of HL7 Objects and Bioinformatics Markup:</emph></p><p>When exploring the Genotype model one could identify the use of bioinformatics markup such as MAGE for gene expression and BSML for DNA sequencing. Also, a few of the HL7 Classes such as the property classes are overlapping the elements of the bioinformatics markup in a way that it is possible to find a SNP represented in both the Sequence class as well as in the SequenceVariationProperty class. The question then arises, what are the relationships of the two and how do they coexist? The following are a few points to note about that issue:</p><list role="unordered"><item>HL7 mission is to develop message/document specs that will be used in healthcare practice. The mission of the HL7 Clinical Genomics SIG is to develop message/document specs where genomic data are involved (e.g., Tissue Typing, Genetic Testing, and Clinical Trials).</item><item>Bioinformatics communities develop models/markups and are usually not ANSI-Accredited SDOs and thus cannot sanction and maintain these formats. Naturally, their orientation is more towards research and the needs of information exchange between research facilities, data mining and statistical analysis tools.</item><item>The HL7 Clinical Genomics SIG attempts to constrain existing bioinformatics markups and embed them in the HL7 model. This effort brings up the issue of overlapping between the HL7 core Reference Information Model (RIM) classes &amp; data types from which we derive the Genotype model and embedded bioinformatics markups. One approach is not allowing overlaps. For example, if we model a SNP in an HL7 class, and also allow BSML extractions to be embedded in the Sequence class, then we should constrain the BSML extractions so that it will not hold SNP data (in the Isoform tag), rather those parts of the BSML (if exist) should be transformed and moved to HL7 classes.</item><item>Another approach is seeing the overlap as beneficial: The bioinformatics markups are kind of raw data that might not always get into the HL7 Clinical Genomics actual instances, rather might be only referenced from the HL7 instance as supporting evidences. When it does get into an HL7 instance then we have a blend of HL7 classes and embedded genomic markup. This situation is analogous to the raw imaging data. The average referring physician doesn't dig into the dozens of CT images taken in a study, rather look at the already designated ROIs or just read the radiologist report.</item><item>A similar situation might exist in the Clinical Genomics specification: many clinicians might not be able to grasp the raw genomic data represented in the bioinformatics markup but it could be helpful to have parts of it in the HL7 instances for purposes like evidence availably and machine-processabilty. The HL7 classes should be seen as representing the digest of the raw genomic data which is most pertinent to the healthcare practice itself. There is a space here for applications that might parse the bioinformatics markup, intelligently populate the HL7 classes and then associate them with the appropriate clinical data.</item><item>The HL7 classes in the Genotype model have the advantage of being better tied with the other HL7 classes in the patient record (e.g., in a problem/allergy list) and thus serves better the ability to link individual genomic data to the clinical data of that individual.  Note that bioinformatics models also include clinical data so this poses an overlapping problem in the other direction.</item><item>The integration applications that recognize bioinformatics markups could integrate various genomic sources into healthcare standards used for patient care, so there will not be one winning format necessarily. The issue should not be which bioinformatics model is the "best fit with HL7 Reference Information Model", rather, how could we develop mechanisms to digest data in various representations and link them to the HL7 RIM for the benefit of personalized medicine.</item><item>For example, the BSML markup is fairly simple and the HL7 SIG has done some work on BSML in constraining it to be embedded in HL7 classes. XML samples are available to show how the BSML is embedded in an HL7 message of the tissue typing use case. The constraining process of BSML made sure that data items related to presentation elements are not included and that the instance includes one and only one patient's data and this patient is uniquely identified. In contrast, PharmaGKB has a repository orientation like GenBank with actual data available for retrieval. This could be a data source of generic knowledge that can be accessed by healthcare information systems. In HL7 these repositories are usually treated as controlled coding schemes. They need to be recognized by the HL7 Vocabulary Committee and then any HL7 instance can reference terms, identifiers and data from that taxonomy.</item></list><p>Figure 3 shows a conceptual workflow where the above co-existence takes place and executed step-wise. Figure 4 shows an example taken form the sequencing type of data: the most clinically-significant SNPs are bubbled-up from the raw sequencing data and being associated with clinical phenotypes. For illustration of the latter scenario, see sample on the EGRF (described in the samples appendix B), courtesy of the NHANES project carried out in the USA CDC.<graphic alt="Figure 3: Bubbling up the most clinically-significant portions of the raw genomic data embedded in the encapsulating objects." source="POCG_GR000002.gif"></graphic></p><p><graphic alt="Figure 4: Bubbling up the most clinically-significant SNPs of the raw sequencing data embedded in the encapsulating objects." source="POCG_GR000003.gif"></graphic></p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="POCG_DO000000UV"/><diagref ref="POCG_RM000010UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="POCG_HD000010UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000010UV01"/></rmim><rmim identifier="POCG_RM000050UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLoci" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-19T13:35:55"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_RM000050UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" id="desc-POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2006-11-19T13:35:55">The GeneticLoci model allows the representation of data relating to a set of loci along the DNA material. The set of loci could be of differnet types, for example, a haplotype (allele or SNP), a genetic profile, a biological pathway, a set of genetic test results which contains results of multiple genes, etc. The Genetic Loci model utlizes the Genetic Locus model as a CMET.<p><emph role="strong">Model Walk-Through:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Entry Point and Locus/Gene/Allele Classes:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLoci</emph></p><p>The entry point is a GeneticLoci class allowing the representation of the type of this loci group (e.g., allele haplotype like in tissue typing of HLA antigens) and an optional code for identifying the loci set (if available).</p><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLoci Attributes:</emph></p><graphic source="GeneticLociAttr.gif"></graphic><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">LociChoice</emph></p><p>A GeneticLoci instance consists of zero to many GeneticLocus CMETs or other GeneticLoci classes. This recursive structure allows the representation of a complex set of genetic loci as comprised of 'sub' genetic loci sets. The actual genetic/genomic data is represented through GeneticLocus instances at any level of nesting required.   </p></item><item><emph role="strong">AssociatedObservation</emph><p>The AssociatedObservation class associated with GeneticLoci  is a place holder for various observations related to the set of loci that have been observed independently of the parent observation. This is a generic catcher for data that can be placed in any other class in this model. Population of the code &amp; value attributes of this class is controlled by a vocabulary which is still under development.   </p></item><item><emph role="strong">Interpretation</emph><p>In cases where there is an interpretation to the entire set of loci data, it is possible to use the interpretationCode attribute of the GeneticLoci class or populate the associated phenotypes (the phenotype model is identical to that in the GeneticLocus model and might be packaged as an internal CMET for better modularity).</p></item><item><emph role="strong">Raw genomic data and the value attribute:</emph><p>While the value attribute typically holds a common code of this set of loci, it can also hold raw genomic data for the entire set of loci. For example, if the set of loci is a gene expression assay, the value attribute can hold the part of the MAGE-ML xml that holds data on all loci. </p></item></list></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Other Classes</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">GeneticReportDocument </emph></p><p>A report document that summarizes the data of a genetic loci set could be associated with the GeneticLoci class and is of type DOCCLIN which represents in HL7 a CDA type (Clinical Document Architecture). It is possible to actually embed an entire CDA document in the text attribute of the GeneticReportDocument class or just point to this document through the id attribute. Other related reports (e.g., follow-up's, addenda) could be associated as well. For more details about the use of clinical documents, please refer to the CDA and the Medical Records specification in the HL7 V3 Ballot Package.   </p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">sequelTo</emph></p><p>This is a recursive association to the GeneticReportDocument class, which allows the representation of several documents that relate to one another and to the Genetic loci of course. For example, an addendum or follow-up document to the first summary. </p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Participants</emph></p><p>In general, a group of optional participants are associated with both the GeneticLoci and the GeneticTestOrder classes allowing the recording of participants of the order act as well as the results fulfilling that order:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">recordTarget</emph></p><p>The record target indicates whose medical record holds the documentation of this act (i.e., the order or the results). This is especially important when the subject of a service is not the patient himself. Note that the subject can be overridden in certain GeneticLocus instances. This could be useful when describing for example genomic data relating to various specimens (healthy and tumor tissues) or relating to virus, as part of a genetic testing of a patient who carries this virus.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">author</emph></p><p>Author of the data.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">performer</emph></p><p>Performer of the observations.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">verifier</emph></p><p>Verifier of the observations.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">informationRecipient</emph></p><p>To whom the data should be sent.</p></item></list></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">The GeneticTestOrder model (for comments only)</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">General:</emph></p><p>The GeneticLoci class might be representing a fulfillment of a test order. For that purpose we work with the HL7 Lab SIG to see how our models could be embedded in their messages. Nevertheless, the new GeneticTestOrder model (presented here for comments only at this point) is an attempt to 'roll-out' the Lab order model and take those classes that we need. In addition it serves as a 'gap analysis' to see if the Lab model can accommodate all the genetic testing requirements. In cases where gaps encountered, there are additions to this model whose origins cannot found in the Lab model. </p><p>Therefore, this model serves our dialog with the Lab SIG, as well as a starting point for a generic implementation guide on how to use the Lab model for genetic testing purposes. It could be that this model will be balloted in future ballot cycles, depending on feedback we get from ballotters, early adopters and other stakeholders.   </p><p><emph role="strong">GeneticTestOrder class:</emph></p><p>
The entry point is a GeneticTestOrder class allowing the representation of a genetic test order. It's an observation in RQO (Request) mood code. It is (or may be) fulfilled by zero to many GeneticLoci CMETs (see below for further description on how to represent the result of this order). As aforementioned, this class and its associations are also a "roll-out" of the ObservationRequest class in the A_PlacerOrder CMET of the HL7 Lab Result model.
</p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes of the GeneticTestOrder class</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item>id: Instance identifier used to uniquely identify the GeneticTestOrder instance.</item><item>Code: The GeneticTestOrder.code attribute can hold a code denoting the type of test, for example - an HLA haplotype or a genes panel for a specific disease, etc.</item><item>text: Free-text description, including a reference mechanism.</item><item>effectiveTime: Time at which the genetic test was ordered.</item><item>confidentialityCode: A code that controls the disclosure of information about this genetic test order. Vocabulary- The HL7 Vocabulary "Confidentiality" with possible extensions from the Clinical Genomics group (TBD).</item><item>reasonCode: A code specifying the motivation, cause, or rationale of the ordering this genetic test.</item><item>statusCode	The status of this genetic test order. Based on the HL7 Vocabulary "ActStatus" with possible extensions from the Clinical Genomics group (TBD).</item><item>methodCode: The method(s) by which this genetic test should be performed (note - this is optional and even if exists - doesn't necessarily imply the actual method used (which is conveyed through the results in the GeneticLoci and GeneticLocus instances). Vocabulary- the HL7 Vocabulary "ObservationMethod" with possible extensions from the Clinical Genomics group (TBD).</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Associations</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">GeneticLoci CMET:</emph></p><p>
The GeneticLoci CMET itself can be in request or event mood. If it's in request mood, it serves the representation of requested observation, e.g., the test order is about requesting to find specific sequence variations in certain genes. If it's in event mood, then it represents the actual findings/results of the genetic testing.
</p></item><item><p>In general, there are four types of data that can be associated with the test order and they are represented by the following association classes coming off the GeneticTestOrder class:  </p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">component</emph></p><p>This is a recursive association back to GeneticTestOrder to allow the representation of '-sub-orders' as components of a complex order.  </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">sequelTo</emph></p><p>This is a recursive association back to GeneticTestOrder, allowing representation of reflex genetic tests.
</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">definition</emph></p><p>This association connects the order to a master service catalog for elaboration on further details of the ordered test.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">pertinentInformation</emph></p><p>This association connects to the A_SupportingClinicalInformation CMET, which allows the representation of patient specific data that is important to accompany the test order. This CMET might be replaced by the Clinical Statement model, under development in HL7.</p></item></list></item></list><p><graphic alt="Figure 1: Draft of the GeneticTestOrder Model" source="POCG_RM000060.gif"></graphic></p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="POCG_DO000000UV"/><diagref ref="POCG_RM000050UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="POCG_HD000050UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000050UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="POCG_HD000010UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLocus" parent="POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" id="POCG_HD000010UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:38:38"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_HD000010UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_RM000010UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000010UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="POCG_MT000010UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000010UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="POCG_HD000050UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLoci" parent="POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" id="POCG_HD000050UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:57:29"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_HD000050UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_RM000050UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000050UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="POCG_MT000050UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000050UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic" id="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Genotype-ic"><msgtype identifier="POCG_MT000010UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLocus" parent="POCG_HD000010UV01-hmd" id="POCG_MT000010UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:39:20"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_MT000010UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="POCG_HD000010UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLocus" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000010UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="POCG_MT000050UV01" name="Genotype Event" familiarName="GeneticLoci" parent="POCG_HD000050UV01-hmd" id="POCG_MT000050UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|20|99|" baseClass="Genotype" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:57:43"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_MT000050UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="POCG_HD000050UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Genotype Event" refFamiliarName="GeneticLoci" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000050UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn></subdivn><subdivn identifier="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Pedigree Topic" familiarName="Pedigree" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="02" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><storydivn identifier="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Storyboards" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="POCG_ST000040UV01" name="Pedigree Family History" familiarName="Family History" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" sortPrefix="02|FAMILY HISTORY" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:27"><descriptive identifier="purp-POCG_ST000040UV01" name="Purpose" parent="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" id="purp-POCG_ST000040UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:27"><p>The objective of this storyboard is to illustrate the way a patient's pedigree with clinical and genomic data could be represented for risk analysis purposes in the context of breast and ovarian cancers and other diseases. The initial context for this storyboard was set by the BRCA storyboard which is still under development. The UML Activity Diagram below as well as the Presentation section further on are taken from the BRCA storyboard, illustrating the use of family history data in this case.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POCG_SN000040UV01" name="Genotype Family History" familiarName="Family History" parent="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" id="POCG_ST000040UV01-POCG_SN000040UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="02|FAMILY HISTORY" baseClass="Pedigree" lastEdit="2008-06-04T16:50:43" class="changed"><p><emph role="strong">Summary</emph></p><p>The Family History storyboard and its HL7 Pedigree Model is part of the HL7 Clinical-Genomics SIG effort to design various higher-level models of using genomic data in healthcare practice, that utilize the basic model of a Genotype (described at this point as the Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model). The need to represent a patient's pedigree information as associated with clinical and genomic data was introduced in the BRCA (Breast Cancer) storyboard which is still under development.</p><p>The BRCA storyboard includes a sample outline for the way the patient's pedigree should look:</p><graphic source="FMsampleData.gif"></graphic><p>Populating the above outline with actual data might result in a spreadsheet found in the following link:</p><graphic source="T-FMsampleDataSheet.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Presentation</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman has a family history of breast and ovarian cancer, and she is not of Ashkenazi Jewish descent.</item><item>She believes she is at high risk of developing breast cancer.</item><item>She goes to see her clinician (Medical oncologist, surgical oncologist , radiation oncologist, primary care provider) who takes a thorough family history.  This history is recorded in the chart and the electronic medical record.</item><item>The clinician reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The clinician thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares her Family History to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO, see http://www.isds.duke.edu/~gp/brcapro.html).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Her risk of a mutation is 25%, because her father's 4 sisters had ovarian caner.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk of having a mutation, and this information is given to her.</item><item>She is referred to a Risk Clinic.</item><item>She agrees to go to the Risk Clinic.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman's Genetic History details are sent to this clinic (the HL7 Interaction <artref alt="POCG_IN000001" ref="POCG_IN000001UV"></artref> is used), including her Family History, the syndrome suspected and her level of risk.</item><item>The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, genetic counselor, MD, etc.) reviews the family history information collected by the primary clinician, edits it and adds additional details.</item><item>The Counselor reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The Counselor thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares the family history to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Her risk of a mutation is 25%, because her father's 4 sisters had ovarian caner.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  This discussion is recorded in the electronic medical record.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman wants to have testing, but as she is not affected, it is the standard of care to test a living affected relative first.</item><item>The Counselor suggests that her Aunt, Ms. Jeanne Aunt, is the most appropriate candidate for testing.  Ms. Jeanne Aunt had ovarian caner, and is still living.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman agrees to contact Ms. Jeanne Aunt.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman signs consent to release her own Family History details to Ms Jeanne Aunt and her Provider.</item><item>Ms. Jeanne Aunt is a 39-year-old woman had been diagnosed with ovarian cancer at age 35.</item><item>Ms Jeanne Aunt agrees to discuss testing, and provides the name and address of the Risk Clinic she will attend.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman's FH details are sent to this clinic (the HL7 Interaction POCG_IN000001 is used).</item><item>The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, genetic counselor, MD, etc.) reviews the family history information collected by the primary clinician through a pedigree drawing program, and changes the Proband* to Ms Jeanne Aunt, edits it and adds additional details (The family history message had had Ms Eve Everywoman as the Proband (Self), and Ms Jeanne Aunt as the aunt.  The pedigree from the point of view of Ms Jeanne Aunt must have Jeanne Aunt as the Proband (Self) and must show Ms Eve Everywoman as the niece).</item><item>The Counselor reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The Counselor thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares the family history to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Ms. Jeanne Aunt is virtually at 100% risk of having a mutation.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  This discussion is reviewed in the electronic medical record.</item><item>Ms. Jeanne Aunt wants to have testing.  She signs an informed consent document.</item><item>The order for testing is issued, and the informed consent, and the family history are included with the lab requisition.  All are MESSEGED to the blood drawing facility. In case the family history is messaged separately, then HL7 Interaction POCG_IN000001 is used.</item><item>The blood is drawn, and sent to the central testing facility along with the informed consent, the family history, the results of Ms Jeanne Aunt's test, and the lab requisition.</item><item>At the central testing facility, the specimen is checked in, and the DNA is separated and PCRed.</item><item>Full gene sequencing of BRCA1 and BRCA 2 are undertaken.</item><item>The sequence is assessed for mutations.</item><item>Identified mutations are assessed for functional significance by determining if they are truncating (deleterious), or if they are irrelevant (No change in amino acid coded by that codon).  All other mutations are compared to known mutations to determine if information is available on their functional significance.</item><item>The actual mutation, and the assessment of functional significance are sent to the counselor.</item><item>In this case, a mutation is identified in BRCA1 and the mutation is Deleterious.</item><item>The counselor discusses the result with the patient.</item><item>Management decisions (Screening, chemoprevention, prophylactic surgery) are probably beyond the scope of this storyboard.</item><item>Ms Jeanne Aunt agrees to share this information with Ms Eve Everywoman's Clinician.</item><item>This information is sent to Ms Eve Everywoman's Clinician.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman wants to have testing.  She signs an informed consent document.</item><item>The order for testing is issued, and the informed consent, and the family history are included with the requisition, as well as the results of Ms Jeanne Aunt's test.  All are MESSEGED to the blood drawing facility.</item><item>The blood is drawn, and sent to the central testing facility along with the informed consent, the family history and the lab requisition.</item><item>At the central testing facility, the specimen is checked in, and the DNA is separated and PCRed.</item><item>Full gene sequencing is not needed.  Testing only for the identified mutation is undertaken.</item><item>The DNA is assessed for that specific mutation.</item><item>The mutation is not found.</item><item>The normal result is sent to the counselor.</item><item>The counselor discusses the result with the patient.</item><item>Management decisions (Screening, chemoprevention, prophylactic surgery) are probably beyond the scope of this storyboard.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">* Glossary:</emph></p><p>Proband: First affected family member coming to medlcal attention.</p><p>Consultand:  Individual (s) seeking genetic counseling/tetsing.</p><p>These definitions are based on: Bennett RL, Steinhaus KA, Uhrich SB, O'Sullivan CK, Resta RG, Lochner-Doyle D, Markel DS, Vincent V, Hamanishi J. Recommendations for standardized human pedigree nomenclature. Pedigree Standardization Task Force of the National Society of Genetic Counselors.  Am J Hum Genet. 1995 Mar;56(3):745-52.
</p><p><emph role="strong">The Family History Shared Model</emph></p><p>Following the above sample of a patient's pedigree as well as the contextual presentation, we have developed an HL7 model to allow the representation of such a pedigree with an unlimited depth of generations. This model is described in detail (including a walk-through) in the section: "Refined Message Information Models".</p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_ST000040UV01.gif"/><intref ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01" sequence="1"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Application Roles" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="roles-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="arop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Receiver" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000002UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Sender" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000001UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="POCG_AR000002UV01" name="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" familiarName="Pedigree Receiver" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="02|20|99|22|PEDIGREE RECEIVER|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:35"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_AR000002UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" id="desc-POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:35"><p>A role of receiving a person's pedigree from a Pedigree Sender.</p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="POCG_AR000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" familiarName="Pedigree Sender" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="02|20|99|25|PEDIGREE SENDER|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:40"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_AR000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" id="desc-POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:40"><p>A role of sending a person's pedigree to a Pedigree Receiver.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Trigger Events" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="tes-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="teop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="POCG_TE000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Original New Notification" familiarName="Original Pedigree Notification" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" role="Interaction based" sortPrefix="02|20ORIGINAL|05||05|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:48"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_TE000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" id="desc-POCG_TE000001UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:48"><p>This is a notification of the availability of a person's pedigree to be sent to another pedigree application.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="POCG_RM000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Clinical Genomics Family History" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-16T15:35:41"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_RM000040UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" id="desc-POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2007-07-16T15:35:41"><p><emph role="strong">The Clinical Genomics Family History Model</emph></p><p>Following the above sample of a patient's pedigree as well as the contextual presentation, 
	we have developed an HL7 model to allow the representation of such a pedigree
	with an unlimited depth of generations. The model addresses the Family History requirements
	and represents a patient's pedigree while making use of the Genotype model for genomic
	data.     Each family member object is represented in relation to another family member who
	'scopes' its role and is designated by a code taken from the HL7 vocabulary "RoleCode", domain ="PersonalRelationshipRoleType". </p><p>General Notes:  </p><p>The Family History model is used in a message interaction designed to serve the need of information exchange between two disparate pedigree applications (see section on message interactions). This interaction does not serve other needs like sending genetic lab orders accompanied by family history. For the latter, there is a need to use Lab messages that might use this model as a payload.</p><p>The model utilizes the GeneticLocus model (the Genotype Topic) in order to
	capture genomic data in any resolution needed. For that end, the GeneticLocus model was
	packaged as an internal CMET and was also moved to the HL7 Common Domains in the V3 Ballot
	Package. It is utilized in this model as one of the choices in the main Clinical Genomics
	choice box (see the model walk through below). 
	The model suggests the use of the Clinical Statement shared model (under
	development in HL7) to represent the clinical data. Meanwhile, it has a generic
	ClinicalObservation class to hold common clinical data (e.g., problems, diagnoses,
	reactions to drugs, allergies, etc.).      </p><p><emph role="strong">Model Walk-Through</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">Starting Point - FamilyHistory:</emph></p><p>The starting point of the model is the FamilyHistory Observation class. This
	class has several associations, one of which is subject participation of the Patient role
	played by a Person entity. The latter scopes the Relative class which can hold information
	about the patient's relatives. This constitutes the backbone of the model. In addition, the
	entry point is associated with risk analysis results and with problems that can not be
	attributed to specific family members.</p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes of FamilyHistory:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item>id: holds a unique identifier of this family history instance</item><item>code: the code attribute shall hold a code representing Family History data in general, for example: the LOINC code 10157-6, HISTORY OF FAMILY MEMBER DISEASES or any other code that carries similar semantics.</item><item>statusCode: indicates whether the act of family history observation as a whole has completed, still active, etc. (based on the HL7 RIM Act State Machine)</item><item>methodCode: The methodCode holds the identification of the program creating the family history data</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Patient &amp; Person:</emph></p><p>The Patient role class is the root of the pedigree but in terms of data, it only captures an id assigned by the family history application on behalf of the provider hosting the family history application. Note that the id is optional and so is the class Provider (the scoping entity of the Patient role). Person is the player entity of Patient and holds general information about the person like gender, birth time, deceased indication, etc.</p><p>Note that the gender attribute of the Person class is an "administrative gender" and the way to represent genotypic / phenotypic gender is to populate an instance of the clinical observation class in the clinical genomic choice box.</p><p><emph role="strong">Clinical and Genomic Data:</emph></p><p>At the right side of the Patient role there is a 'subjectOf2' participation that
	associates the patient (as a 'subject of') to a choice box of zero to many clinical
	statements as well as genomic data represented by the GeneticLocus model. Note that this
	association is shadowed at the bottom of the model, associated with the Relative class,
	which represents a role of a patient's relative.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">ClinicalObservation</emph></p><p>The ClinicalObservation class represents any clinical data that
			is part of the Person clinical history. Currently, the class has the classCode of 'OBS'
			which means that it is capable of representing only observations. However, the full
			expression of a clinical statement will be available when this single class will be
			replaced by the HL7 Clinical Statement model (under development). The Clinical Statement
			model will provide the 'grammar' of how various discrete acts (observations, procedures,
			substance administrations, etc.) are associated to a meaningful clinical statement.
			Nevertheless, in the January 2007 ballot we added a recursive ActRelationship (sourceOf) to the clinical observation to address use cases where a richer clinical statement is need, as introduced to us by early adopters of the model. The addition of this association is in consistent with the Clinical Statement model, so that when eventually this single observation is replaced with the Clinical Statement model or a derivative of it, this current addition is in consistent with it and will not require substantive changes to the family history implementations.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">DataEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The DataEstimatedAge class is used to hold the
					estimated age of the subject at the effective time of the observation (e.g, the diagnosis
					time). The diagnosis is represented by the source observation , i.e., the
					ClinicalObservation class. It is used due to the absence of an age attribute in all HL7
					classes. We have proposed to RIM harmonization  the addition of an age attribute to the Act
					class as well as other classes, but were asked to try and model this piece of information
					using associated observations like this class.   The data type is an interval to allow a
					range of ages such as in cases when the patient only remembers that the diagnosis was made
					when the family member was in her forties for example.  </p><p>The code attribute shall hold a code representing age of subject at the effective time when the source observation was made for that subject. Its purpose is to allow parser applications to understand this class without referring to its name.</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">A_GeneticLocus (CMET)</emph></p><p><p>This CMET is the main model we are developing at the HL7
				Clinical Genomics SIG. In principle, the GeneticLocus model can hold relevant genomic data
				in any resolution required. In the BRCA storyboard, it could be information on mutations
				that the patient's relatives have or full DNA sequences of the patient's genes at
				stake.</p></p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">A_GeneticLoci (CMET)</emph></p><p>This CMET allows the association of data on a set of loci such as genetic test panel results or gene expression assay.
			</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">informant:</emph></p><p>This class optionally represents the source of information from which this family history was collected.
</p><p><emph role="strong">PedigreeAnalysisResults:</emph></p><p>This class represents the results of analysis done to the data captured in the
	family history pedigree.   Use the code attribute to identify the disease or variation for
	which the probabilities/risks/etc. are calculated.   Use the methodCode to hold the
	algorithm used to analyze the pedigree.    </p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes of PedigreeAnalysisResults:</emph></p><p>* code: identifies the disease or variation for which the probabilities/risks/etc. are calculated. Note that this class can be populated as many times as needed, for each clinical condition which is the is the focus of the risk calculations</p><p>* negationInd: can be used to represent the fact that there is no risk found for this family history and the clinical condition in the code attribute</p><p>* methodCode: holds the type of the algorithm used to analyze the pedigree (e.g., BRCAPRO)</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">risk</emph></p><p>The risk association links the FamilyHistory class to the PedigreeAnalysisResults class and represents the risk associated with that family history. The risk Act Relationship is defined in the RIM as follows: "A noteworthy undesired outcome of a patient's condition that is either likely enough to become an issue or is less likely but dangerous enough to be addressed." The patient condition in this model is the patient's family history and the risk is represented through the classes associated with PedigreeAnalysisResults class.</p><p>Consequently, the PedigreeAnalysisResults class and the observation classes associated with it are in 'risk' mood (moodCode= RSK) to express the fact that these are not observations that happened, rather they represent a risk associated wit the family history.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">InputParameters</emph></p><p>The controlVariable association links PedigreeAnalysisResults to
			input parameters used in the analysis like sensitivity and specificity in the BRCAPRO
			algorithm. For example, if the code attributes holds "sensitivity" then the value attribute holds the sensitivity itself. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Choice</emph></p><p>The component association links PedigreeAnalysisResults to a choice box that contains several options to represent the actual results:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AnalysisResult</emph></p><p>This class is a catcher for any analysis that cannot be represented through the other classes in this choice box.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Probability</emph></p><p>The value holds a probability of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation). 
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a probability observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">PercentageRisk</emph></p><p>The value holds a percentage risk of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation).
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a percentage risk observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Relative Risk</emph></p><p>The value holds a relative risk of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation).
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a relative risk observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Age &amp; Probability</emph></p><p>The pertinentInformation association links Age to Probability and multiple traversals of the Age class along with Probability can hold
					pairs of age-probability data for what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation). </p><p>The code attribute shall hold a code representing the concept of   "Age" in general (e.g., the value 397659008 "Age" in SNOMED CT).</p></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Relative:</emph></p><p>This refinement of the HL7 Role Class represents a patient's relative and is
	scoped by the Person entity which plays the Patient role in the first traversal of the model
	(see further explanation in the "Person and Relative" bullet below). The cardinality of
	this association is 0..* which allows for the representation of any number of relatives who
	all relate to the Person who scopes the role.     
	The Relative class has a classCode = "PRS", defined as "links two people in a
	personal relationship... the character of the relationship must be defined by a
	PersonalRelationshipRoleType code..." The latter code is defined by the Relative.code
	attribute whose value set is drawn from the domain "PersonalRelationshipRoleType".
	Appendix E includes a table that shows the codes of this domain. Using values from this
	domain it is possible to designate the relation to the patient or to the patient's family
	member. Thus, in this model it is possible to use, for example, the code GRMTH
	(grandmother) for Relative associated directly to the patient, or use the code NMTH
	(mother) for Relative associated to the mother of the patient. This makes the model more
	flexible.  </p><p>The basis of this part of the model is in the RIM definition of family member relationships which are based on the relationship between a scoping entity and a role. For example, the code CHILD is defines as "The player of the role is a child of the scoping entity", and the same goes for any type of family relationship. Note that this is valid not only to the relationship between the patient and a relative directly associated with the patient, rather this is true for any relationship between family members on this pedigree, for example, between the patient's mother  (the scoper) and her father (the role).</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">SubjectEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>This choice box is associated with the Relative class and holds</p><p>two classes concerned with estimated ages of the subject as follows:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">DeceasedEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The DeceasedEstimatedAge class is used to hold
					the estimated age when the subject died. It is used due to a lack of age attribute in all
					HL7 classes. We have proposed to RIM harmonization the addition of age attribute to hold
					the deceased age as well as the subject age at the time a diagnosis was made (see above in
					the DataEstimatedAge class description), but were asked to try and model this piece of
					information using associated observations like this class. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">LivingEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The LivingEstimatedAge class is used to hold the
					estimated age of a living relative whose birth date is unknown. </p></item><item>For a living subject, the code shall represent semantics similar to the LOINC code "21611-9" that represents the concept of an estimated age (as opposed to precise age). For a deceased subject, the code shall represent semantics similar to the LOINC code 39016-1 (AGE AT DEATH). </item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">subjectOf Shadow</emph></p><p>This class is a shadow of the subjectOf2 class associated with Patient and thus
	also includes all its associated classes. This means that the same clinical and genomic
	data structures attached to the patient could be optionally attached to any of his/her
	relatives represented by the Relative class. It could be that the clinical data of any of
	the persons involved in this pedigree model exist elsewhere (in the same message or
	document, or in the person medical records). In this case it is possible to point to that
	data by including stub classes which only hold ids of the actual data, thus enabling
	applications to get the information if needed.</p><p><emph role="strong">Person and Relative</emph></p><p>The Person class allows the representation of personal information like gender
	and birth time of each of the patient's relatives. It is also linked back to the Relative
	class, an association which enables a recursive traversal a pedigree at any level of depth
	in a pure XML hierarchical fashion (i.e., only by nesting elements). Note that in each new
	traversal of this recursive association, the scoping Person represents another family
	member, and consequently the Relative class relates to this family member and not directly
	to the patient. </p><p>In general, the issue of recursion and XML hierarchy relate to the
	representation of pedigree data which is hierarchical by nature but could be represented in
	various ways using XML nesting elements on the one hand or mother and father ids for each
	relative thus constituting the hierarchy via links and pointers and not via nesting
	elements. The latter format also allows the flat outline of the pedigree. These issues are
	discussed in more detail in the documentation available from the HL7 Clinical Genomics SIG
	page in the HL7 site. </p><p><emph role="strong">Relative - Mother and Father Identifiers</emph></p><p>In a flat XML representation of a pedigree it is often required to maintain
	mother and father ids for each relative, in order to allow the family history application
	to reconstruct the pedigree. These ids should be placed in the id attribute of the Person
	class. That class should be populated for each parent if available. The first XML sample in
	appendix D shows a flat representation of a pedigree with the ids populated in the Person
	class (XML element is relationshipHolder.id).</p><p>It is required to use globally unique ids as mandated from the use of the II data type for
	the id attribute. Regarding the generation of thses ids, there can be two situations: (1)
	The application generating the pedigree has a 'root' OID dedicated to this purpose and it
	extends it for each pedigree it creates. Then, it generates arbitrary unique ids for each
	relative who doesn't have a globally unique id and places it in the extension component.
	The concatenation of the pedigree root and relative extension creates a globally unique id
	for the person; (2) The application knows a globally unique id of a relative and uses it.
	Note that in a certain pedigree there can be a mixture of the two situations. </p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="POCG_DO000000UV"/><diagref ref="POCG_RM000040UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="POCG_HD000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Pedigree Event" parent="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" id="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-20T15:51:51"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Family History" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000040UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><msgtype identifier="POCG_MT000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Pedigree Event" parent="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" id="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:59:02"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Interactions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="ints-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="inop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="POCG_IN000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" familiarName="Original Pedigree" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="02|20ORIGINAL|05|05|FROM ORIGINATOR|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:45:36"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_IN000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" id="desc-POCG_IN000001UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:45:36">A number of pedigree applications are in use by healthcare professionals (e.g., CAGENE) as well as by patients (e.g., the US Surgeon General Family History Program), which each have their own internal proprietary format of representing data for pedigree drawing and maintenance of family history information. We envision that any pedigree application will be able to send and receive an individual's family history information using this HL7 specification, either electronically or through import/export routines that will be developed for each Pedigree application. Note that this is a general purpose information exchange, i.e., it's not designed to serve use cases such as lab orders or specific patient care scenarios.  For example, the interaction can serve the following short storyboard (derived from the "Family History" storyboard presented in the Clinical Genomics domain):

Ms. Martha Francis is 48 years old.  Her mother had ovarian cancer and was found to have a deleterious BRCA1 mutation.  She has two sisters, a husband and a daughter.  She is not of Ashkenazi Jewish descent

She makes an appointment at a Risk Clinic.  The Clinic instructs the patient to use the Surgeon General's Family History Tool to prepare for the visit.  She downloads the Surgeon General's Family History Tool onto her computer at home, and enters her family history.

She then exports the data as an HL7 MESSAGE, places it on Portable Media (CD, Flash drive) and brings it to her Risk Clinic appointment.

The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, Nurse Practitioner, Genetic Counselor, MD, etc.) imports the HL7 MESSAGE into CAGENE, a pedigree drawing program that runs risk models.  The counselor edits the data after confirming and clarifying various issues with the patient, and adds additional information that had not been entered at home.

The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  The patient decides not to have testing, and leaves.</descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Sender" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Receiver" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree Notification" refIdentifier="POCG_TE000001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

