<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/4/2008 5:24:43 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/4/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-FICR_DO000000UV"><head>FICR_DO000000UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="secondary_payor" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:16:44"><label>Secondary Payor</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:16:44"><p>The Payor that is responsible for payment of a Healthcare Invoice if the Primary Payor does not pay.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="provider_adjustments" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:57:51"><label>Provider Adjustments</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:57:51"><p>Changes to the billable amount as a result of items such as taxes, mark-ups, surcharges or discounts.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="deductible" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:44:53"><label>Deductible</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:44:53"><p>The dollar amount for which the plan beneficiary must pay before any remaining eligible expenses are reimbursed under the plan. This is usually calculated on an annual basis.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payor_adjustments" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:20:32"><label>Payor Adjustments</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:20:32"><p>Adjustments made by the Payor to the billed amount as a result of items such as deductibles or professional dues. Can also be referred to as adjustments to Payee.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="product/service_code" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:56:34"><label>Product/Service Code</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:56:34"><p>The code used to identify what service is being billed. Synonymous with fee-code.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="clinical_product_billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:01:51"><label>Clinical Product Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:01:51"><p>The set of information to describe the provision of healthcare goods/products for a patient's care that is billed in an invoice. This may include among other things - date of service, goods/product specification (including UPC code, serial number, manufacturer, packaging, warranty) provider, location from and delivery to location.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="prior_approval" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:33:50"><label>Prior Approval</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="coverage_extension">Coverage Extension</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="sessional_invoice" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:27:25"><label>Sessional Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:27:25"><p>An invoice for services provided on a sessional basis, e.g., 4 hours in an operating theatre.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="rootinvoiceelement" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:17:11"><label>RootInvoiceElement</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:17:11"><p>An Invoice Element at the top level (root) of the hierarchy of billable items that form part of an Invoice. Relationships for insurance, service target (e.g. patient), incident, EOBs (explanation of benefits) submitted for downstream payors (to support Coordination of Benefits) and attachments are made to the RootInvoiceElement. The information thus supplied applies to each individual Invoice Element (billable item) associated to the RootInvoiceElement.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="co-pay" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:03:41"><label>Co-pay</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:03:41"><p>The portion of a claim that is apportioned to the patient, often as a percentage of the total value of the claim.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="pharmacy_dispense_billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:21:25"><label>Pharmacy Dispense Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:21:25"><p>The set of information to describe the dispensing of a drug to a patient that is billed in an invoice. This may include among other things - date of service, drug supplied (specification, quantity, days supply), prescription and prescriber, number of refills, alerts and pharmacy.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="sofa" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:18:37"><label>SOFA</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:18:37"><p>This acronym is for Statement Of Financial Activity. This is a category of interactions that facilitate the exchange of detailed and summarized financial information between an Invoice Requestor and Adjudication Manager.  It includes Payment Advices, summarized counts and amounts for processed invoices as well as details of individual counts and amounts over a specified period of time</p></def></gitem><gitem id="group_service" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:13"><label>Group Service</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:13"><p>Provision of a service(s) to a group of individuals.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="coverage_extension" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:43:20"><label>Coverage Extension</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:43:20"><p>A form of Authorization where the Provider requests payment approval for extension of a Person's benefit coverage.  Typically, Coverage Extensions require manual or human intervention and decision by the Adjudicator. Synonymous with Prior Approval.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payment_advice" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:42:04"><label>Payment Advice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:42:04"><p>The payment details for adjudicated Invoices and non-Invoice adjustments which correspond to an actual payment either by cheque or electronic funds transfer.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="re-adjudication" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:23:33"><label>Re-Adjudication (of an invoice)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:23:33"><p>Process whereby a Provider can request a re-adjudication of an invoice that has been partially paid by a Payor. A TE660101  message can be used to perform this function or alternatively, the original invoice can be cancelled and a new invoice submitted to the same Payor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="drug_interactions" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:08"><label>Drug Interactions</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:08"><p>An interaction, usually adverse, between two or more medications being taken by the individual.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="deferred_adjudication" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:04:26"><label>Deferred Adjudication</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:04:26"><p>Adjudication of a claim that does not occur in real time i.e. the request for payment is responded to with a simple "acknowledgment of receipt" message. The final adjudication and transmission of adjudication results will occur at a later time as determined by the adjudicator's system.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="goods_service" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:13:11"><label>Goods Service</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:13:11"><p>A service provided to a Good (for a Person) such as wheelchair repair, hearing aid repair or prosthesis repair.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="service" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:17:55"><label>Service</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:17:55"><p>A consultation, diagnosis, treatment or intervention performed for a Person and/or other activity performed for a Person. Includes health, goods and support services.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="explanation_of_benefits" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:48:05"><label>Explanation of Benefits (EOB)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:48:05"><p>Identifies paid amount, adjudication results and informational items for n Invoice Grouping. The Provider may forward EOB details from a Primary Payor unaltered toa  Secondary Adjudicator for co-ordination of benefits.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="e-claim" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:07:21"><label>e-Claim</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:07:21"><p>An invoice for health related good(s) and/or service(s) transmitted for payment in an electronic format.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="preferred_accommodation_benefits" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:11:28"><label>Preferred Accommodation Benefits</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:11:28"><p>Benefits covering special healthcare lodging requirements. This includes private or semi-private hospital accommodation.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="formulary" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:11:32"><label>Formulary</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:11:32"><p>The list of medications that are a benefit for an individual or a defined group.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payment_reconciliation" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:20:04"><label>Payment Reconciliation</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:20:04"><p>The process of comparing what has been paid versus what was expected to be paid.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="din" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:05:50"><label>DIN</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:05:50"><p>The Drug Identification Number assigned to a specific medication by Health Canada.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="attachment_healthcare_invoice" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:57:56"><label>Attachment Healthcare Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:57:56"><p>Additional supporting material attached to a NeCST message such as a form, report or image.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="billable_line_item" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:41:27"><label>Billable Line Item</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:41:27"><p>A single billable unit for a product, e.g. product cost, tax, etc. or service, e.g. office visit.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="goods" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:38:23"><label>Goods</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:38:23"><p>A durable or consumable product provided to a Person including equipment, food and furniture. Splint, wheelchair, prosthetic and custom table are examples of goods.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_document" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:22"><label>Health Document</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:22"><p>A form, report or image that substantiates the authorization, adjudication and subsequent payment of a Healthcare Invoice. A Health Document can be submitted manually or electronically. When submitted electronically, it can be submitted with a Healthcare Invoice or separately from the Healthcare Invoice.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="patient_pays_portion" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:19:16"><label>Patient Pays Portion</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:19:16"><p>The amount of a claim that is the responsibility of the patient.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="prescription" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:05:27"><label>Prescription</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:05:27"><p>An order from a recognized prescriber for a health care good or service.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="service_relationship" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:26:54"><label>Service Relationship</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:26:54"><p>A defined relationship or association between a Provider and Payee or Person and Payee that defines the financial and/or contract terms and conditions.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="form" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:00:46"><label>Form</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:00:46"><p>Structured document with content, transmission, display and storage requirements identified in a standard.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="professional_fee" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:22:53"><label>Professional Fee</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:22:53"><p>In health care, the fee charged by the health care provider for the provision of a service. In pharmacy, this often refers to the fee charged for the dispensing of a medication.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="business_arrangement_identifier" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:01:21"><label>Business Arrangement Identifier (BAI)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:01:21"><p>Identifier assigned to represent the business arrangement (or contract) between a Payee and Provider.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="adjudication_results" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:35:54"><label>Adjudication Results</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:35:54"><p>A response by the Adjudicator to the Provider identifying edit errors and/or adjudication results for invoices (by Product Service Line Item) that have been paid in full, partially paid (adjusted) or not paid and reasons for adjustment and non-payment.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:59:47"><label>Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:59:47"><p>An invoice attachment that provides additional details on the claim.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="healthcare_good" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:15:55"><label>Healthcare Good</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:15:55"><p>A product that is supplied from a healthcare provider and that is/ may be a benefit of an individual's benefit plan e.g. wheelchair, syringes.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="invoice_element" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:14:45"><label>Invoice Element</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-09T11:14:45"><p>A single billable item, made up of an identifiable code (e.g. office visit, wheel chair) and pricing for that billable item.  For example, it can be used to specify 4 wheel chairs @ $250 per wheel chair.  Invoice Elements may be specified in a hierarchy to fully specify the item being invoiced.  That is, it includes a grouping variant as well as a detail variant (the detail variant contains the detailed pricing information).  For example, a group Invoice Element may contain 2 detail Invoice Elements, one for the good and one for the associated taxes.  Therefore, the group Invoice Element would represent the amount for the good and taxes.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="electronic_health_record" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:07:57"><label>Electronic Health Record (EHR)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:07:57"><p>An electronic representation of an individual's health record, either in a single data repository or in separate linked repositories.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="clinical_service_billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:02:10"><label>Clinical Service Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:02:10"><p>The set of information to describe the patient care or other activity performed by a provider that is billed in an invoice. This may include among other things - date of service, healthcare provider, location and diagnosis. It may also include information about the maintenance of a healthcare product (wheelchair).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="requester" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:11:27"><label>Requester</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:11:27"><p>An organization or person on whose behalf a request message for authorization, information, etc. is submitted.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="billable_invoice_items" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:00:10"><label>Billable Invoice Items</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:00:10"><p>One or more billable services performed or products supplied by a Provider.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="co-ordination_of_benefits" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:43:05"><label>Co-ordination of Benefits</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:43:05"><p>Refers to the co-ordination of payment of an invoice or invoice line item that may be payable by more than oneAdjudictor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="information_invoice" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:18:54"><label>Information Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:18:54"><p>An invoice that is for information purposes only. Used in situations where a non fee for service funding method is used but details on the products/services provided is still required.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="global_product_identification_number" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:48:33"><label>Global Product Identification Number (EAN, UCC, GPIN)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:48:33"><p>A globally unique identifier assigned to a product</p></def></gitem><gitem id="drug_utilization_review" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:47"><label>Drug Utilization Review</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:47"><p>A review of the medication regimen of an individual, either prospective (concurrent) or retrospective (past).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="receiver" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:12:05"><label>Receiver</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:12:05"><p>The application fulfilling the Receiving Application role in an interaction</p></def></gitem><gitem id="invoice_element_detail" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:14"><label>Invoice Element Detail</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:14"><p>The information contained in a Healthcare Invoice such as quantity, unit and cost, authorization, service location and comment information. Synonymous with fee-item.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="service_bureau" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:26:39"><label>Service Bureau</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:26:39"><p>An agent retained by a Provider to assemble and submit Healthcare Invoices and receive validation and adjudication results.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="sender" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:12:27"><label>Sender</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-12T11:12:27"><p>The application fulfilling the Sending Application role in an interaction</p></def></gitem><gitem id="healthcare_provider" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:16:32"><label>Healthcare Provider</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="provider">Provider</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="insurance_carrier" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:54:02"><label>Insurance Carrier</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="carrier">Carrier</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="demographic_information" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:04:43"><label>Demographic Information</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:04:43"><p>Relates to the patient's name, address, date of birth, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="time_charge" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:28:26"><label>Time Charge</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:28:26"><p>An extra time charge in addition to the professional fee that may be charged by a pharmacist when preparing a compound.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="authorization" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:39:53"><label>Authorization</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:39:53"><p>A communication process betweenthe  Provider and Adjudicator regarding (pre)-approval for payment of a service.  Authorization is an Adjudicator's commitment to pay for a service even though an Adjudicator may or may not reserve monies for the pre-approved amount.  Typically, Authorizations are processed automatically by the Payor's adjudication engine.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="assignment_of_benefits" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:37:50"><label>Assignment of Benefits</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:37:50"><p>The formal transfer of the right to certain benefit payments by a plan member to a third-party.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="adjudication_response" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:58:08"><label>Adjudication Response</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="adjudication_results">Adjudication Results</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="co-insurance" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:42:45"><label>Co-insurance</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:42:45"><p>A set percentage of any  claim cost payable by plan members after any deductible has been paid</p></def></gitem><gitem id="attachment_reference_identifier" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:57:25"><label>Attachment Reference Identifier</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:57:25"><p>A unique number (made up of form number and Network Application ID) that uniquely identifies the Health Document that is attached to the Healthcare Invoice.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_service_provider" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:15:16"><label>Health Service Provider</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="provider">Provider</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="duplicate_therapy" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:24"><label>Duplicate Therapy</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:06:24"><p>The provision of the same or a similar medication for an individual for the same purpose.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="alert_no_text" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:56:05"><label>Alert No Text</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:56:05"><p>The set of information that describes the details about potential problems or warnings associated with an Act.  This is used for drug utilization review findings such as drug interactions. This may include among other things - alert code, type of alert, severity and reason alert was issued( including drug and supply information). No text representation is provided.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payment" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:39:46"><label>Payment</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:39:46"><p>A cheque or Electronic Funds Transfer (EFT) issued to a Payee.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="patient" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:36:20"><label>Patient</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:36:20"><p>Person, in the role of patient for a particular situation. For example, this person is a patient at the hospital, but this person is not a patient at this time. See also Person.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="primary_payor" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:16:48"><label>Primary Payor</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:16:48"><p>The Payor that is responsible for payment of a Healthcare Invoice.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payee" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:54:50"><label>Payee</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:54:50"><p>A Person or organization that receives payment for Goods provided and/or Services rendered or receives payment on behalf of one or more Providers. As well, a Payee may be a Person who has directly paid the Provider for the Goods provided and/or Services rendered and is being reimbursed by the Adjudicator. In some cases, a Payee may be the same as the Provider.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="pre-determination" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:05:04"><label>Pre-Determination</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:05:04"><p>The submission of a 'mock' Healthcare Invoice to a Payor to determine the extent to which an Adjudicator will reimburse for the goods or services.   A Provider may use this to compare alternate treatments to determine least cost alternative for the patient.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="enrolment" lastEdit="2004-10-27T09:02:23"><label>Enrolment</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-10-27T09:02:23"><p>The process of registering with an insurer to obtain benefits coverage.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payment_request" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:43:17"><label>Payment Request</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="invoice">Invoice</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="invoice" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:52:24"><label>Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:52:24"><p>A request initiated by a Provider, on behalf of a plan member (insured), for payment for services rendered and/or goods provided. Stated another way, an Invoice is a request by a plan member to a plan administrator (Adjudicator) for payment of a benefit covered by the benefit plan.</p><p>Can be synonymous with Fee for Service Claim, Claim, and Bill.</p><p>An invoice can be submitted for any payment modalities (e.g., fee for service, sessional, group, contract and/or block services).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="benefit_group" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:40:55"><label>Benefit Group</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:40:55"><p>A collection of related healthcare providers and/or organizations and/or type of service, usually based on provider specialty, that negotiate fee schedules/payment contracts with Insurance Carriers, e.g. Pharmacy, Preferred Accommodation, Chiropractors.  Benefit Groups are used in Financial Management, Claims and Reimbursement (FICR) to classify Messages, Application Roles and Interactions that are allowed for that group.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="third_party_administrator" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:24:49"><label>Third Party Administrator (TPA)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T15:24:49"><p>A TPA is an organization retained by a Payor to receive and apply Payor rules, validate Healthcare Invoices and issue payments on behalf of the Payor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="up-charge" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:29:08"><label>Up-charge</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:29:08"><p>A percentage that may be added to the cost of a product when calculating the cost of a claim.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="allowed_benefit" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:56:36"><label>Allowed Benefit</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:56:36"><p>A good or service that is a benefit under the patient's instance of insurance.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="adjudication_response_time" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:55:23"><label>Adjudication Response Time</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:55:23"><p>The elapsed time between the electronic submission of the claim for adjudication and the receipt of the adjudication results.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="reciprocal_healthcare_invoice" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:24:10"><label>Reciprocal Healthcare Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:24:10"><p>A request for payment of Service rendered and/or Goods provided by a Provider in one province to a Person who is insured by a different province. Reciprocal invoices are based on agreements between the provinces, except Quebec and only apply to Physician related claims.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="adjudicator" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:36:53"><label>Adjudicator</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:36:53"><p>The organization that interprets insurance policy rules through an adjudication process and makes a determination on how much money should be paid for a particular invoice .An Adjudicator typically acts on behalf of an Insurance Carrier.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payment_intent" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:55:39"><label>Payment Intent</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:55:39"><p>Based on the adjudicated results of an invoice, Payment Intent is the details of the items and amounts the Adjudicator intends to pay. This is not a record of payment but rather an intention to pay which may be more or less than what was requested in the invoice.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="compound" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:03:02"><label>Compound</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:03:02"><p>Generally an extemporaneous mixture that has been prepared by the pharmacist based on a prescription from a prescriber.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_goods_provider" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:39"><label>Health Goods Provider</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:14:39"><p>A party that provides medical and support goods to a Person.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="adjudication" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:54:28"><label>Adjudication</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:54:28"><p>A process by which an adjudicator identifies edit errors and/or determines payment intent based on insurance policy rules for submitted invoices.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="carrier" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:02:46"><label>Carrier</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:02:46"><p>An organization that etablishes insurance policies, determines eligibility and benefits under those insurance policies, and underwrites payments for products and/or services provided to a beneficiary (person or organization).</p><p>A Carrier may retain a TPA (Third Party Administrator) insurance carrier to perform some or all invoice validation, adjudication and payment.</p><p>This may also be known as the insurance company or public insurance carrier.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="vision_product_billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:29:26"><label>Vision Product Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:29:26"><p>The set of information to describe the dispensing of a vision care product to a patient that is billed in an invoice. This may include among other things - date of service, vision care product specification, prescription and prescriber, performer, location and diagnosis.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="healthcare_claim" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:15:39"><label>Healthcare Claim</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:15:39"><p>An invoice for health related good(s) and/or service(s) transmitted for payment. See also invoice.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="provider" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:07:06"><label>Provider</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T20:07:06"><p>An individual who delivers a health service to a person or animal e.g., doctor, nurse, pharmacist, technician, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="request_for_payment" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:25:59"><label>Request for Payment</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="invoice">Invoice</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="implied_consent" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:17:14"><label>Implied Consent</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:17:14"><p>Consent for an activity that is inferred by a prior activity and not a result of a discussion i.e. supplying a healthcare provider with a benefit card implied the provider should transmit claims for payment where possible.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="benefit_coverage" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:58:46"><label>Benefit Coverage</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T18:58:46"><p>A description of the benefits provided by an individual's benefit plan.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="invoice_element_grouping" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:47"><label>Invoice Element Grouping</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:47"><p>A collection of Invoice Elements that make up a package of items that need to be adjudicated together.  For example, a drug dispense, with Invoice Elements (costing elements) for the drug cost, markup and professional fees.  An Invoice Grouping has a root Invoice Element Group, with multiple Invoice Element Details and Invoice Element Groups.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="person" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:50:34"><label>Person</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:50:34"><p>Individual person, who can assume multiple roles over time. For example, a person may be a patient for a period of time at a hospital or a provider on a different occasion.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="procedure" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:55:27"><label>Procedure</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:55:27"><p>In the context of a Health Care procedure this is the details identifying the service or procedure that was actually provided to a Person such as the procedure code, duration of procedure, time procedure took place and Provider who performed the procedure.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="diagnosis" lastEdit="2003-04-09T13:57:03"><label>Diagnosis</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T13:57:03"><p>Identification of disease or condition by a practitioner by means of a Persons symptoms, diagnostic tests, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="healthcare_invoice" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:16:14"><label>Healthcare Invoice</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="invoice">Invoice</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="payor" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:59:17"><label>Payor</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-03-09T19:59:17"><p>A Payor is the organization who is responisble for the payment. This is typically the name on the cheque.</p><p>Also known as the Plan Sponsor.</p><p>Note that this may be a different organization than the Carrier (insurance carrier) and Adjudicator.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="tpa/payor" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:28:55"><label>TPA/Payor</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:28:55"><p>A label used to refer to processes that may be performed by either a TPA or Payor. For example, in some circumstances a Payor may both administer a Healthcare Invoice and authorize benefits, while in other circumstances a Payor may act as a TPA for another Payor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="invoice_element_group" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:26"><label>Invoice Element Group</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:18:26"><p>A grouping of Invoice Element Details.  For example, a group represents all of the costing elements that make up a drug cost (e.g. drug cost + markup).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="supporting_documentation" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:27:50"><label>Supporting Documentation</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:27:50"><p>Forms, Reports, Attachments submitted by Third Parties (e.g., Employer) to a Payor that may be applicable to a Healthcare Invoice. Submission not included in scope of NeCST.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_service" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:16:31"><label>Health Service</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T14:16:31"><p>A health care service such as diagnosis, treatment or intervention performed for a person.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="diagnosis_code" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:05:28"><label>Diagnosis Code</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:05:28"><p>A coding scheme (e.g., ICD-10CA/CCI) used to indicate diagnosis.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="preferred_accommodation_billable_act" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:22:05"><label>Preferred Accommodation Billable Act</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-06-13T19:22:05"><p>The set of information to describe the patient's premium hospital accommodation that is billed in an invoice. This may include among other things - date range of occupation, location, accommodation requested and available, reason for accommodation and requestor.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="eligibility" lastEdit="2003-04-09T13:57:00"><label>Eligibility (for benefits coverage)</label><def domainid="FICR_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-04-09T13:57:00"><p>A Person meets the criteria for benefits coverage. Benefits coverage is determined by the Insurance Carrier and may be delegated to an Adjudicator.</p><p>Eligibility for benefits does not necessarily imply a specific service or good will be covered for payment. Eligibility with one insurance carrier does not imply eligibility with another insurance carrier.</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

