<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/9/2008 3:38:00 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/9/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-COCT_DO000000UV"><head>COCT_DO000000UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="contact_cmet" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:47:44"><label>contact CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:47:44"><p>A CMET variant that provides sufficient information to allow the object identified to be contacted.  This is likely to have the content of identified and confirmable plus telephone number.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="minimal_cmet&#xA;minimal_cmet" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:48:55"><label>minimal CMET
minimal CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:48:55"><p>A CMET variant that provides more than identified, but not as much as universal.  There are not expected to be many of these.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="identified-confirmable_cmet" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:47:52"><label>identified-confirmable CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:47:52"><p>A CMET variant that extends the identified variant by adding just sufficient additional information to allow the identity of object modeled to be confirmed by a number of corroborating items of data;  for instance a patient's date of birth and current address.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="identified-informational_cmet" lastEdit="2005-11-13T15:30:10"><label>identified-informational CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-11-13T15:30:10"><p>A CMET variant that contains the same attributes and associations present in the confirmable CMET (or the identified/confirmable if the confirmable does not exist), however the informational variant of dependant CMETs is used, which relaxes the constraints on dependant CMETs. This allows more flexible use of the CMET. </p></def></gitem><gitem id="universal_cmet" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:45:44"><label>universal CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:45:44"><p>A CMET variant that includes all attributes and associations present in the R-MIM. Any of non-mandatory and non-required attributes and/or associations may be present or absent, as permitted in the cardinality constraints.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="informational_cmet" lastEdit="2005-11-13T15:25:35"><label>informational CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-11-13T15:25:35"><p>A CMET variant that includes approximately the same attributes and associations present in the identified/confirmable CMET, however the entry class id is required, not mandatory. This allows more flexible use of the CMET. </p></def></gitem><gitem id="identified_cmet" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:48:04"><label>identified CMET</label><def domainid="COCT_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-07-18T12:48:04"><p>A CMET variant that is a proper subset of universal and is intended to provide sufficient information to identify the object(s) modeled by the CMET.  This variant is only suitable for use within TIGHTLY COUPLED SYSTEMS ONLY. This variant provides ONLY the ID (and code where applicable) and Name.   Other variants may not be substituted at runtime.</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

