<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" sectionCode="HMREDS" lastEdit="11/19/2006 9:25:14 PM" rendered="5/30/2008 1:32:39 PM"><header><title>Domain: Clinical Decision Support</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="1"/><date>5/30/2008</date><authlist><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="1">Robert Greenes, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare/Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital</affiliation></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="2">Robert A. Jenders, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center/University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="4">R. Matthew Sailors, PhD</name><affiliation>University of Texas, Houston</affiliation></author><author><role>Editor</role><name key="5">Guilherme Del Fiol, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Editor/M&amp;M Facilitator/Co-chair</role><name key="6">Craig Parker, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="70">James R. Campbell, MD</name><affiliation>University of Nebraska</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="71">James Cimino, MD</name><affiliation>Columbia University, New York</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="72">Robert Dolin, MD</name><affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="73">Thom Kuhn</name><affiliation>American College of Physicians</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="74">Saverio Maviglia, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare, Boston</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="75">Roberto Rocha, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>University of Utah, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="76">Howard Strasberg, MD</name><affiliation>WoltersKluwer Health</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="prefNotes"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p> In this ballot, the Clinical Decision Support domain contains multiple "topics", as outlined below.</p><list role="unordered"><item>Context-aware Information Retrieval Topic (Infobutton): normative document.</item><item>Infobutton URL-Based Implementation Guide: informative document.</item><item>Order Sets</item></list></div1><div1 id="prefChange"><head>Changes from Previous Release</head><list role="unordered"><item>Context-aware Information Retrieval Topic (Infobutton): this ballot contains minor corrections and enhancements as a result of prior committee level ballot feedback, more specifically: 1) removal of artifacts that were related to future phases of this proposed topic; 2) use of more specific names for interactions; 3) HMD was not published in the previous ballot; 4) fixed UCUM codes used in the documentation.</item><item>Infobutton URL-Based Implementation Guide: this is the first time this document is submitted for ballot.</item><item>Order Sets: This version of the Order Sets ballot contains some enhancements based on input from the previous ballot cycle, most notably the addition of the "OrderSet" class to distinguish between the document and the order set itself.  The Order Set topic is not complete at this time.  The included material is submitted for informaiton and for comment.</item></list></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Message Model" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="REDS_HD100001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_HD100001UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-11-08T21:34:47"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="dmims-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"/><subdivn identifier="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Context-aware Information Retrieval (Infobutton) Topic" familiarName="Context-aware Information Retrieval (Infobutton)" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="10" baseClass="Context-aware Information Retrieval (Infobutton)" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><div2 id="intro-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><head>Introduction</head><div3 id=""><head>Topic Overview</head><p>
Infobuttons are point-of-care information retrieval tools that automatically generate and send queries to On-Line Health Information Resources (or simply information resources) using patient data extracted from an Electronic Health Record (EHR) and context information that is captured from the interaction between a clinical user and an EHR (e.g., user characteristics, patient demographics, task being performed by the user). A number of Infobutton implementations are available and have been described in the medical informatics literature.</p><p>Infobuttons can be implemented using an Infobutton Manager (IM), which is a Decision Support System (DSS) that supports the implementation of Infobuttons in an institution and application-independent fashion. In current implementations, an IM is typically called by an EHR, receiving a set of parameters. The IM then generates an HTML document containing a set of clinical questions that are pertinent in a given context (e.g., "how do I treat pneumonia," "how do I diagnose pneumonia"), each of which is a hyperlink that is used to run a query on a set of available information resources. </p><p>An Infobutton request is composed of a set of context parameters that are ultimately used by an information resource to run a search for content and return a list of matches to this search. Examples of these context parameters are:</p><list role="unordered"><item>A clinical concept (e.g., a medication, a lab test result, a disease in the patient's problem list) displayed on the electronic health record (EHR) screen. These concepts are typically displayed with an Infobutton next to them.</item><item>Information captured in the background, based on the context of the interaction between a user and the EHR. Examples are the user's role (e.g., physician, nurse), patient demographics (age, gender), and the type of application the user is using or the task that the user is trying to perform (e.g., order entry, lab results, problem list, medications list).</item><item>Information displayed on an Infobutton screen and selected by the user (e.g., question subtopics, such as "diagnosis," "treatment," "prognosis").</item></list><p>Currently, there are two major problems that complicate the integration between EHRs and IMs and also between IMs and available information resources:</p><list role="unordered"><item>Information resources typically provide an Application Program Interface (API) that can be used by IMs. However, these APIs follow a proprietary syntax and vocabulary, requiring the development of custom software for each new information resource that is made available to an Infobutton.</item><item>Several EHR modules in the same institution may implement Infobutton requests to an IM (e.g., Order Entry, Clinical Notes, Nurse charting, Lab Results). Different vendors may provide these EHR modules (applications), requiring each vendor to write additional software for every IM that they integrate with.</item></list><p><graphic source="REDS_EX010001.gif" alt="non-standard-based integration: multiple EHRs or EHR modules, multiple Infobutton Managers, and multiple content sources."></graphic>The focus of this proposal is to address the two problems mentioned above by developing a standard set of messages to support the communication between 1) EHRs and IMs and 2) IMs and information resources. <graphic source="REDS_EX010002.gif" alt="Integration supported by the proposed standard."></graphic></p></div3><div3 id=""><head>Requirements and scope</head><p>The standard will be developed and released into 3 different phases. Although this document focuses on phase 1, potential future enhancements are also listed in this section. The following table describes the main requirements of the proposal and the phase that each requirement is currently assigned. The remainder of this document focuses on phase 1.</p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td>Req. number</td><td>Requirement description</td><td>Phase</td></tr><tr><td>1</td><td>Support requests from a EHR to a DSS and from a DSS to information resources.</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Support for queries with different levels of sophistication (e.g., from free-text, single-parameter searches to coded, multiple parameter searches).</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Support search criteria with coded parameters using standard terminologies.</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Support context parameters (e.g., age, gender, user role, information system module). Context being defined as background information about the user or patient while using a EHR and that may help an IM and information resources to determine the user's information needs.</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Support search modifiers that narrow down the search criteria to a subtopic of interest (e.g., treatment, diagnosis, complications, prognosis).</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Specify a standard message for a structured response from information resources back to the DSS.</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Support requests for additional data from a DSS to a EHR.</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table></div3><div3 id=""><head>Phase 1 Overview</head><p>The current ballot cycle covers the first phase of the development of this standard. The "Introduction &amp; scope" and "Storyboard" sections explain the scope of each phase. In this first phase only the communication from EHR to DSS and from DSS to information resources is covered, with no standard communication back from the information resource to the DSS or form the DSS to the EHR. This strategy is in line with current Infobutton implementations, where DSSs obtain additional information from an EHR user typically by displaying an Infobutton HTML page and the requested content is sent back to the EHR user also typically in an HTML page. Future releases of this standard will provide a standard structure way to cover these steps that are currently done by exchanging HTML content.</p></div3><div3 id=""><head>Notes</head>
The following notes should be considered when reading this documentation:
<list role="unordered"><item>The standard does not determine how the components involved in the integration between an EHR and an information resource are implemented or how they operate. </item><item>The standard does not define the information resource content structure and indexing strategy. However, information resource developers can use the proposed standard as a guideline to define their content structure / indexing strategy, making their product more efficient in terms of responding to standard Infobutton requests.</item><item>Although Infobutton Managers constitute the most appropriate approach for implementing Infobuttons in a large scale, such a component is not necessary for an EHR developer to start adopting the proposed standard. EHRs MAY generate Infobutton requests that communicate directly with information resources.</item><item>HIPAA: the standard recognizes that the data to be sent to/by an IM could potentially lead to the identification of a patient in some special cases (e.g., rare condition in a small hospital). However, the standard does not determine any strategy to prevent such identification. It is the role of the involved parties (EHRs, IMs, and information resources) to establish data communication, processing, and storage in a secure environment.</item></list></div3><div3 id=""><head>Encoding Rules and Processing</head><p>To be compliant with the proposed Infobutton standard, EHRs, IMs, and information resources are not required to handle all the parameters previously listed. In order to maximize interoperability, the following directives should be followed:</p><list role="unordered"><item>An EHR or IM SHOULD formulate queries as complete as possible, using all available coded concepts and all message data elements that the EHR or IM have information about.</item><item>Information resources SHALL process only the data elements that they can handle (other data elements SHALL be ignored). For example, if an information resource does not use gender as an index for its content, gender SHALL be ignored by the information resource. The simplest request that an information resource has to be able to process would be limited to the <emph>displayName</emph> attribute of the MainSearchCriteria.code class attribute (see RMIM documentation for more details).</item></list><p>These directives allow applications to create generic queries that will run on any information resource that implements the standard, without requiring major modifications to the indexing strategy and content structure of the information resources.</p></div3></div2><storydivn identifier="sbs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Storyboards" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="sbs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="sstop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="REDS_ST010001UV01" name="Infobutton" familiarName="Infobutton" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:46:02"><descriptive identifier="purp-REDS_ST010001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" id="purp-REDS_ST010001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:46:02"><p>The following storyboard describes a typical Infobutton transaction. In addition to the interactions being covered as part of this ballot, the storyboard also describes steps that will be developed in future phases of this topic (the left most column of the table indicates the phase that each storyboard step is associated with). </p><p>Storyboard -  Infobutton request originated from a problem list.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REDS_SN010001UV01" name="Infobutton Act Infobutton Storyboard Narrative" familiarName="Infobutton Storyboard Narrative" parent="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" id="REDS_ST010001UV01-REDS_SN010001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="Infobutton" lastEdit="2006-11-08T18:01:33"><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td>Step</td><td>Development phase</td><td>Actor</td><td>Step description</td></tr><tr><td>1</td><td>phase 1</td><td>EHR</td><td>A clinician is reviewing a problem list module of an EHR and is unfamiliar with a rare disease (Camurati-Engelmann Disease) that the patient, a 15-year-old female, has. The problem list module provides an infobutton link next to the "Camurati-Engelmann Disease" problem. The user clicks on the infobutton link, initiating an infobutton event.</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>phase 1</td><td>EHR</td><td><artref ref="REDS_IN010001" alt="A request is sent to the DSS"></artref>. Context data available to the EHR is passed to the DSS (main search concept="Camurati-Engelmann Disease", age=15, gender=female, and task context=problem list review).</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>phase 3</td><td>DSS</td><td>The DSS receives the request and replies with a list of questions related to the disease the user is interested in (e.g., "What is the definition of Camurati-Engelmann Disease," "How do I diagnose Camurati-Engelmann Disease," "How do I treat Camurati-Engelmann Disease")</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>phase 3</td><td>EHR</td><td>The user selects the "What is the definition of Camurati-Engelmann Disease" option and a request is sent to the DSS. </td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>phase 1</td><td>DSS</td><td><artref ref="REDS_IN010002" alt="DSS sends a request to the target information resource"></artref>  (main search concept="Camurati-Engelmann Disease", age=15, gender=female, subtopic=definition)</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>phase 1</td><td>information resource</td><td>The information resource receives the request and searches its database using only the request elements that are understood by its search engine (e.g., main search concept and subtopic). Other request elements are ignored. </td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>phase 2</td><td>information resource</td><td>The information resource replies with a result set that contains pointers to content that matches the request.</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>phase 2</td><td>EHR</td><td>The user selects one of the content options that are presented. A request is sent to the information resource.</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>phase 2</td><td>information resource</td><td>The information resource returns the content requested by the user.</td></tr></tbody></table></descriptive><diagref ref="REDS_ST010001UV01.gif"/><intref ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01" sequence="1"/><intref ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Information Resource Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01" sequence="2"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Application Roles" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="roles-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="arop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Decision Support System" refFamiliarName="Decision Support System" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Electronic Health Record" refFamiliarName="Electronic Health Record" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REDS_AR010003UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Information Resource" refFamiliarName="Information Resource" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010003UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="REDS_AR010002UV01" name="Infobutton Event Decision Support System" familiarName="Decision Support System" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|20|99|99|DECISION SUPPORT SYSTEM" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:46:23"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_AR010002UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" id="desc-REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:46:23"><p>An application role that processes Infobutton requests from the EHR application role. In current implementations, this role is typically implemented by an Infobutton Manager component.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Information Resource Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="REDS_AR010001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Electronic Health Record" familiarName="Electronic Health Record" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|20|99|99|ELECTRONIC HEALTH RECORD" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:23:00"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_AR010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" id="desc-REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:23:00"><p>Any clinical information system or clinical information system module where infobuttons are available.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="REDS_AR010003UV01" name="Infobutton Event Information Resource" familiarName="Information Resource" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_AR010003UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|20|99|99|INFORMATION RESOURCE" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:00:33"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_AR010003UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_AR010003UV01-ar" id="desc-REDS_AR010003UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:00:33"><p>An application role that fulfills requests for reference information from the DSS.</p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Information Resource Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Trigger Events" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="tes-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="teop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="REDS_TE010001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Notification" familiarName="Infobutton Event Notification" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" role="User request" sortPrefix="10|20|99||05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-08T18:41:04"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_TE010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" id="desc-REDS_TE010001UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-11-08T18:41:04"><p>Infobutton request initiated by the EHR (typically as a result of a user clicking on an Infobutton). </p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/><intref role="fires" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Information Resource Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="rmims-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="rmop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="REDS_RM010001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Clinical Decision Support" familiarName="Infobutton Event Message Model" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="10|20|99|CLINICAL DECISION SUPPORT" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-09T13:26:25"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_RM010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" id="desc-REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2006-11-09T13:26:25"><p>The purpose of the transmitted data is to enable the requesting of reference information relevant to a given context in the patient care workflow.</p><p><emph role="strong">NOTE: </emph>The HL7 Reference Information Model is the definitive source of definitions for classes and definitions. What follows are special considerations for the referenced RIM components as they are used in this model. Note that at no time do the comments presented here conflict with the RIM, but instead further constrain the RIM definitions. </p><p><emph role="strong">InfobuttonEventNotification class</emph></p><p>This class represents the root of the InfobuttonEventNotification RMIM. The following are definitions of the attributes of the InfobuttonEventNotification class.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">InfobuttonEventNotification.id: </emph>Represents the globally unique instance identifier of an Infobutton message. </p></item><item><p>I<emph role="strong">nfobuttonEventNotification.effectiveTime: </emph>creation time of the Infobutton message.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">InfobuttonEventNotifcation Relationships</emph></p><p>This section describes classes related to the root InfobuttonEventNotification class:</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">MainSearchCriteria: </emph>this class represents the main clinical concept(s) of interest in an Infobutton request (e.g., a medication, a lab test result, a disease in the patient's problem list). In Infobutton implementations, this concept is typically displayed in the EHR user interface with an Infobutton next to it. Multiple concepts MAY be expressed, assuming an implicit AND operator (e.g., Pneumonia AND diabetes). The following are attributes of the mainSearchCriteria class and classes associated with it:<list role="unordered"><item>MainSearchCriteria.code: the clinical concept itself as a CE data type. Any code system MAY be used, but recommended code systems are: Problems = SNOMED-CT (others such as  MeSH, ICD-9CM, and ICD-10 can also be used); Meds = RxNorm (NDC can also be used); Lab tests = LOINC. <p>CE data type restrictions for mainSearchCriteria.code: <emph>displayName</emph> SHALL be always present, thereby information resources that don't support a given code system can still process the request using <emph>displayName </emph>as a search keyword; <emph>code</emph> MAY be used, but if present, <emph>codeSystem</emph> SHALL be present; <emph>originalText</emph> represents the human readable representation of the code as displayed to the user in the EHR and SHOULD be used only if different than the <emph>displayName</emph>.</p></item><item><emph role="strong">SeverityObservation </emph>class: specifies the interpretation of a lab result (e.g., 'high', 'low', 'abnormal', 'normal'). Used to support Infobuttons where the MainSearchCriteria consists of a lab result. Supports questions such as "what are the causes of <emph role="strong">high</emph> serum potassium?"					<list role="unordered"><item>SeverityObservation.code: code of the observation interpretation. SHOULD use the ObservationInterpretation code system.</item></list></item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">SubTopic:</emph> narrows down the search criteria by specifying a subdomain (e.g., indications, contra-indications, dose) of interest related to the MainSearchCriteria. In Infobutton implementations, the SubTopic may be selected by the user from an Infobutton page that presents a list of questions that are relevant to a specific context (e.g., "what are the <emph role="strong">contra-indications</emph> of digoxin", "what are the <emph role="strong">adverse effects</emph> of digoxin?").<list role="unordered"><item>SubTopic.code: code of the subtopic. MAY use MeSH (qualifiers subset) as the code system.<p>CE data type restrictions for SubTopic.code: <emph>displayName </emph>SHALL be always present, thereby information resources that don't support a given code system can still process the request using <emph>displayName </emph>as a search keyword; <emph>code </emph>is optional, but if present, <emph>codeSystem </emph>SHALL be present; <emph>originalText </emph>represents the human readable representation of the code as displayed to the user by the Infobutton application and SHOULD be used only if different than the <emph>displayName</emph>.</p></item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">TaskContext:</emph> the task that the user is trying to perform in the clinical information system when the Infobutton is clicked, initiating the Infobutton transaction (e.g., order entry, lab results, problem list, medications list)			<list role="unordered"><item>TaskContext.code: code of the task. SHOULD use task context code system (not included in this ballot, was submitted to RIM harmonization in November 2006).</item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">Encounter:</emph> information about the type of patient encounter (e.g., inpatient, outpatient) in which the Infobutton transaction takes place. 		<list role="unordered"><item>Encounter.code: code of the type of encounter. SHOULD use subset of RoleCode.ServiceDeliveryLocationRoleType [hospital=S10602; outpatient facility= S10589].</item><item><emph role="strong">DeliveryLocation:</emph> facility where the Infobutton transaction takes place. MAY be used by the filler of the request (DSS) to identify potential local information resources (e.g., local protocols) that are specific to the facility where the patient care is being delivered.					<list role="unordered"><item>DeliveryLocation.id: identifier of the facility where the patient care takes place.</item></list></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">InfobuttonEventNotification Participants</emph></p><p>This section describes participants of the InfobuttonEventNotification RMIM.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">AssignedEntity</emph>: entity (e.g., institution) that initiated the request. MAY be used by DSSs to determine the information resources that the requesting entity has access to. Also allows the identification of an individual within the institution, so that personal preferences can be considered by the DSS when processing the request.<list role="unordered"><item>AssignedEntity.name: username used by the entity (typically as part of an institutional subscription to an information resource)</item><item>AssignedEntity.certificateText: password associated with the username of the entity</item><item><emph role="strong">Organization</emph>: the entity that initiated the request					<list role="unordered"><item>Organization.id: identifier of the organization where the request was initiated</item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">AuthorizedPerson</emph>: the individual that initiated the request					<list role="unordered"><item>AuthorizedPerson.name: username of the person who initiated the request. MAY be used so that the DSS or information resource can apply personal preferences during the user's session.</item></list></item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">PatientContext</emph>: information about the patient that MAY be used by the DSS as context to predict the user's information needs or by the information resource to narrow down the search criteria. <list role="unordered"><item>PatientPerson.administrativeGenderCode: gender of the patient involved in the request. SHOULD use AdministrativeGender code system.</item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">PerformerChoice:</emph> defines the type of Participants that act as the "performer" (user who initiated the Infobutton request) and "informationRecipient" (person who will consume the requested information) of the request. Can be instantiated as a <emph role="strong">Patient</emph> or <emph role="strong">HealthCareProvider</emph> class. When a care provider initiates the Infobutton request, seeking information to fulfill his/her own information needs, both the performer and informationRecipient SHALL be associated with a <emph role="strong">HealthCareProvider</emph>. When a care provider initiates the Infobutton request, but looking for educational information to be given to the patient, the performer SHALL be associated with a <emph role="strong">HealthCareProvider</emph> and the informationRecipient SHALL be associated with a <emph role="strong">Patient</emph>. When a patient is looking for information to fulfill her own information needs, both the performer and the informationProvider SHALL be associated a <emph role="strong">Patient</emph>.		</item><item><emph role="strong">Age</emph>: age of the patient			<list role="unordered"><item>Age.code: code representing that the observation refers to the patient's age. Code SHALL be fixed to "30525-0" (LOINC code representing the "age" observation); codeSystem SHALL be fixed to "2.16.840.1.113883.6.1"; codeSystemName SHALL be fixed to "LN"; displayName SHALL be fixed to "AGE".</item><item>Age.value: age of the patient. SHALL be expressed in one of the following units (per the Unified Code for Units of Measure): years (a), months (mo), weeks (wk), days (d), or hours (h).</item></list></item><item><emph role="strong">AgeGroup</emph>: a coded value representing a predefined age interval.			<list role="unordered"><item>AgeGroup.code: code representing that the observation refers to the patient's age group. Code SHALL be fixed to "46251-5" (LOINC code representing the "age group" observation); codeSystem SHALL be fixed to "2.16.840.1.113883.6.1"; codeSystemName SHALL be fixed to "LN"</item><item>AgeGroup.value: code representing the age group of the patient. SHOULD use MeSH age groups. </item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">PerformerChoice Relationships</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">LanguageCommunication</emph>: language of the performer / informationRecipient. In implementations, language of the performer MAY be used by to determine the language of the individual who initiated the Infobutton request, while language of the informationRecipient MAY be used to determine the language of the individual who will consume the content. For example, when a clinician looks for patient education information, the clinician's language can be an English speaker, while the patient is a Spanish speaker. In this case, the screen dialog between the computer and the clinicians can be done in English, but the requested patient education content retrieved in Spanish.<list role="unordered"><item>LanguageCommunication.code: SHALL use HumanLanguage (ISO639-2) code system.</item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Note about the use of CE data type</emph>: all attributes that are based on the CE data type, except MainSearchCriteria.code and SubTopic.code (specific restriction rules are specified in the respective sections of these attributes), SHALL have a <emph>code</emph>, <emph>codeSystem</emph>, and <emph>displayName</emph>. </p></descriptive><diagref ref="REDS_RM010001UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="REDS_HD100001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_HD100001UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="hmds-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="hdop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="REDS_HD100001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Notification" familiarName="Infobutton Event Notification" parent="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" id="REDS_HD100001UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="10|20|99|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-10-24T13:15:38"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="REDS_HD100001UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Clinical Decision Support" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Message Model" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Act Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="msgs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><msgtype identifier="REDS_MT010001UV01" name="Act Event Notification" familiarName="Event Notification" parent="REDS_HD100001UV01-hmd" id="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sortPrefix="99ACT|20|99|NOTIFICATION" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-06-05T11:33:58"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="REDS_HD100001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_HD100001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Information Resource Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Interactions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="ints-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="inop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="REDS_IN010001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Notification" familiarName="Infobutton Event Notification" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|20|99|05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:47:19"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_IN010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" id="desc-REDS_IN010001UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-11-08T16:47:19"><p> Infobutton request initiated by the EHR (typically as a result of a user clicking on an Infobutton). The request is sent to the DSS.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Electronic Health Record" refFamiliarName="Electronic Health Record" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Decision Support System" refFamiliarName="Decision Support System" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_TE010001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="REDS_IN010002UV01" name="Infobutton Event Notification" familiarName="Information Resource Event Notification" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|20|99|05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-11-08T18:40:39"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_IN010002UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" id="desc-REDS_IN010002UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-11-08T18:40:39"><p>In this interaction, the DSS sends a request for content to the information resource. </p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Decision Support System" refFamiliarName="Decision Support System" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="REDS_AR010003UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Information Resource" refFamiliarName="Information Resource" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010003UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_TE010001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

