<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/4/2008 3:58:17 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/4/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-REPC_DO000000UV"><head>REPC_DO000000UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="request_mood" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:12:35"><label>Request Mood</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:12:35"><p>'Request' is 'A request or order for a service is an intent directed from a placer (request author) to a fulfiller (service performer).' - HL7 RIM Definition</p><p>When combined with the Act Care Provision and a Performer, the Request Mood of the Act distinguishes whether the performer is requested to take on responsibility for care.  </p></def></gitem><gitem id="author" lastEdit="2005-06-23T16:14:54"><label>Author</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-06-23T16:14:54"><p>Author is 'A party that originates an act and therefore has responsibility for the information 
given in the act and ownership of this Act. Example: the report writer, the person writing the act 
definition, the guideline author, the placer of an order, the EKG cart (device) creating a report, etc. 
Every Act should have an Author...' -HL7 RIM Definition</p><p>When combined with the Care Provision Act, the implication is that the author 
	has current responsibility for Care Provision or responsibility for coordination of Care Provision 
	to the Targets of Care. Two use cases are important: </p><p>1) When the author and performer are the same, then the statement of 
		responsibility regards the author as performer.</p><p>2) When the author and performer are the same, then the statement of 
		responsibility regards the author as performer. </p><p>When the author and performer are different, then 
		the statement of responsibility regards the performer.</p><p>The set of use cases implied is that the responsibility for care is being:</p><p>1) Started or continued by the author (mood = event), a)for the author or b)for another performer</p><p>2) Requested form another performer (mod = request)</p><p>Promised by the author (mood = promise)</p><p>Rejected by the author (mood = event)</p><p>Discontinued by the author (mood = event), a) for the author or b) for another performer</p></def></gitem><gitem id="patient_care_responsibility" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:11:21"><label>Patient Care Responsibility</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:11:21"><p>Most governments describe the accountability a care provider has for a person under care. Although the specifics of this responsibility vary from jurisdiction to jurisdiction, the concept is general at the international level. In many cases, this accountability is present even without personal contact between the care provider and the patient or delivery of services, e.g. responsibility of a public health clinic for a population of patients; an enrollment of a patient in the patient panel of a physician.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="mood" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:15"><label>Mood</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:15"><p>'Mood' is 'A code distinguishing whether an Act is conceived of as a factual statement or in some other manner as a command, possibility, etc.' - HL7 RIM Definition  </p><p>When combined with the Act Care Provision and a Performer, the Mood of the Act distinguishes whether the performer actually has (or had) Responsibility for Care, whether the performer is requested to take on responsibility, or whether the performer is promising to take on responsibility for care. </p><p>Mood for other Acts in the DMIM may take on the myriad of moods that are described in the HL7 RIM documentation under values for "moodCode."</p></def></gitem><gitem id="findings" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:08:07"><label>Findings</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:08:07"><p>'The results of an investigation'-Webster</p><p>'an observation; a condition discovered'--Dorland</p></def></gitem><gitem id="workflow" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:18:54"><label>Workflow</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:18:54"><p>The sequence of activities by an individual that is required to complete a specific business process.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="pertinent_information" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:11:39"><label>Pertinent Information</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:11:39"><p>An HL7 Act Relationship that asserts a 'very unspecific relationship from one item of clinical information to another. It does not judge about the role the pertinent information plays.' - HL7 RIM definition</p></def></gitem><gitem id="clinical_decision_support" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:06:14"><label>Clinical decision support</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:06:14"><p>The ability to use data to discover/justify the proper activities planned for a patient.
</p></def></gitem><gitem id="event_mood" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:07:43"><label>Event Mood</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:07:43"><p>'Event' is 'A service that actually happens, may be an ongoing service or a documentation of a past service.' - HL7 RIM Definition  </p><p>When combined with the Act Care Provision and a Performer, the Event Mood of the Act distinguishes whether the performer actually has (or had) Responsibility for Care.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_record_summary" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:00"><label>Health Record Summary</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:00"><p>A judgment or assessment based on parts of a health record that produces a shortened version of the parts assessed.</p><p>-based on a definition from Australia's HealthConnect project </p></def></gitem><gitem id="outcome" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:49"><label>Outcome</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:10:49"><p>The observation on the subject made following a specific intervention or collection of interventions on the subject or related subjects - paraphrased from the Nursing Terminology Summit.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="episode_of_care" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:07:21"><label>Episode of Care</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:07:21"><p>"Encounter" is an HL7 Class that describes 'An interaction between a patient and healthcare participant(s) for the purpose of providing patient service(s) or assessing the health status of a patient.' - HL7 RIM Definition</p><p>Episode of Care is a collection of one or more encounters that address the same target of care and that include a relationship to the same Episode of Illness or Condition</p></def></gitem><gitem id="promise_mood" lastEdit="2005-03-15T11:47:35"><label>Promise Mood</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T11:47:35"><p>'Promise' is 'An intent to perform a service that has the strength of a commitment, i.e., other parties may rely on the originator of such promise that said originator will see to it that the promised act will be fulfilled. A promise can be either solicited or unsolicited.' - HL7 RIM Definition </p><p> When combined with the Act Care Provision and a Performer, the Promise Mood of the Act distinguishes whether the performer is promising to take on responsibility for care. </p></def></gitem><gitem id="care_provider" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:05:10"><label>Care Provider</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:05:10"><p>"Performer" is an HL7 Participation that identifies 'A person who actually and principally carries out the action...may be the patient in self-care...' -HL7 RIM Definition</p><p>When combined with the Care Provision Act, the post-coordinated concept is "Care Provider."</p></def></gitem><gitem id="collaborating" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:06:28"><label>Collaborating</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:06:28"><p>'To work jointly with others'-Webster</p><p>This use assumes the care providers are collaborating around the care of a specific subject.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="health_record_extracts" lastEdit="2005-03-15T16:15:47"><label>Health Record Extracts</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-15T16:15:47"><p>Portions of the HL7 Electronic Health Record (EHR) Domain that are copied from the larger EHR for a specific purpose.</p><p>--based on health record terminology from Australia's HealthConnect project</p></def></gitem><gitem id="care_provision" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:05:53"><label>Care Provision</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:05:53"><p>"CareProvision" is an HL7 Act that describes 'the taking on of the responsibility by a performer for care activities of a subject of care.</p><p>Discussion: The care event can exist without any care actions having taken place. The scope of the care is identified by Act.code.</p><p>For example:</p><p>Preferred primary care provision: the primary care physician being the primary performer participation, author being the patient;</p><p>Referral from general practitioner to specialist (a PCPR in request mood, where the author participant is the GP, and the primary performer participation is the specialist);</p><p>A case manager to a patient or group of patients;</p><p>Assigning nurses to patients each shift;</p><p>Care of herd of animals;</p><p>Care of contaminated environmental site;</p><p>Care of a device. </p></def></gitem><gitem id="targets_of_care" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:12:56"><label>Targets of Care</label><def domainid="REPC_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-03-16T11:12:56"><p>'Subject' is an HL7 Participation that identifies the 'The principle target that the service acts on, e.g. the patient in physical examination, a specimen in a lab observation. May also be a patient's family member (teaching) or a device or room (cleaning, disinfecting, housekeeping). Note: not all direct targets are subjects. Consumables and devices used as tools for a service are not subjects. However, a device may be a subject of a maintenance service. '- HL7 RIM definition.</p><p>'Indirect Target' is an HL7 Participation differentiated from Direct Target by 'A Target that is not substantially present in the act and which is not directly affected by the act, but which will be a focus of the record or documentation of the act.' HL7 examples include 'record target,' which 'indicates whose medical record holds the documentation of this act. This is especially important when the subject of the service is not the patient himself.' - HL7 RIM definition.</p><p>When combined with the Care Provision Act, the post-coordinated concepts are 'Targets of Care.'</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

