<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/5/2008 4:03:40 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/5/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-PRPM_DO000000UV"><head>PRPM_DO000000UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="qualification" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:39"><label>Qualification (Definition and Instatiation)</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:39"><p>The supertype/parent of Credential.  A statement of a specific capability, competency, and/or capacity which may either be asserted by or required for a Role or Position.  An attribute of a Qualification may be whether or not a scoper Party requires the Qualification for an Initial Application to a Role/Position, as opposed to requiring it for Reapplication to the named Role or Position.  A Qualification is differentiated from a Credential by virtue of the fact that a Credential carries the requirement of both the assertion and the validation ('vetting') of the capability, competency, and/or capacity, whereas the Qualification is simply the assertion per se.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="privilege" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:27"><label>Privilege</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:27"><p>A subtype of Responsibility that is differentiated from Responsibility by virtue of the fact that it is associated with specific Credentials rather than simply Qualifications.  Although Privileges may be associated with a Position (e.g. the Position of Attending Physician may be associated with Admitting Privileges), a Person in a Role may, in addition, apply for other Privileges.  Each application involves at least one other Party who must review the Person-in-a-Role's specific Credentials required in order for the Privilege to be granted.   Requirements may be defined by the Granting Party and/or by external organizations.  NOTE:  A Privilege differs from a Responsibility in that the association/assignment of a Privilege to a Person-in-a-Role requires the interaction of at least two instances of Party, i.e. the Person-in-a-Role (who may or may not be in a Position) requesting the Privilege and the Person/Organization-in-a-Role granting the Privilege.  In the sense that it requires a 2-Party interaction,' the concept Privilege is therefore similar to Credential.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="credential" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:54"><label>Credential (Definition and Instantiation)</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:54"><p>An abstract concept (i.e. there are no physical instances of Credential per se) that represents the various collections of data associated with a verifiable claim by a Person or Organization as to one or more skills, abilities, education, experience, etc.  A Credential collects (at minimum) the date/time of issuance and an associated expiration date after which the credential must be renewed to remain valid. The important differentiator between a Credential (or, more correctly, one of its concrete subtypes) and a Qualification is that the former (Credential) can always be verified in terms of the Credential being issued by/associated with a 'credentialing organization' responsible for issuing an instance of a particular credential to an instance of a Party, whereas the latter (Qualification) is simply a statement by the Party of a particular skill, ability, etc.  (NOTE:  The notion of 'verifiable' that differentiates a Credential from a Qualification is similar to the difference between a Responsibility and a Privilege in that both a Credential and a Privilege involve a formal relationship between at least two instances of Party, whereas a Qualification and a Responsibility do not possess this level of 'contract' formalism.)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="animal" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:42"><label>Animal</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:42"><p>A subtype of Living Subject representing any animal-of-interest to the Personnel Management domain.  An instance of an animal is uniquely identifiable and, as a result, able to be certified, licensed, or otherwise credentialed by an appropriate Credentialing Authority for the purpose of involvement in one or more healthcare processes.  Examples include a German Shepard trained as a seeing eye dog, or a kitten licensed to a patient for comfort therapy.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="application_or_assignment" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:10"><label>Application or Assignment</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:10"><p>The collection of data (structured and unstructured) that a Person submits to an organization in the context of requesting or applying for/being assigned to a Position.  (NOTE:  An Application does NOT include the Person's Qualifications or various Credentials (which are represented explicitly elsewhere in the model), but is simply a signed or otherwise verified statement by the Person applying for the Position that the data submitted in the context of the application process (including the Person's Qualifications/Credentials) are complete, accurate, etc.  An Attestation is normally date/time stamped.)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="certificate_of_verification" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:21"><label>Certificate of Verification</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:21"><p>A collection of data documenting that a specific instance of a Credential has been verified/validated in association with the requirement for that credential for either an Assignment of a Party in a Role to a Position or the requirement for a particular instance of a Credential in order for a Party in a Role to qualify for a specific instance of a Privilege.  A Certificate of Verification will minimally include a definitive identification of the verifier, a date/time stamp of verification, and (optionally) a structured or unstructured statement of the verification process, contacts, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="person" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:18"><label>Person</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:18"><p>- A subtype of Living Subject representing single human being who, in the context of the Personnel Management domain, must also be uniquely identifiable through one or more legal documents (e.g. Driver's License, Birth Certificate, etc.)  Instances of Person include:  John Smith, RN, Mary Jones, MD, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="license" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:59"><label>License</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:59"><p>A subtype of Credential that documents that an instance of a Party (Person or Organization) has satisfied a set of criteria (skills, knowledge, etc.) defined by the Organization or Person issuing the License. The difference between a License and a Certificate is found in the amount of legal/regulatory context surrounding the issuing organization, a License typically being issued by known regulatory agencies (e.g. State government), a Certificate being issued by a non-regulatory institution (e.g. school, continuing education center, etc.)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="experience" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:12"><label>Experience</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:12"><p>A subtype of Credential that documents a particular instance of Party's (most often a Person's) accomplishments, skills, time of involvement, etc. in a particular context, usually a Position or Role.  QUESTION:  Is this where Internship, Residency, etc. go?</p></def></gitem><gitem id="responsibility" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:23"><label>Responsibility</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:23"><p>A defined task, associated with a Position.  A given Responsibiltiy may be Required (Y/N) A responsibility may be required or optional.  The optionality of a particular Responsibility as part of the definition of a Position may ultimately end up being Required when a particular Person is Assigned to a Position.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="organization" lastEdit="2004-11-30T10:43:40"><label>Organization</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-30T10:43:40"><p>A formalized group of persons with a common purpose (e.g. administrative, legal, political, etc.) and infrastructure necessary to achieve said purpose..  An Organization is recognized as an entity from the perspective of one or more authorities and/or other organizations external to the Organization-of-Interest including legal, social, etc.  Instances of Organization include:  Joint Commission for Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations, Province of British Columbia, California State Board of Medical Examiners,  etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="relationship" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:09"><label>Relationship</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:09"><p>A class used to collect instances of a class as either Source or Target of the intervening Relationship instance</p></def></gitem><gitem id="time-based_criterion" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:55"><label>Time-based Criterion</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:55"/></gitem><gitem id="education" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:09"><label>Education</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:09"><p>A subtype of Credential that documents a particular Person's accomplishments, awards, skills, time of involvement, etc. in the context of a recognized educational institution (e.g. high school, college, graduate school, non-degree granting training programs, vocational training, etc.)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="task_bundle" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:25"><label>Task Bundle</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:25"><p>Within the context of an instance of an Organization, a Position is a named collection of Responsibilities (including Privileges). A Position may exist without a Person in a Role being Assigned to that Position, i.e. a Position can be created/defined in terms of the Qualifications (including various forms of Credentials that a Person much have to qualify for an Assignment to that Position).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="assignment" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:14"><label>Assignment</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:14"><p>A collection of data documenting the association between an instance of a Party (normally a Person)  and a Position.  The minimal data in an Assignment are date/time of Assignment and Person/Organization making the Assignment.  An Assignment also usually includes a time period after which the Assignment is invalid and must be redone if the association between the Person and the Position is to continue.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="description" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:21"><label>Description</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:21"><p>A structured or non-structured collection of (usually) text that collectively defines an instance of a Position.  Examples include 'Job Descriptions' on file for the various Jobs/Job Titles within an Organization.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="party" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:12"><label>Party</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:12"><p>An abstract class that is the parent class for Organization and Person.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="living_subject" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:22:01"><label>Living Subject</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:22:01"><p>The abstract super-class (parent class) of Person and Animal</p></def></gitem><gitem id="role" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:20"><label>Role</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:20"><p>A named context in which a Party (usually, but not always, a Person) is identified in a context-of-interest.  Roles represent specific semantics involved in the relationship between two (and only two) instances of a Party:  one instance of a Party plays a Role scoped by another instance of a Party.  Note that the naming of the Role may be formal or informal within the organization, but that the identity of the instance of Person (or Organization) playing the Role does not end when the Role itself ends.  In addition, a Role specifies a competency, capability, and/or capacity which the Entity assuming the Role scoper piece of the relationship implicitly or explicitly acknowledges as being present/possessed by the Entity assuming the Role player portion of the relationship.  In particular, the Personnel Management domain is particularly interested in the various Roles associated with all aspects of healthcare delivery, as well as the various Acts by which a given Role is defined, identified, guaranteed, or acknowledged by the scoper Party.  (NOTE:  The more formal association of a Person in a Role Assigned to a Position with associated Responsibilities and/or Privileges is explicitly covered elsewhere in the Domain Analysis Model)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="capability" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:16"><label>Capability</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:16"><p>A quantitative, semi-quantitative, or qualitative assessment of the ability of an instance of a Party in a Role to perform and/or participate in a specific activity or task.  An a subtype of Credential, a Capability is assigned to an instance of a Party (the instance with the ability) by another instance of Party (the Person or Organization assessing the capability).  A Capability is often a specific (e.g. 'can do this task' (Person), or 'has 5 slots available' (Organization)).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="position" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:31"><label>Position</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-12-02T09:21:31"><p>Within the context of an instance of an Organization, a Position is a named collection of various duties, Responsibilities, and/or Privileges.  A Position may exist without a Person in a Role being Assigned to that Position, i.e. a Position can be created/defined in terms of the Qualifications (including various forms of Credentials that a Person much have to qualify for an Assignment to that Position).  A Position is considered a subtype of Role because of the common domain perspective that a 'base' or 'functional' role (e.g. Staff Physician) is often necessary before the (e.g. person) in a given 'base/functional' role can be assigned to other roles (e.g. Chair of Department of Cardiology, Director of ICU, etc.).  The collection of duties, responsibilities, and/or privileges associated with a given Position is, at minimum, contained in a Description associated with the Position.  The presence of a Description implies that the Position may exist ('be defined') irrespective of whether an instance of a Party in a Role has been assigned to the position.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="certificate" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:07"><label>Certificate</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:33:07"><p>A subtype of Credential that documents that an instance of a Party (Person or Organization) has satisfied a set of criteria (skills, knowledge, etc.) defined by the Organization or Person issuing the Certificate.  A Certificate is often viewed as 'less formal' than a Credential.  However, in this model, a Credential is an abstract concept that captures the notion of verifiable documentation various types of  skills, etc. claimed to be possessed by a Person or Organization (see Credential)</p></def></gitem><gitem id="criterion" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:43"><label>Criterion</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:31:43"><p>A rule which defines the manner in which a particular Qualification (including a Credential) or collection of Qualifications are associated with a given Position.  An instance of a Criterion may be either a Time-based Criterion (e.g. &lt;xxx&gt; for at least 3 years) or a Non-time-based Criterion (e.g. certified as either an &lt;x&gt; or a &lt;y&gt;).</p></def></gitem><gitem id="non-time-based_criterion" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:04"><label>Non-Time-based Criterion</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:04"/></gitem><gitem id="application" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:12"><label>Application</label><def domainid="PRPM_DO000000UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2003-11-18T09:32:12"><p>The collection of data (structured and unstructured) that a Person submits to an organization in the context of requesting or applying for/being assigned to a Position.  (NOTE:  An Application does NOT include the Person's Qualifications or various Credentials (which are represented explicitly elsewhere in the model), but is simply a signed or otherwise verified statement by the Person applying for the Position that the data submitted in the context of the application process (including the Person's Qualifications/Credentials) are complete, accurate, etc.  An Attestation is normally date/time stamped.)</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

