<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPORP" lastEdit="6/3/2008 3:46:38 PM" rendered="6/3/2008 3:46:53 PM">
	<header>
		<title>Domain: Regulated Products</title>
		<version>V 00-00</version>
		<ballot type="MixedContent" number="1"/>
		<date>6/3/2008</date>
		<authlist>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role>
				<name key="Helton, Ed">Ed Helton</name>
				<affiliation>SAS</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM PORP Publishing Facilitator</role>
				<name key="Leizear, Peggy">Peggy Leizear</name>
				<affiliation>US Food and Drug Administration</affiliation>
				<email xlink-form="simple" href="peggy.leizear@fda.hhs.gov" show="embed" actuate="auto">peggy.leizear@fda.hhs.gov</email>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role>
				<name key="Levin, Randy">Randy Levin</name>
				<affiliation>US Food and Drug Administration</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Primary Contributor</role>
				<name key="Rock, Jason">Jason Rock</name>
				<affiliation>GlobalSubmit, Inc</affiliation>
				<email xlink-form="simple" href="jason.rock@globalsubmit.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">jason.rock@globalsubmit.com</email>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Editor (SPL)</role>
				<name key="Schadow, Gunther">Gunther Schadow</name>
				<affiliation>Regenstrief Institute, Indiana University School of Informatics</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role>
				<name key="Tardiff, Barbara">Barbara Tardiff</name>
				<affiliation>Merck</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role>
				<name key="Tripp, Edward">Edward Tripp</name>
				<affiliation>Abbott</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>RCRIM Modeling and Methodology Coordinator</role>
				<name key="Walker, Mead">Mead Walker</name>
				<affiliation>Mead Walker Consulting</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author>
				<role>Primary Contributor</role>
				<name key="Walker, Mead">Mead Walker</name>
				<affiliation>Mead Walker Consulting</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authlist>
		<legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/>
	</header>
	<front>
		<div1 id="prefNotes">
			<head>Notes to Readers</head>
			<p>In the 2008 Normative Edition, the Regulated Products domain contains two "topics" as outlined below.</p>
			<p>Regulated Product Submission topic</p>
			<list role="unordered">
				<item>
					<p>Regulated Product Submission, Release 1 - ANSI Approved Standard</p>
				</item>
			</list>
			<p>Structured Product Labeling, Release 3 topic</p>
			<list role="unordered">
				<item>Structure Product Labeling, Release 3 -  - ANSI Approved Standard</item>
				<item>Structured Product Labeling Release 3 Implementation Guide - HL7 approved informative document</item>
			</list>
		</div1>
		<div1 id="navigate-divs">
			<head>Message Design Element Navigation</head>
			<artree role="NAVIGATE">
				<artreeitem>
					<rmimref role="rmim" ref="PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Regulated Product Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_RM000001UV01"/>
					<artreeitem>
						<hmdref role="hmd" ref="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Regulated Product Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD000001UV01"/>
						<artreeitem>
							<msgref role="msg" ref="PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Regulated Product Submission MT" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT000001UV01"/>
						</artreeitem>
					</artreeitem>
				</artreeitem>
				<artreeitem>
					<rmimref role="rmim" ref="PORP_RM050032UV03-rmi" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_RM050032UV03"/>
					<artreeitem>
						<hmdref role="hmd" ref="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD050032UV03"/>
						<artreeitem>
							<msgref role="msg" ref="PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT050032UV03"/>
						</artreeitem>
					</artreeitem>
				</artreeitem>
			</artree>
		</div1>
	</front>
	<body>
		<div1 id="intro-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" ballotStatus="MixedContent" ballotNumber="1">
			<head>Overview</head>
			<div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-07-28T10:34:45">
				<head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head>
				<p>This domain includes standards developed as part of the family of messages targeted for the exchange of information about regulated products and the exchange of the data needed to provide approval for such products.</p>
				<p>The principal contributor to this domain is the Regulated Clinical Research Information Management (RCRIM) technical committee.</p>
				<p>This committee supports the HL7 mission to create and promote its standards by developing standards to improve or enhance information management during research and regulatory evaluation of the safety and efficacy of therapeutic products or procedures worldwide.  The committee defines messages, document structures, and terminology to support the systems and processes used in the collection, storage, distribution, integration and analysis of such information.  The work of this committee will facilitate the availability of safe and effective therapies by improving the processes and efficiencies associated with regulated clinical research.</p>
				<p>
					<emph role="strong">SCOPE</emph>
				</p>
				<p>The Regulated Products domain currently contains specifications addressing Regulated Product Submission, and Structured Product Labeling. The topics in this domain support approval of regulated products that includes, but is not limited to, medical devices, drugs, biologics, veterinary medicine, and food and feed additives.</p>
			</div2>
		</div1>
		<dmimdivn identifier="dmims-PORP_DO000001UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="dmims-PORP_DO000001UV-ic"/>
		<subdivn identifier="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Regulated Product Submission Topic" familiarName="Regulated Product Submission" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="10" baseClass="Regulated Product Submission" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1">
			<descriptive identifier="intro-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Introduction" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="intro-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:24:04">
				<p>Regulatory authorities receive submissions to address a variety of regulatory issues. The information contained in these submissions is divided into numerous files (paper and electronic). Frequently, files in one submission are related to files in earlier submissions. Because the information is divided into numerous files sent over time, it is often difficult to efficiently process and review the information.</p>
				<p>The goal of the Regulated Product Submission message is to facilitate the processing and the review of submissions. Accordingly, the Regulated Product Submission Refined Message Information Model captures all information required for the efficient processing and review of regulatory submissions.</p>
				<p>Different product types have different table of contents; that is to say, different lists of topics that must be addressed within the submission.  However, the general data layouts of all regulated products are the same. Therefore, the objective of the Regulated Product Submission message is to define one message structure that can be used for all regulated products. It is intended that this message will be used, worldwide, for regulated products, including but not limited to, foods, medical devices, human therapeutics, and veterinary medicine.  It is important to note that the wide range of products that is contemplated leads to providing a generic structure for the actual specification.</p>
				<p>Please note that Regulated Product Submission is similar to the Medical Records Document Topic.  This is based on the fact that both require attention to needs for managing a complex set of documents.</p>
				<p>
					<emph role="strong">Scope</emph>
				</p>
				<p>The scope of the initial release of this standard is to define the message for submitting information to regulatory authorities. This message includes the contents of a regulatory submission and all information needed to process the submission message. This message is flexible enough to be used for regulatory submissions for any regulated product. Subsequent releases of the standard will provide information about the submission (e.g. information currently collected on application forms) in addition to information about the files in the submission.</p>
				<p>Although this message can be used for company-to-company communication, the initial intent of this message is for the communication from industry to regulatory authority.</p>
				<p>The Regulated Clinical Research Information Management Technical Committee invites anyone with additional requirements to submit content proposals for future releases of the standard.
</p>
			</descriptive>
			<storydivn identifier="sbs-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Storyboards" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="sbs-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="sstop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="sstop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<story identifier="PORP_ST000001UV01" name="Rps 01" familiarName="Managing Applications through Submission Units" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:25:46" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="purp-PORP_ST000001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="purp-PORP_ST000001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:25:46">
						<p>Over time, an application will typically consist of multiple submissions and regulatory assessments. For example, the marketing application for a drug product can generate multiple regulatory decisions. The first decision may support the initial marketing approval of the product for a specific indication. Subsequent regulatory decisions may approve or deny additional indications for the drug product. The application thus contains multiple submissions, each with their own regulatory action. Each of those submissions (e.g., initial marketing application, supplemental marketing application) would generally be comprised of multiple submissions units. </p>
						<p>A submission is made up of one or many submission units.
</p>
						<p>Note: the current specification does not support a message from the regulatory authority to applicant</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000001UV01" name="Rps Sn01" familiarName="Creating a new application and submission" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:15:51" class="inserted">
						<p>Acme Pharmaceuticals has prepared information relating to its new product - Global Fixit.  This information provides information about the quality, safety and effectiveness of the product, and consists of many files that Acme has collected over several years.  Acme has marshaled these files, which are designed to address a previously defined set of categories, into its first submission unit.  That first submission unit will be sent to a regulatory authority for marketing approval in that jurisdiction.  In this initial submission unit, the submission unit message identifies all of the submitted files, and indicates the document category or categories that the files belong.  This first submission unit commences the application and represents the first regulatory submission for that application. 
</p>
						<p>Since this is the initial submission unit for the application, each file in this submission unit is active.  The submission is then transmitted to the regulatory authority.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority receives the submission and validates the message for accuracy. The regulatory authority incorporates the message into their tracking\review system creating a new application, original submission, and the first submission unit to the original submission.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000002UV01" name="Rps Sn02" familiarName="Adding submission units to an existing submission" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:16:05" class="inserted">
						<p>Device Co. is planning on creating a pre-approval submission for a Class III PMA product. Device Co has already sent the original submission unit message and supporting files. However, new studies are available pertaining to the effectiveness of this device. Device Co will submit a new submission unit and the supporting files. This new submission unit will be linked as an amendment to the original submission.
The regulatory authority receives and validates this submission unit and then this submission unit is associated with the original submission
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000003UV01" name="Rps Sn03" familiarName="Creating a new submission to an application" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000003UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:17:56" class="inserted">
						<p>Device Co. is planning on creating a submission for a Class III product. Device Co. has already sent the original submission unit message (i.e., the original submission) and many amendments to the original submission.</p>
						<p>This product is going to be used for a different purpose than stated in the original submission so a new Submission must be initiated. Device Co will submit the new submission and supporting files containing the relevant information that supports the new use of the product. As required by the Regulatory Authority, this new submission and the original submission will be linked together under the same application.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority receives and validates this submission unit for this new submission. This new submission (e.g., referred to as a supplement or variation) and the original submission are both associated to the same application.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note</emph>: In most cases, supplements/variations can only be created after the original has been approved.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000004UV01" name="Rps Sn04" familiarName="Modular Reviews" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000004UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:19:51" class="inserted">
						<p>In some regulatory processes, it is acceptable for the Applicant to provide information to the regulatory authority in defined reviewable units. Generally, these units of information support a particular discipline (e.g., clinical) and provide the opportunity to expedite some regulatory review processes.
</p>
						<p>For example, Acme Pharmaceutics has discovered a potential cure for cancer and received permission to submit a continuous marketing application. Acme now has the ability to send information in predefined reviewable units.
</p>
						<p>Acme creates a submission unit for transmission to the regulatory authority that addresses the clinical modules. Since it is expected that the regulatory authority review may turn up questions related to particular modules, Acme makes sure that the submission unit indicates which type of module it addresses.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority processes this submission unit and associates the unit to the correct submission.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000005UV01" name="Rps Sn05" familiarName="One submission unit to multiple applications" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000005UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:35:33" class="inserted">
						<p>In certain regulatory processes, the same documentation may need to be submitted to multiple applications. 
</p>
						<p>Acme Manufacturing produces an annual report that pertains to multiple active applications.  The company submits one submission unit and applies that unit to each application that requires the annual report.
The regulatory authority processes this submission unit and associates it to all relevant applications.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000006UV01" name="Rps Sn06" familiarName="One submission unit to multiple submissions" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000006UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:23:32" class="inserted">
						<p>In certain regulatory processes, the same documentation may need to be submitted to multiple submissions. 
</p>
						<p>Acme Manufacturing changes some CMC processes that pertains to multiple active submissions for a product.  The company submits one CMC submission unit and applies that unit to each submission that it pertains to.
The regulatory authority processes this submission unit and associates it to all relevant submissions.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000000UV01" name="Rps Sn07" familiarName="Withdrawing a submission unit" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000000UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2007-03-08T07:14:16" class="deleted">
						<p>During the review of a submission, it may be necessary for the Applicant to withdraw the submission from further review. 
</p>
						<p>Acme Pharmaceuticals executives have spent time reviewing the original Global Fixit submission unit and determined that the submission unit that was sent to support the Global Fixit submission contains a host of errors.  Therefore it would be inappropriate for the regulatory authority to use the files contained within the submission unit for its review.  As a result, Acme decides to withdraw the submission unit from consideration.  A transmission is sent that indicates the submission unit has been withdrawn.  The status code for the previous submission unit will be set to obsolete.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority processes this submission unit and marks all file references provided by this submission unit as obsolete.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000008UV01" name="Rps Sn08" familiarName="Withdrawing a submission" parent="PORP_ST000001UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000001UV01-PORP_SN000008UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|01" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:26:41" class="inserted">
						<p>During the review of a submission, it may be necessary for the Applicant to withdraw the submission from further review or to preempt an unfavorable action by the regulatory authority.
</p>
						<p>Subsequent to the original submission of the Global Fixit submission, Acme scientists are able to spend time reviewing the outcome of ongoing studies of Global Fixit's efficacy.  It turns out, after statistical review, that the product is not particularly effective.  As a result, Acme wishes to withdraw the submission from consideration.  A submission unit is created to withdraw the submission and all related submission units; it is transmitted to the regulatory authority.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority processes this submission unit message and marks the submission and related submission units as obsolete.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<diagref ref="PORP_ST000001UV01.gif"/>
					<intref ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01" sequence="1"/>
				</story>
				<story identifier="PORP_ST000002UV01" name="Rps 02" familiarName="Managing the contents of submission units" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:26:40" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="purp-PORP_ST000002UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="purp-PORP_ST000002UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:26:40">
						<p>
 A submission unit is made up of one submission unit message and many files. Properly defined, the submission unit message concept enables companies to create new submission units from any combination of new and previously submitted files. The submission unit message is processed by the regulatory authority and is integrated into their tracking/review system.</p>
						<p>Note: the current specification does not support a message from the regulatory authority to applicant</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000009UV01" name="Rps Sn09" familiarName="Adding new files to a submission" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000009UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:55:17" class="inserted">
						<p>The results of ongoing studies related to Global Fixit are now available; and these results show that the product is even more useful than previously thought.  As a result, Acme decides to add this information to the files that were previously submitted in support of the Global Fixit submission.  A new submission unit is created that refers to the additional files (i.e., the new study results) and appropriate file references to relate this new information to the existing information. The submission unit is transmitted to the regulatory authority. The regulatory authority processes this submission unit.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> A submission unit message contains many file references.  When a submission unit message is provided in support of a submission, individual file references can either be added to the submission, supersede existing file references in the submission, append existing file references, or may mark specific files as obsolete from the submission.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000010UV01" name="Rps Sn10" familiarName="Replacing a previously submitted file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000010UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:55:38" class="inserted">
						<p>The review process for the Global Fixit submission has extended over a substantial amount of time, and Acme has found that new information relevant to the submission has been received.  For example, the original submission contained a summary of clinical pharmacology information derived from a series of studies using human biomaterial, and several new studies contain information that requires changes to this summary.  Therefore, researchers working for the company have rewritten this summary and submits a new submission unit with the new file marked as a replacement to the previous file.
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority processes this submission unit. If information relevant to the submission was not submitted in the original submission unit, the submission might have been non-filed or refused to accept.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> A submission unit message contains many file references.  When a submission unit message is provided in support of a submission, individual file references can either be added to the submission, supersede existing file references in the submission, append an existing file reference, or may mark the file as obsolete from the submission.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000011UV01" name="Rps Sn11" familiarName="Removing a previously submitted file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000011UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:34:31" class="inserted">
						<p>Global Fixit has been manufactured at two locations, Big Factory and Little Factory.  Acme Manufacturing now wishes to concentrate all its manufacturing at Big Factory.  Therefore it is necessary to inform the regulatory authority of this change and to update the submission to ignore all information related to manufacturing taking place at Small Factory.  Therefore Acme creates a submission unit to inform the regulatory authority to ignore all files that relate to the manufacture at Small Factory. 
The regulatory authority processes this submission unit.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> This method can also be applied to logical documents consisting of multiple physical files. 
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000012UV01" name="Rps Sn12" familiarName="Replacing one file with multiple files" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000012UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:42:00" class="inserted">
						<p>The Calming Myst submission, a medication for heart burn, included the inclusion of a drug-substance file.  However, Acme has now decided that it needs to break this file into several smaller files for better file management.  In essence, the company wants regulatory authority to review the drug-substance information in the more granular form.  A new submission unit is created that contains multiple drug-substance files to meet the documentation requirement for drug substance information.  Each file is marked as a replacement for the previously submitted drug-substance file.  The original drug-substance file is marked as obsolete (or replaced).
</p>
						<p>The regulatory authority processes this submission unit.</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> The life cycle of the new more granular file is linked to the original summary file life cycle.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000013UV01" name="Rps Sn13" familiarName="Adding an addendum to a file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000013UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:56:12" class="inserted">
						<p>Before the clinical study begins, Acme would like to add several new (or not previously submitted) pages to a sample case report form file. The addition will allow reviewers at the regulatory authority to have this new information. The company prepares a submission unit that contains a file with only the new pages.  The submission unit message marks this file as an addendum to the previously submitted case report form file. The addendum is considered a separate file that has its own lifecycle
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> A submission unit message contains many file references.  When a submission unit message is provided in support of a submission, individual file references can either be added to the submission, supersede existing file references in the submission, append an existing file reference, or may mark the file as obsolete from the submission.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000014UV01" name="Rps Sn14" familiarName="Replacing an addendum" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000014UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:56:23" class="inserted">
						<p>Acme employee, Fred Firestone, has carried out further review of the recently submitted addendum to the sample case report form.  As a result of his work, the company realizes that it needs to replace the addendum in order to improve the case report form.  Therefore, an additional submission unit is created that contains a new addendum file to replace the previously submitted one.  The new addendum is linked to the old one, and marked as a replacement. 
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> Addendum files has a life cycle independent of the file they are added to.  If a future submission unit replaces the addendum file, the new addendum file would amend the same original file.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000015UV01" name="Rps Sn15" familiarName="Replacing a file and an addendum" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000015UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:58:11" class="inserted">
						<p>Further review of the - much changed - sample case report form mentioned above, leads Acme's Submission Control Branch to determine that the regulatory authority's review task would be eased if all the contents of the case report form were included in a single file.  That is to say, it would be better to support the documentation requirements with a single file, rather than having an original file along with one or more addenda.  Acme would like the regulatory authority to only review the new consolidated file, and it would like the regulatory authority to be aware that the new file replaces both previously submitted files.  A new submission unit is created that contains the new summary file, and marks it as a replacement for both the previous sample case report form file and the addendum.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000016UV01" name="Rps Sn16" familiarName="Adding one file to multiple logical documents" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000016UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:59:16" class="inserted">
						<p>Acme Manufacturing has prepared a submission for a product to be marketed to mountain climbers - known as High Altitude Fixit.  One component of the submission will be a protocol file that pertains to three different studies in the submission.  It documents the protocol that was followed during those studies.  When the High Altitude Fixit submission unit is prepared, it will contain, among other files, the protocol file and other documentation providing the results of the three studies.  Each of the three studies references the protocol file.  The submission unit transmission contains only one copy of the protocol file. 
The regulatory authority processes this submission unit.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000017UV01" name="Rps Sn17" familiarName="Adding files that were previously removed" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000017UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:59:28" class="inserted">
						<p>Several years ago, Acme submitted a submission to market a medication for heart burn known as Calming Myst, which was to be produced under license from a European manufacturer.  However, all the files related to the earlier submission unit have been marked as ignore because Acme was never able to come to a final arrangement with the manufacturer for the production of the product.
</p>
						<p>However, new management of the European firm is more agreeable, and Acme is confident that it will have the Calming Myst contract in hand by early next year.  As a result, Acme would like to reactivate the European manufacturing files for regulatory authority review.  A submission unit message is created that refers to the previously submitted files and reactivates them for regulatory review.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> The all files associated with this manufacturer has been reactivated. The complete lifecycle of all logical documents associated with this manufacturer are also reactivated.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000018UV01" name="Rps Sn18" familiarName="Changing the category of a submitted file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000018UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:38:42" class="inserted">
						<p>Subsequent to the original Global Fixit submission, Acme researchers realize that an analytical procedure file had been mistakenly categorized as the protocol document of one of the studies in that previous submission's units.  This was a mistake, since it should have been categorized as an analytical procedure document. The company wants to inform the regulatory authority to change the category assignment of the file.  The submission unit that Acme transmits to the regulatory authority is designed to inform the regulatory authority that the previously referenced protocol actually should be referenced as an analytical procedure. The procedure file is not re-transmitted.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000019UV01" name="Rps Sn19" familiarName="Referencing files from other applications" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000019UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:43:38" class="inserted">
						<p>The European manufacturer who produces the Calming Myst product, has done previous business with Acme manufacturing for a number of years.  In a previous application - for Calming Balm - Acme had submitted information for that manufacturer that is relevant to the Calming Myst application.  Since the regulatory authority already has the files for the manufacturer, Acme decides to reference those files in the new application.  The Calming Myst submission unit contains references to those previously submitted files.  The submission unit does not contain copies of the previously submitted files. The regulatory authority processes this submission unit. It is possible for the reviewers to access the referenced files as if they had been submitted in this submission unit.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> It is possible for the reviewers to access the referenced files as if they had been submitted in this submission unit.
</p>
						<p>This method applies to studies, logical files, or any other file or groups of files that the company has previously sent to the regulatory authority.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000020UV01" name="Rps Sn20" familiarName="Replacing files referenced from other applications" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000020UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-07-05T14:45:43" class="inserted">
						<p>Subsequent to the Calming Myst application, the European manufacturer decides to move its manufacturing operations to another facility and to introduce advanced technologies to the processes. This requires changing the manufacturer information in all the applications related to the products they manufacture; in particular, it applies to both the Calming Balm and Calming Myst submissions.  Acme will submit a new submission unit as part of the Calming Balm submission that contains the updated files.  A new submission unit for the Calming Myst product is submitted as well.  In that submission unit, references to the new files are included, but the actual files are not.
The regulatory authority processes this submission unit. It is possible for the reviewers to access the referenced file as it was submitted in this submission unit.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> This method applies to files, logical documents or any other files or groups of files that the company has previously sent to the regulatory authority.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000021UV01" name="Rps Sn21" familiarName="Replacing one file in multiple logical documents" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000021UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:04:21" class="inserted">
						<p>In the High Altitude Fixit submission, Acme had previously submitted a protocol file that pertained to three different studies within the application.  Since that time, investigators under contract to Acme have updated the protocol file specifically for one of the three studies.  However, these changes are not relevant to the other two studies.  Acme would like the regulatory authority to review the new protocol file for the one study, while continuing to review the previous protocol file for the other two.  A new submission unit is created that has the new protocol file marked as a replacement for the relevant study.  The submission unit contains no reference to the other two studies.  As a result, regulatory authority continues to review the previous protocol file for them.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000022UV01" name="Rps Sn22" familiarName="Replacing multiple files with one file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000022UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:04:33" class="inserted">
						<p>The original Global Fixit submission unit included a safety file.  In a later submission unit for the same submission, the same safety file was mistakenly submitted again as an original file.  However, new information has been received, which has led to an updated safety report.  Acme wants to replace both previously submitted safety files with the new report.  A submission unit is created that contains the new safety file, and marks it as replacement for both of the previously submitted files.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> This method can be applied when switching from a more granular document structure to a less granular one.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<descriptive identifier="PORP_SN000023UV01" name="Rps Sn23" familiarName="Replacing sections of a file" parent="PORP_ST000002UV01-str" id="PORP_ST000002UV01-PORP_SN000023UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|02" baseClass="Rps" lastEdit="2007-03-08T07:14:30" class="deleted">
						<p>A previous submission unit for the Global Fixit submission contained a structured product labeling (SPL) file.  Based on new data, Acme has decided to update the warning section of the label.  The company wants the regulatory authority to review only the changes to the warning section, not the entire label.  A new submission unit is created containing the changed section of the labeling file and marks it as an update to the previously submitted label. 
The updated SPL file section is merged with the previously submitted SPL files.
</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Note:</emph> As we move towards XML, sectional life cycle is possible. The life cycle of sections in the label is defined in the SPL specification.
</p>
					</descriptive>
					<diagref ref="PORP_ST000002UV01.gif"/>
					<intref ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01" sequence="1"/>
				</story>
			</storydivn>
			<approledivn identifier="roles-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Application Roles" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="roles-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="arop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="arop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<artree>
					<artreeitem>
						<arref role="included" ref="PORP_AR000001UV01-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Definition Apc" refFamiliarName="Applicant" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR000001UV01"/>
					</artreeitem>
					<artreeitem>
						<arref role="included" ref="PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Definition Ra" refFamiliarName="Regulatory Authority" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR000002UV01"/>
					</artreeitem>
				</artree>
				<approle identifier="PORP_AR000001UV01" name="Rps Definition Apc" familiarName="Applicant" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_AR000001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|02|99|99|APC" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-03-16T11:55:02" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_AR000001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_AR000001UV01-ar" id="desc-PORP_AR000001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-03-16T11:55:02">
						<p>The organization that assumes responsibility for producing documentation for the purpose of seeking approval to either start testing or market a specified product.
</p>
					</descriptive>
				</approle>
				<approle identifier="PORP_AR000002UV01" name="Rps Definition Ra" familiarName="Regulatory Authority" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|02|99|99|RA" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:00:54" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_AR000002UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" id="desc-PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:00:54">
						<p>The organization that reviews relevant information and has the ability to approve a product for testing or marketing.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<intref role="sends" ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01"/>
					<intref role="receives" ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01"/>
				</approle>
			</approledivn>
			<triggerdivn identifier="tes-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Trigger Events" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="tes-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="teop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="teop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<trigger identifier="PORP_TE000001UV01" name="Rps Event Activate Notification" familiarName="Regulatory Product Submission Unit Notification" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_TE000001UV01-te" role="Interaction based" sortPrefix="10|20|16||05|" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:07:15">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_TE000001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_TE000001UV01-te" id="desc-PORP_TE000001UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:07:15">
						<p>Applicant determines they have enough information that warrants a submission unit to a regulatory authority. The applicant can create a new submission unit, amend an existing submission or withdraw a submission.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<intref role="fires" ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01"/>
				</trigger>
			</triggerdivn>
			<rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="rmims-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="rmop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="rmop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<rmim identifier="PORP_RM000001UV01" name="Rps Event" familiarName="Regulated Product Submission" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="10|20|99|" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2007-03-08T07:20:32">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_RM000001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" id="desc-PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2007-03-08T07:20:32">
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Security, Confidentiality, and Data Integrity</emph>
						</p>
						<p>Application systems sending and receiving documents are responsible for meeting all legal requirements for document authentication, confidentiality, and retention. For communications over public media, cryptographic techniques for source/recipient authentication and secure transport of encapsulated documents may be required, and should be addressed with commercially available tools outside the scope of this standard.</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda </emph>
						</p>
						<p>An original report is the first version of a report. It gets a new unique value for ContextOfUse.id, a new value for ContextOfUse.setId, and has the value of ContextOfUse.versionNumber set to equal "1". </p>
						<p>
							<p>An addendum is an appendage to an existing report that contains supplemental information. The appendage is itself an original report, as described in the previous paragraph. The related report being appended is referenced via an ActRelationship, where the ActRelationship.typeCode is set to equal "APND" (for "appends"). The related report being appended remains in place and its content and status are unaltered. If the related report is subsequently replaced, the addendum will then be associated with the most current related report in the related report set (see setId). If a new report replaces both the previous report and the addendum, the ContextOfUse.setId will be the same as the previous reports ContextOfUse.setId and will have an ActRelationship.typeCode is set to equal "RPLC" (for "replace") for both the previous report and the addendum.</p>
							<p>A replacement report replaces an existing report. The replacement report gets a new globally unique ID value, while the replacement report uses the same value for ContextOfUse.setId as the related report being replaced, and increments the value of ContextOfUse.versionNumber by 1. (Note that version number must be incremented by one when a report is replaced, but can also be incremented more often to meet local requirements.) The related report is considered superseded, but is still retained in the system for historical reference. The related report being replaced is referenced via an ActRelationship, where the ActRelationship.typeCode is set to equal "RPLC" (for "replaces").</p>
						</p>
						<p>These relationships are summarized in the following illustration: </p>
						<p>
							<diagref ref="DocLifecycle.gif"/>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Context of Use (Document) Statuses and Transitions </emph>
						</p>
						<p>A context of use is a file that is being referenced in a particular submission unit with a particular code value. The same file can have several context of use. Accordingly, it is possible that each context of use of the same file has different statuses. In addition, a context of use is associated to a submission through a submission unit. Thus, it is possible to query all active documents in a approved submission.</p>
						<p>Documents only assume a subset of the states that other Acts can take on. When a document is released to regulatory authorities, its status becomes "active". Documents that are "active" are rendered "obsolete" when they are replaced with a revision. A document can also be rendered "obsolete"by a status change. If a document is rendered "obsolete", that document can be reactivated. Obsolete documents cannot be revised.</p>
						<p>In a later phase an active document will end its life when the submission that document belongs to has come to a conclusion.</p>
						<p>
							<diagref ref="DocStates.gif"/>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Submission Statuses and Transitions</emph>
						</p>
						<p>Submissions only assume a subset of the states that other Acts can take on. When a submission is released to regulatory authorities, its status becomes "active" or "In Review". Since the current specification only supports communication from applicant to regulatory authority, only withdrawing and activating a submission is currently supported.</p>
						<p>In the future, submissions will have the extra states of approvable, not approvable, and approved.</p>
						<p>
							<diagref ref="SubmissionStates.gif"/>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Submission Interaction</emph>
						</p>
						<p>For the scope of this project, all communication from applicant to regulatory authority are in the form of a submission. Note: the current specification does not support a message from the regulatory authority to applicant.</p>
						<p>Applicant determines it has enough information to warrant sending a submission to a regulatory authority. The applicant can create a new submission, amend an existing submission or withdraw a submission.</p>
						<p>
							<diagref ref="SubmissionInteract.gif"/>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">ContextOfUse Codes</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A document's content is defined by one or more topic codes (e.g. Manufacturer, Introduction, Summary, etc.). The combinations of these topic codes are well defined by product types. A single topic code can be used in different context. For example, in human therapeutic products the combination of the topic codes Chemistry, Drug substance, Manufacturer is a valid document context. If Chemistry has a topic code of 35, Drug substance has a topic code of 71, and Manufacturer has a topic code of 140, then the combination of Chemistry, Drug substance, and Manufacturer would have a ContextOfUse code of 35-71-140. In addition, if Drug Product has a topic code of 70, then the combination of Chemistry, Drug Product, and Manufacturer would have a ContextOfUse code of 35-70-140.</p>
						<p>In addition the same ContextOfUse code can be used for multiple products. For example the combination of Chemistry, Drug substance, and Manufacturer would be a valid ContextOfUse code for both Human Therapeutic products as well as Animal Products.</p>
						<p>It is also common that different product types will use different combinations of the same topic code. For example a Medical Device product would have a ContextOfUse code that specifies a Cover Letter. However, a Human Therapeutic product would have a ContextOfUse code that would combine the topic codes of both Administrative and Cover Letter.</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Model Overview</emph>
						</p>
						<p>As industry moves away from paper submissions, all companies producing regulated products will benefit from having published electronic submission standards. Accordingly, the focus of the initial message allows applicants to submit information electronically. The submitted information is structured as a collection of documents that is organized by report sections.  The actual table of required and optional report sections varies from product to product and is defined by regulatory authorities.</p>
						<p>Submitted documents are assigned to support one or more report sections. Furthermore, multiple documents can be assigned to a single report section. Since the same information can be submitted to support multiple applications, it is imperative that this standard allows the re-use of data between applications. Re-using data is accomplished by using the Uniform Resource Locator scheme (through the reference property of the ED datatype that is assigned to Act.text) in the File Act. The URL scheme allows the file in one application to provide a reference to a document that was submitted in another application.</p>
						<p>A single document can be in multiple report sections of an application and can also be in multiple applications. For this reason, we have defined the ContextOfUse Act which provides the relationship of a document to a report section.  Since a submission unit can contain multiple ContextOfUse, this class can be used to indicates each assignment of a document to a section.  Looking across multiple submissions, it is possible to record a single document's context in multiple applications as needed.</p>
						<p>Since this message is primarily focused on document management, it would seem that the ContextOfUse Act would be the obvious choice to the entry point of this message. However, applicants transmit information to regulatory authorities in the form of submission units containing multiple ContextOfUse. These submission units support the overall application. Accordingly, the entry point for this message is the Submission Unit Act.</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Domain Model Walk-Through</emph>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">SubmissionUnit</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A collection of documents submitted at a particular point in time in order to further the granting of a submission.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit.ID: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit.code: The code specifying the particular kind of submission unit (e.g. Original, Amendment, Supplement). 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit.statusCode: A submission unit is either active or null. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Submission: This clone defines the organization of the submission unit. A submission unit either pertains to one or more Submissions or pertains to one or more Reviewable Units. For example, an annual report submission unit can apply to multiple applications. Therefore, the applicant will create one submission unit and associate that unit to multiple submissions. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ReviewableUnit: A reviewable unit is a way to organize several submission units so they are reviewed as an independent unit within a submission. A submission unit either pertains to one or more Submissions or pertains to one or more Reviewable Units. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse: A submission unit contains zero to many ContextOfUse. The ContextOfUse Act contains most of the supporting information to help further the granting of an application. Two ContextOfUse Acts with the same Code can be sorted by priorityNumber. When the applicant administratively changes the status of the submission to obsolete, the applicant would create a submission unit message with no context of use.</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Submission</emph>
						</p>
						<p>The submission is a way to organize an application into discrete units. Most typically the submission will be used to organize information based on a review clock. Receipt date from the regulatory authority is important for a submission. Since the message, at this time, is only from applicant to regulatory authority, submission does not have a date attribute.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Submission.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Submission.Code: The code specifying the particular kind of submission (e.g. Original, Supplement, Annual report). 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Submission.statusCode: A submission is either active or null. In the future we plan on extending the status code to reflect the approval status of the submission. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit: The submission can be related to one or more submission units or one or more reviewable units. The submission unit can have a default order, the priorityNumber, used in the relationship to a submission. Note: There is a harmonization proposal to change priorityNumber from the value type of INT to REAL. The REAL value type will allow the applicant to order a submission unit between two other previously submitted submission units. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ReviewableUnit: The submission can be related to one or more submission units or one or more reviewable units. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Application: Each submission organizes information for a single application. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">ReviewableUnit</emph>
						</p>
						<p>The reviewable unit is a way to organize a submission into discrete units. Each reviewable unit can have a status. A reviewable unit performs similar to submission.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>ReviewableUnit.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ReviewableUnit.Code: The code specifying the particular kind of submission (e.g. Original, Supplement, Annual report). 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ReviewableUnit.statusCode: A submission is either active or null. In the future we plan on extending the status code to reflect the approval status of the submission. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit: The submission can be related to one or more submission units or one or more reviewable units. The submission unit can have a default order, the priorityNumber, used in the relationship to a submission. Note: There is a harmonization proposal to change priorityNumber from the value type of INT to REAL. The REAL value type will allow the applicant to order a submission unit between two other previously submitted submission units. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Submission: Each reviewable unit organizes information for a single submission. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Application</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A request for approval to either market a product or to allow the applicant to start testing of a proposed product.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Application.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Application.code: The code specifying the particular kind of application (e.g. New Drug Application, 510k, Veterinary New Drug Submission). Each product type will be supported by a different application code. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Application.statusCode: An application is either active or null. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Submission: There are zero to many submissions that contain information for an application. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition: An application has zero to many keywords that can be used to make a KeywordDefinition. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>File: An application can have zero to many files that can be referenced by a ContextOfUse Act. Once a file has been established any submission unit in any application to refer to that file. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">File</emph>
						</p>
						<p>The File Act defines the submitted document in a submission unit.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>File.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>File.text: The File.text attribute uses an encapsulated data (ED) type. The components of this data type will be used to transmit a document's URL (ED.reference), a document format or media type (ED.type). In addition, the ED type can be used to transmit the document itself (ED.BIN). However, this message will not allow the use of the ED.BIN attribute. To allow document re-use it is important that each file is transmitted separately from this message. The mechanism for packaging an HL7 Clinical Document Architecture (CDA) document in File.text is described in the CDA specification.</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Application: A file can be submitted in an application. Although that file can be reused within this application and in other application, please refer to specific implementation guide on how to reuse documents. There can be zero to many Files within an Application. For example, if a submission status is changed to obsolete no files will be submitted. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">FileReference</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A file can be used many times. Each time the file is used, that file has a different context of use. Accordingly, each context of use must refer to one file. 	 		</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>FileReference.id: This is the same id that is used in the File Act.</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse: A context of use reference one file. In the case that a context of use is being made obsolete, there is no need for a file reference. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">Keyword</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A Keyword is a reference to the KeywordDefinition Act. One or more Keywords can be associated to a contect of use.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Keyword.id: Reference to the KeywordDefinition.id. This field should only be used if there is not coding system equivalent 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Keyword.code: Used if the keyword is from a coding system not from keyword definition. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">KeywordDefinition</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A keyword definition contains name value pairs that are used within the context of an application.  Each keyword is an item of information that provides context for the document(s) in a context of use.  Keywords are used only to further define the context of a ContextOfUse, and the Keywords, by themselves, have no intrinsic value. Since one of the goals of this message was to create one message structure that can be used for all regulated product types, we decided not model individual keywords or keyword groups as classes and relate these classes to specific ContextOfUse codes.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition.code: The type of Keyword (e.g., Manufacture, Dosage Form, Rout of Admin) 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition.statusCode: Active or nullified. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition.effectiveTime: Signifies the keyword's creation time, when the keyword first came into being. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition.value: The value of the KeywordDefination.code 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>Application: A Keyword can be used in one to many context of use. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>PreviousKeywordDefinition: This clone represents the source of a replacement relationship. One can only replace another KeywordDefinition. When the KeywordDefination is replaced, that KeywordDefinition is obsolete; therefore, that KeywordDefiniation cannot be used in a context of use. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">PreviousKeywordDefinition</emph>
						</p>
						<p>PreviousKeywordDefinition is used to replace an existing KeywordDefination. Once a KeywordDefinition is replaces, that KeywordDefination can no longer be associated with a context of use.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>PreviousKeywordDefination.id: Reference to the KeywordDefinition.id. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>KeywordDefinition: This clone represents the target of a replacement relationship. One can only replace another KeywordDefinition. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">ContextOfUse</emph>
						</p>
						<p>The ContextOfUse Act defines the use of the submitted document in the context of a submission unit. The document and its assignment to a particular code will be used to create a table of contents. This table of contents will be used by Regulatory Authorities to review an application. Based on regional guidance, a document can be submitted once and be referred to by other ContextOfUse's text attribute in the same submission unit, different submission unit for the same application, or different submission units in a different application.</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.id: The unique identifier that is used to refer to this act 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.code: The code that specifies how the file is to be used within the submission process (e.g. Protocol, Summary Introduction). Note: ContextOfUse codes vary between different product types. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.title: The title for the document in the associated assignment. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.statusCode: See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda" 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.setId: See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda" 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse.versionNumber: See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda" 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>RelatedContextOfUse: This clone represents the source of a document relationship. The target is either being appended, revised, or transformed by the source document. One ContextOfUse can be the targets for many ParentContextOfUses. See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda" 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>SubmissionUnit: RelatedContextOfUses is the components of the submission unit. There can be one or more ContextOfUses within a submission unit. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Keyword: A ContextOfUse can be further defined, based on the ContextOfUse.code attribute, by zero to many Keywords. This is used to determine additional attributes of the document. (e.g., a document that is associated with a particular Study or Manufacturer). Only certain, well defined, ContextOfUse.code can be associated to a particular Keyword. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>FileReference: A ContextOfUse refers to a File through the FileReference. Accordingly every ContextOfUse, must have one and only one FileReference. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph role="strong">RelatedContextOfUse</emph>
						</p>
						<p>A ParentContextOfUse provides a relationship between a ContextOfUse and ContextOfUse that was recorded previously. See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda"</p>
						<p>
							<emph>Attributes</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>RelatedContextOfUse.id: Reference to the ContextOfUse.id 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ReleatedContextOfUse.versionNumber: See section "Document Identification, Revisions, and Addenda" 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
						<p>
							<emph>Relationships</emph>
						</p>
						<list role="unordered">
							<item>
								<p>sequelTo: Relates RelatedContextOfUse to the ContextOfUse and defines the sequence order of the ContextOfUse Act. 		</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>ContextOfUse: This clone represents the target of a document relationship.One ContextOfUse be associated with zero to many RelatedContextOfUses. 		</p>
							</item>
						</list>
					</descriptive>
					<diagref ref="PORP_RM000001UV.gif"/>
					<hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate" refFamiliarName="Regulated Product Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD000001UV01"/>
				</rmim>
			</rmimdivn>
			<hmddivn identifier="hmds-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="hmds-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="hdop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="hdop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<hmd identifier="PORP_HD000001UV01" name="Rps Event Activate" familiarName="Regulated Product Submission" parent="PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" id="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="10|20|16|" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2006-03-05T14:07:26">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_HD000001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" id="desc-PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2006-03-05T14:07:26">
						<p>This is the HMD for the Regulated Product Submission, submission units message.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PORP_HD000001UV01"/>
					<rmimref role="parent" ref="PORP_RM000001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event" refFamiliarName="Regulated Product Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_RM000001UV01"/>
					<msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate" refFamiliarName="Regulated Product Submission MT" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT000001UV01"/>
				</hmd>
			</hmddivn>
			<msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="msgs-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<msgtype identifier="PORP_MT000001UV01" name="Rps Event Activate" familiarName="Regulated Product Submission MT" parent="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" id="PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" sortPrefix="10|20|16|" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:07:54">
					<descriptive identifier="devnote-PORP_MT000001UV01" name="Design Note" parent="PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" id="devnote-PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" role="designComment" lastEdit="2006-03-20T18:07:54">
						<p>This is the message type for the Regulated Product Submission, submission unit message</p>
					</descriptive>
					<msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORP_MT000001UV01"/>
					<hmdref role="parent" ref="PORP_HD000001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate" refFamiliarName="Regulated Product Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD000001UV01"/>
					<intref role="sentIn" ref="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Submission Unit sent" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_IN000001UV01"/>
				</msgtype>
			</msgtypedivn>
			<interactiondivn identifier="ints-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Interactions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="ints-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="inop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="inop-PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<interaction identifier="PORP_IN000001UV01" name="Rps Event Activate Notification" familiarName="Submission Unit sent" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-Rps-ic" id="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|20|16|05|" baseClass="Rps" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2006-03-05T14:08:35">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_IN000001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORP_IN000001UV01-int" id="desc-PORP_IN000001UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-05T14:08:35">
						<p>The submission unit is sent from the application to the regultory authority</p>
					</descriptive>
					<arref role="sendrole" ref="PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Definition Ra" refFamiliarName="Regulatory Authority" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR000002UV01"/>
					<arref role="rcvrole" ref="PORP_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Definition Ra" refFamiliarName="Regulatory Authority" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR000002UV01"/>
					<teref role="trigger" ref="PORP_TE000001UV01-te" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Rps Event Activate Notification" refFamiliarName="Regulatory Product Submission Unit Notification" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_TE000001UV01"/>
					<msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/>
					<msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/>
					<msgref role="msgtype" ref="PORP_MT000001UV01-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Regulated Product Submission MT" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT000001UV01"/>
				</interaction>
			</interactiondivn>
		</subdivn>
		<subdivn identifier="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Structured Product Labeling (SPL) Release 3 Topic" familiarName="Structured Product Labeling (SPL) Release 3" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="40" baseClass="Structured Product Labeling (SPL) Release 3" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3">
			<descriptive identifier="intro-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Introduction" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="intro-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:18:41">
				  <div3 id=""><head>Preface</head>
      <p>This is the third release of the Structured Product Labeling standard (SPL R3). SPL release 3 is a minor maintenance update to the SPL release 2 content, subsequent to nation-wide implementation in the United States. Only very few substantive items have changed; and the change is being documented in this introduction.</p>
      <p>While only minor modifications are proposed to the content of SPL, the editorial form of the specification has changed significantly. The first two releases of SPL were specified in a word processor document and not in the more rigorous structure in which all HL7 v3 standards are to be defined and published. For the first time now, the SPL standard is fully integrated into the electronic HL7 publishing framework.</p>
      <p>SPL R2 was discussed as consisting of 2 parts, sometimes confusingly referred to as "SPL 2a" and "SPL 2b". This release of SPL merges these parts together into one. Structurally, SPL consists of 3 parts: (1) document data structures, (2) data structures describing the medicine, and (3) data structures describing the clinical use of the medicine, and connected through the highlight excerpt.
      In anticipation of further consolidation of the specification into the HL7 publishing framework, a lot of material has also been removed from this word-processor document. This removed material falls in three categories:</p>
      <ol>
         <li>Text which is mostly tutorial or introductory to HL7 v3 in general, teaching about general approaches and mechanisms of HL7 v3, RIM and Data Types. It is assumed that such material is repetitive and at the risk of being inconsistent with the overall HL7 framework.</li>
         <li>Design rationales of SPL, hopes for its use, and visions for its future development. This text has been removed because it tends to be in the way of stating clearly what an implementer must do and how one should interpret an SPL document. An attempt was made to faithfully retain all text which actually specifies either actionable requirements or rules of interpretation. Each of these points was stated only once and repetitions merged. Some general requirements statements were moved into the main body of the SPL specification, which is no longer this document. The fate of each section of the previous SPL release is documented in the following text under the respective major heading.</li>
         <li>Examples and code list appendices. The entire appendix apparatus of prior SPL releases was removed. This material was non-normative to begin with, and due to changes in and outside SPL proper has become possibly inconsistent. Vocabulary sets have been extended and many more examples exist from real SPL implementations today (See the DailyMed web site, where SPL content for all of U.S. FDA approved drugs is being published [http://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov]).</li>
      </ol>
   </div3>
   <div3 id=""><head>What is SPL?</head>
      <p>The Structured Product Labeling (SPL) specification is a document markup standard that specifies the structure and semantics of the content of authorized published information that accompanies any medicine licensed by a national or international medicines licensing authority. These documents are known as "product label," "package insert," "prescribing information," "product information," "medicines information,"  "summary of product characteristics," and many others. The precise definition and content of product labeling usually varies depending on the country. (For example, in the U.S., all written, printed, or graphic matter accompanying a drug product is called "labeling." For human prescription drugs, the "content of labeling" includes all text tables and figures in the labeling described in 21CFR 201.57.) Implementers of this standard should refer to regulations, definitions and guidances applicable for the realm in which the standard will be used.</p>
      <p>An SPL document is created by an organization that is required by law to submit product information document because it is responsible for the creation or marketing of a product, or any other person or organization compelled by other motives to submit information about products, whether originally created or not. This includes, original manufacturers, repackagers, relabelers, and public agencies or private information publishers that submit product information documents. Recipients of product label documents are any person or organization, including the public at large, or an agent of the public (such as a regulatory authority). The need to create SPL documents is typically governed by legal statutes which set points such as the completion of a new drug application, the change of product information or annual reports as requiring submission of an SPL document.</p>
      <p>Like most documents, an SPL document has sections and sections contain text (paragraphs, lists, tables); SPL documents can be rendered and published in these standard narrative presentations. At the same time, the SPL specification provides semantic markup that permits extraction of relevant data embedded in the narrative so that it can be used for other purposes. In other words, SPL markup of a product labeling document both preserves the human readability of the content and facilitates machine processing of that content. The document may contain references to media files, such as images, which should accompany the SPL document. However, the wrapping of files is not specified, and guidances to this effect exist by regulatory authorities who accept SPL.</p>
      <p>SPL is based on the HL7 Clinical Document Architecture (CDA), which specifies the structure and semantics of "clinical documents" for the purpose of exchange. In earlier releases of SPL the CDA text markup XML schema and its defining text had been copied from the CDA specification. This XML schema is also known as the "narrative block" schema, and included in the SPL XML schema release as NarrativeBlock.xml. This narrative block schema is part of the SPL specification; however, it will no longer be reproduced verbatim but rather will be included into the SPL specification by reference only and only variances between CDA and SPL will be discussed in detail.</p>
      <p>Even though the SPL specification is based on the HL7 Clinical Document Architecture, there are fundamental differences between the two specifications, for example:</p>
      <ul>
         <li>CDA documents involve a Patient- SPL documents do not.</li>
         <li>CDA documents involve one or more Providers- SPL documents do not.</li>
         <li>CDA documents involve an Encounter- SPL documents do not.</li>
         <li>The potential for authentication is subtly different for product labeling documents than for CDA documents. While a product labeling document may be authenticated, and may even have a requirement for legal authentication in some realms, this authentication occurs on the official, approved version of the document rather than on each instance (copy) of the document.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The purpose of the SPL specification is to facilitate the review, editing, storage, dissemination of, and access to product labeling document content. It is intended to:</p>
      <ul>
         <li>Facilitate provision of the content of product labeling both electronically and in a human readable format.  SPL documents can be exchanged across systems without the need for additional transformation steps.</li>
         <li>Improve dissemination of product labeling (both new product labeling and product labeling updates) to users of product labeling. The ability to provide the most up-to-date product labeling in a timely manner is considered to be critical to improving risk management of regulated products.</li>
         <li>Facilitate more efficient evaluation of labeling changes by allowing more effective use of computer technology to compare different versions of labeling on a section by section basis.</li>
         <li>Promote more coordinated data collection throughout the regulatory agency and improve processing, storage and archiving capabilities. Reduce or eliminate redundancies in data collection.</li>
         <li>Improve access to information and enhance the ability to query and report on the content of labeling, allowing better support for specific analyses such as sub-population assessments of differences in products based on gender, race, age, and geographic location.</li>
         <li>Improve interoperability of the regulatory agency's systems with other clinical information systems</li>
         <li>Use standards to improve integration of clinical data</li>
         <li>Enhance patient safety by helping to provide prescribers and consumers with improved access to information needed to make better risk management decisions in a format that will enhance integration with other technical and clinical applications.</li>
         <li>Support retention of legacy product labeling in databases</li>
      </ul>
      <p>It is important to note that the SPL specification models the structure and semantics of labeling content <b>and not the presentation found in printed labeling!</b> It standardizes the markup of the required content, specifically the structure and semantics of that content. Although the human readability requirement specifies that the content must at the very least be readable using a generic stylesheet that applies to all HL7 structured documents, the use of specialized stylesheets for specific presentation purposes is not prohibited. Limited support for the presentation of content is provided in CDA "narrative block" and has been adopted by SPL.</p>
      <p>The SPL specification does not specify the creation or management of documents, only their storage and exchange markup. Document management is critically interdependent with the product labeling specification, but the specification of document management messages is outside the scope of the SPL specification.</p>
      <p>This specification does not address the transfer mechanism for product labeling documents. The specification for messages that might carry the product labeling document is outside the scope of the SPL specification, although the CDA standard does specify how to package clinical documents within HL7 messages. An SPL document may be transmitted in an HL7 message that is designed to transfer clinical documents. Alternatively, several other mechanisms may be used to transfer product labeling including physical media, PDF, electronic transfer of word processing applications, among many others.</p>
      <div4 id=""><head>XML Markup of SPL Documents</head>
         <p>The SPL specification is a part of HL7 v3 specifications and follows its methodology. According to this methodology, XML Implementation Specification is governed by the rules of the XML Implementation Technology Specification (ITS) and SPL makes no exceptions to this. The XML ITS makes clear that a W3C XML-Schema is provided as informative and useful tool to implementers, but the W3C XML-Schema neither completely defines SPL nor is it an exclusive representative of the XML ITS. Hence, the SPL Schema itself is not normative.</p>
         <p>There are no deviations in the XML Schema which is generated from the SPL Hierarchical Description (PORP_HD050032). However, it may be noted that the ordering of elements in the HD deviates from the standard ordering of elements in other HL7 v3 HDs. This is done for backwards compatibility as the order of these elements does matter to most XML technology.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>Security, Confidentiality, and Data Integrity</head>
         <p>Strong security, confidentiality and data integrity mechanism are currently out of scope of this specification. Implementers will have to comply with applicable law, regulations and guidances.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>SPL Extensibility</head>
         <p>Extensibility of SPL follows all the same rules and guidelines as extensibility of any other HL7 v3 specification. See the applicable extensibility and conformance specifications.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>SPL Context Inheritance</head>
         <p>SPL context inheritance is managed in exactly the same way as context inheritance in all other HL7 v3 specifications. This includes contextControlCode for Participations; contextConductionInd (context conduction indicator) for ActRelationships. Most of these attributes have fixed values assigned. In SPL these assignments have been made to the effect that the author-Participation inherits from the Document to all nested Sections unless overridden. Confidentiality and human language codes are also considered part of this context. Because this context always propagates unless overridden, the representation of unknown context is achieved by overriding with a null value.</p>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 id=""><head>SPL Conformance (NORMATIVE)</head>
      <p>A conformant SPL document is one that at a minimum validates against the SPL Schema, and that restricts its use of coded vocabulary to values allowable within the specified vocabulary domains. However a computer cannot validate many aspects of conformance. The focus of this section is to highlight these aspects of SPL that cannot be machine validated - particularly those aspects related to the SPL human readability requirements.</p>
      <p>Description of Application Roles moved to the main specification.  The following responsibilities have been condensed leaving the actual requirements and not mentioning optional steps which were not required. Also those requirements which are simply restating some constraints that are documented in the HD and XML Schema are not repeated.</p>
      <p>Recipient responsibilities</p>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <b>Assume default values where they are defined in this specification, and where the instance does not contain a value:</b> Where SPL defines default values, the recipient must assume these values in the event that no value is contained in an SPL instance. This holds regardless of whether or not the SPL Schema supplies the recipient with the default values.</li>
         <li>
            <b>Parse and interpret the SPL content sufficiently to be able to render it:</b> A recipient of an SPL document must be able to parse and interpret the SPL document sufficiently to be able to render it, using the following rendering rules:</li>
         <li>The NonXMLBody, will need to be rendered with a software tool that recognizes its particular MIME media type. <b>Since there can be no guarantee that a recipient can render every possible MIME type, a NonXMLBody may be ignored by a recipient. A sender can only rely on the recipient being able to render a NonXMLBody if there is a prior bilateral agreement. Hence, the NonXMLBody is not plug-and-play interoperable. See also the HL7 Data Type specification for the status of various MIME types.</b>
         </li>
         <li>The StructuredBody, must be rendered by the recipient including at least the Section.title, and Section.text (Narrative Block) elements. The absence of the Section.title signifies an unlabeled section.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Originator responsibilities</p>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <b>Properly construct SPL Narrative Blocks:</b> An originator of an SPL document must ensure that the content of the document body is structured such that a recipient, adhering to the recipient responsibilities above, will correctly render the document.</li>
      </ul>
   </div3>
   <div3 id=""><head>Product Labeling Scope</head>
      <p>This section summarizes the scope of the SPL document and data structures. Formally it was discussed as 'requirements' and split over two parts of the specification. A discussion of requirements can not be actionable normative content. But the material is suitable as a scope statement, providing a summary of data covered by SPL.</p>
      <div4 id=""><head>Scope of Document and Section Structures</head>
         <p>Product labeling documents should be both human readable and machine processable.</p>
         <p>Precise requirements regarding metadata for document management have not been established. Therefore, the model contains information that would be required regardless of document management processes (e.g., document identifier [id]) as well as information that may be desired in some realms (e.g., author, legal authenticator).</p>
         <p>Product labeling documents may be revised or replaced. One document may be a transformation from another.</p>
         <p>Formatting of documents may vary from one realm to another or one implementation to another.</p>
         <p>HL7 structured documents contain sections. Product labeling documents tend to be organized into commonly understood sections (e.g., indications, precautions). While there may be a standard set of section names and hierarchies for a product labeling document in a given realm, at this time there is no single international standard product labeling document structure. Product labeling document content and structure is usually specified in regulations. Therefore, the SPL model is deliberately flat and non-hierarchical  the ability to identify and name sections has been provided, but the exact names, order, and nesting of sections are not specified. This provides a high level of flexibility in the model.</p>
         <p>Product labeling document sections may be revised or replaced on a modular basis.</p>
         <p>Sections contain narrative text.</p>
         <p>Sections may contain data elements. Sections may also contain images (e.g., the chemical structure of a drug).</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>Scope of Medicine Description Data Structures</head>
         <p>In order to facilitate machine processing of data contained within the narrative of product labeling document sections, it is necessary to provide markup of these data, which are referred to in this specification as data elements. The primary intent of data elements defined to date is to facilitate document indexing, search and retrieval, and to provide a standard convention for insertion of codes in order to identify required data elements.</p>
         <p>For this version of the SPL specification, a number of data elements related to drug product labeling have been identified. These include:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>Imprint information for solid dosage form:</li>
            <ul>
               <li>Imprint code</li>
               <li>Size</li>
               <li>Shape</li>
               <li>Color</li>
               <li>Coating</li>
               <li>Scoring</li>
               <li>Logo</li>
            </ul>
            <li>Drug product code (e.g., NDC code in the U.S.)</li>
            <li>Package type</li>
            <li>Package quantity</li>
            <li>Controlled substance classification or schedule (e.g., DEA number in the U.S.)</li>
            <li>Active ingredients (name, code, strength)</li>
            <li>Active moiety (code)</li>
            <li>Inactive ingredients (name, code, strength)</li>
            <li>Labeled route of administration</li>
            <li>Proprietary name (sometimes known as brand name)</li>
            <li>Nonproprietary (generic) name</li>
         </ul>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>Scope of Clinical Use Data Structures</head>
         <p>This scope is outlined by the following data requirements are being addressed.</p>
         <ol>
            <li>Drug Interaction</li>
            <ol>
               <li>highlight text</li>
               <li>other drug or class interacting</li>
               <li>consequence</li>
               <li>special population</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Food Interaction</li>
            <ol>
               <li>highlight text</li>
               <li>food or meal interacting</li>
               <li>consequence</li>
               <li>special population</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Laboratory Test Interaction</li>
            <ol>
               <li>highlight text</li>
               <li>laboratory test interacting</li>
               <li>consequence</li>
               <li>special population</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Adverse Event</li>
            <ol>
               <li>highlight text</li>
               <li>(does not apply)</li>
               <li>consequence</li>
               <li>special population</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Indication</li>
            <ol>
               <li>indication name</li>
               <li>limitations</li>
               <li>pharmacologic class (e.g. antihypertensive)</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Dosing</li>
            <ol>
               <li>initiation dose</li>
               <li>usual daily dose</li>
               <li>do not exceed dose</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Monitoring</li>
            <ol>
               <li>which tests to run, how frequent</li>
               <li>criteria for test results</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Mechanism of Action</li>
            <ul>
               <li>cellular/molecular action (e.g., Ca-channel blocker)</li>
               <li>physiologic action (e.g., vasodilator)</li>
               <li>molecular/chemical class (e.g. aminopenicillin)</li>
            </ul>
            <li>Miscellanea</li>
            <ul>
               <li>Adverse Event contact Phone Number</li>
               <li>Initial approval date of the molecular compound</li>
               <li>Approval number and country of approval for the product</li>
            </ul>
         </ol>
         <p>NOTE: Encoding all detail and nuances of the label content are not in the current scope of SPL. If any information of the text is not encoded, this does not imply that this information could be ignored.</p>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 id=""><head>Description of SPL Data Structures (NORMATIVE)</head>
      <p>This section contains the normative description of the SPL data structures. In SPL releases 1 and 2, these descriptions were spread over former sections 4, 5 and 6. This material has now been condensed such that each element is described only once and the material has moved entirely into the HL7 v3 specification and publication framework, linked directly to the SPL refined information model (RMIM), and thus will also be available in the Hierarchical Descriptor (HD) and in the XML-Schema. For this purpose the text of the descriptions has undergone some editorial redaction to form more concise definitions without substantially changing any of the previously established meaning.</p>
      <div4 id=""><head>Document Structure Elements</head>
         <p>
            <b>Document:</b> The Structured Product Labeling document as a whole.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.id:</b> A required, globally-unique instance identifier, which is different from the XML element identifier; see the HL7 Data Types specification for more information about use of globally-unique instance identifiers.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.setId:</b> An optional globally-unique identifier, that remains constant across all document revisions that derive from a common original document.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.versionNumber:</b> An optional version number is incremented for each subsequent version of a document. For example, an original document is the first version of a document, and gets a new globally unique "id" value; it can also contain a new value for "setId" and a value of "versionNumber" set to equal "1".</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.code:</b> 
A code specifying the type of product labeling document (e.g., prescription drug label or over-the-counter prescription drug label). The externally-defined vocabulary domain for "Document.code" is preferentially drawn from LOINC.
</p>
         <p>NOTE: Within the LOINC database, beginning with version 2.09, May 2003, document type codes are those that have a value of "DOC" in the Scale component.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.title:</b> 
Free text entry of the human readable title of the document. It is this title of a document that is rendered. The title describes (but does not guarantee) the content of the document.
</p>
         <p>The title is either a simple string (ST) or an XML content (ED) with limited NarrativeBlock markup which allows for stylesCode, super- and sub-script, line breaks and few other functions, but explicitly excludes tables, lists, etc.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.effectiveTime:</b> Document origination time, i.e., a timestamp specifying when the document was created.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.availabilityTime:</b> The release date of the product labeling document.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Participation.time:</b> Other time stamps in the document lifecycle may be recorded through the various participants in the document (see below for a description of people and organizations that play a role in a product labeling document). Each Participation class clone has a required 'time' attribute. Thus, there is a time associated with an Author, Verifier (reviewer), and LegalAuthenticator.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.confidentialityCode:</b> Specifies confidentiality of the entire document. May be overriden for specific parts of the document. Values may be drawn from the Confidentiality vocabulary domain. Values other than those in the HL7 vocabulary domain (such as local codes) can also be used if necessary.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Document.languageCode:</b> A code specifying the human language of character data in the product labeling document (whether in contents or attribute values). The values of the attribute are language identifiers as defined by the IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force) RFC 3066: Tags for the Identification of Languages, ed. H. Alvestrand, 1995 (http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt), which obsoletes RFC 1766. Language is a contextual component of SPL, where the value expressed in the header holds true for the entire document, unless overridden by a nested value.</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument (Participation) (RelatedDocument1):</b> One or more specific relationships between documents. These relationships rely on document identifiers described above.</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument1.typeCode:</b> The nature of the relationship. For example, a replacement document replaces an existing document, where the document being replaced is referenced via this relationship with a type code of RPLC (for "replaces").</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument (Act) (RelatedDocument):</b> A reference to another Document. The set of attributes in this class has the purpose of identifying the related document by identifiers only. To learn the contents of the related document, one needs to retrieve that document by the identifier(s) provided here.</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument.id:</b> Provides unambiguous explicit identification of documents and document revisions. When the RelatedDocument is used to indicate versioning, then each version has a unique document id, and the RelatedDocument.id references the previous document version.</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument.setId:</b> Can be used to support conventional revision numbering in addition to the explicit links to the ancestor versions using the RelatedDocument.id. One example scenario is: The new replacement Document gets a new globally unique id value, and uses the same value for setId as the RelatedDocument being replaced, and increments the value of versionNumber. The RelatedDocument is then considered superseded, but is still retained in the system for historical reference.</p>
         <p>
            <b>RelatedDocument.versionNumber:</b> Can be used to support conventional revision numbering in addition to the explicit links to the ancestor versions using the RelatedDocument.id. One example scenario is: The new replacement Document gets a new globally unique id value, and uses the same value for setId as the RelatedDocument being replaced, and increments the value of versionNumber by 1. (If used, the versionNumber will be incremented by one when a document is replaced, but can also be incremented more often to meet local requirements.) The parent document is considered superseded, but is still retained in the system for historical reference.</p>
         <p>
            <b>AssignedEntity:</b> 
Possible persons and organizations involved in the creation and review of a product labeling document are associated with the document as Participations. Participations may include document originators (authors), legal authenticators, organizations that own the marketing authority for the product, and product labeling reviewers at the regulatory agency. Participants are capable of and accountable for their independent decisions. All of these participants are optional in the SPL model but could be constrained to be required for a given realm.
</p>
         <p>Information about participants is captured by means of clones of several interrelated RIM classes: Participations, Roles, and Entities. In general, an Entity (person or organization) playing a particular Role (in this case, AssignedEntity), participates in an Act (e.g., a document). It is the Participation clone that identifies the type of participant. The type of Participation (e.g., author) is indicated by a code. The Role played by the Entity establishes that entity's competency or authority to participate as indicated. For example, a person participating as an author of a label is only authorized to do so if assigned by the organization responsible for authorship of the label.</p>
         <p>The way in which a Person or Organization is participating in the document is specified by the typeCode attribute on the relevant Participation class clone. While the nature of the participation may be suggested by the XML element name, the typeCode values are the definitive indication.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Author:</b> A Participation clone that links a Document (or Section) to the Person who originated the document (or section, respectively), and, through AssignedEntity, also links to the Organization that owns the document. If desired, the author(s) of specific sections can be identified using the same structures as it is done for Document.author, which will then override the author(s) specified for the Document. (Note: In the SPL RMIM, this class is represented as a "shadow" of the author class for document, indicating that this participation is used by both the section and the document classes.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Author.typeCode:</b> The way in which a Person or Organization is participating in the document is specified by the typeCode attribute on the relevant Participation class clone. While the nature of the participation may be suggested by the XML element name, the typeCode values are the definitive indication.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Author.time:</b> The time of participation by the author (usually the time of origination).</p>
         <p>
            <b>LegalAuthenticator:</b> 
In some realms there may be a requirement to capture a legal authenticator of the labeling content. A legally authenticated document exists when an individual with the proper legal authority has attested to the accuracy of the document content. A document can be legally authenticated by zero or more people.
</p>
         <p>Requirements for capture of information about a potential legal authenticator have not been defined to date. However, in the case where a local document is transformed into a SPL document for exchange, authentication only occurs on the local document and the fact of authentication is reflected in the exchanged SPL document. An SPL document can reflect the unauthenticated or authenticated state. The unauthenticated state exists when no authentication information has been recorded (i.e., it is the absence of being authenticated).</p>
         <p>
            <b>LegalAuthenticator.typeCode:</b> The way in which a Person or Organization is participating in the document is specified by the typeCode attribute on the relevant Participation class clone. While the nature of the participation may be suggested by the XML element name, the typeCode values are the definitive indication.</p>
         <p>
            <b>LegalAuthenticator.time:</b> The time of participation by the legal authenticator (the time at which the document was authenticated, i.e., signed).</p>
         <p>
            <b>LegalAuthenticator.signatureCode:</b> Document the existence of a signature if the value for signatureCode is "S" (for "signed"). Authentication involves signing of the document either manually or electronically by the responsible individual. The electronic signature mechanism that uses the RIM attributes Participation.signatureText and Role.certificateText, is currently not included in SPL.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Verifier:</b> Represents reviewers, typically within the regulatory agency, where the AssignedEntity.representedOrganization provides details about the organization (e.g., the regulatory agency) for which the verifier is working. (It is possible to indicate reviewers of a different organization, such as the manufacturer itself, the representedOrganization specification will tell what level of review the Verifier participation represents.)</p>
         <p>
            <b>Verifier.typeCode:</b> The way in which a Person or Organization is participating in the document is specified by the typeCode attribute on the relevant Participation class clone. While the nature of the participation may be suggested by the XML element name, the typeCode values are the definitive indication.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Verifier.time:</b> Indicates the time of participation by the verifier (usually the time of review).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Verifier.signatureCode:</b> Document the existence of a signature if the value for signatureCode is "S" (for "signed"). Verification may involve signing of the document either manually or electronically by the responsible individual. The electronic signature mechanism that uses the RIM attributes Participation.signatureText and Role.certificateText, is currently not included in SPL.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Person:</b> The AssignedEntity.assignedPerson, provides the details (e.g., name) about the person participating in the document as an author. Because assignedPerson is optional, it is possible to capture only information about the representedOrganization.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Organization:</b> The AssignedEntity.representedOrganization provides details about the organization (the manufacturer or owner of the marketing authority) for which the author is working. This specifies the organization from which the document originates and that is in charge of maintaining the document (e.g., the owner of the marketing authority or a contractor in charge of the labeling), commonly called the manufacturer.</p>
         <class name="Component7" title="Document to Content" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>StructuredBody:</b> Represents an XML document body that is comprised of one or more Sections.</p>
         <p>
            <b>NonXMLBody:</b> Represents a document body that is in some format other than SPL XML (e.g., a PDF document.)</p>
         <class name="Component6" title="Content to Section" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>Section:</b> 
Provides a means of organizing the product labeling content into the commonly understood sections generally found in these documents. The Section class is a container used to wrap other containers. A section element can occur in the StructuredBody, or can be nested within another Section. A section can also be replaced by another section. A section can contain nested section elements or other structures such as observations.
The SPL section contains the actual product labeling text and graphics to be rendered.  There are three logical components of the SPL section:
</p>
         <p>(1) General section information.</p>
         <p>(2) Information about participants in creation of the section.</p>
         <p>(3) The actual product labeling text and graphics to be included in the label section (and which will be rendered), along with structured data elements (that may be used for machine processing).</p>
         <p>The mechanisms to uniquely identify a specific product labeling section, to indicate a standard type code and name for the section, and to include a local name for the section (e.g. realm or language specific name; possibly constrained by the type code) are all included.</p>
         <p>Note the section element contains an optional local identifier (represented as an XML ID attribute) that can serve as the target of an XML reference.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.id:</b> A globally-unique instance identifier, which is different from the XML ID attribute; see the HL7 Data Types specification for more information about use of globally-unique instance identifiers.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Special XML attribute Section/@ID (Section.ID):</b> In XML rendition of SPL, the section-element contains an optional local identifier (represented as an XML ID attribute) that can serve as the target of a reference.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.code:</b> A code that describes (but does not guarantee) the content of the section. The externally-defined vocabulary domain for Section.code may be drawn from LOINC. However, because the coding strength is CWE, the code set may be extended locally. Examples of possible section codes include: Indications and usage, Dosage and administration, Contraindications, Warnings, Drug interactions, Adverse reactions</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.title:</b> An optional free text entry of the human readable title of the section. It is the title of a section that is rendered. The title describes (but does not guarantee) the content of the section. (It is important to note that title is optional, and sections should be created for logical sub-units of the document, whether they have titles or not.)</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.effectiveTime:</b> Interval of time, specifying the section origination time, i.e., when the section was created.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.confidentialityCode:</b> Can override the confidentialityCode attribute in Document.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.languageCode:</b> Specifies the human language of character in the same way that Document.languageCode works. Language is a contextual component of SPL, where the value expressed in the header holds true for the entire document, unless overridden by a nested value </p>
         <p>
            <b>Section.text:</b> 
The attribute that holds narrative to be rendered and is a special hand-crafted content model (the same as Section.text in CDA) that is part of the SPL standard. The SPL schema incorporates by reference the NarrativeBlock schema for this content model. The content model for Section.text is defined by the Clinical Document Architecture specification (currently section 4.3.5  Section Narrative Block), to which normative reference is hereby made.
</p>
         <p>While the Narrative Block schema defined by the Clinical Document Architecture is the only allowed content model for Section.text. Updates have been made to it since the last release and ballot of CDA in collaboration between the Structured Document Technical Committee and the SPL Group.</p>
         <p>The content revised attribute has an additional value of revised in addition to the existing values insert and delete. This can be used to mark text as revised without specifying in detail the nature of the change.</p>
         <class name="Component5" title="Section to Subsection" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>ReplacementOf:</b> An explicit representation of the relationships between versions of sections. Whether and how this information is used depends on the document management system in use. A replacement section replaces an existing section.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ReplacementOf.typeCode:</b> The value of RPLC for "replacement of" as contained in the ActRelationshipType vocabulary domain.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SectionReplaced:</b> A section that is related to the section it replaces through the replacementOf relationship (an ActRelationship clone).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Observation (DEPRECATED) (Observation):</b> Allowed inserting free-standing codes and other observations into SPL documents. Because this function has no interoperable definition and no requirement and can overlap with the explicit SPL data structures it has been deprecated since release 2 or SPL, it will be discarded shortly. Use Characteristic instead, which better relates the characteristics with the thing so characterized.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationMedia:</b> Holds multi-medial content, that is logically a part of a product labeling document, but may be stored outside the document and incorporated by reference. Multimedia that is integral to a document, and part of the attestable content of the document, requires the use of observationMedia. (An example might be the molecular structure for a drug in a drug product labeling document.) Multimedia that is simply referenced by the document and not an integral part of the document can use linkHtml. The XML ID attribute on the observationMedia element is used by the renderMultiMedia element (of the Narrative Block) to identify the media to be rendered.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationMedia.id:</b> An ObservationMedia class contains an optional instance identifier.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Special XML attribute ObservationMedia/@ID (ObservationMedia.ID):</b> The XML ID attribute on the observationMedia element is used by the renderMultiMedia element to identify the media to be rendered (renderMultiMedia).</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationMedia.value:</b> Encoded data (ED) which contains the media data either inline or by reference.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Section as Subject of Comments (Subject8):</b> Links a comment to a section. The comment does not participate in the context of the document, i.e., is never assumed to be attributed to the document or section author and is not considered part of the document.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Comment:</b> 
Editorial comments much like the comments which can be attached to text with some word processors. Comment.text contains the free text of the comment.  The comment can reference a precise location in the section text using the TextFragmentReference. The following is an example:
</p>
         <p>
            <pre>
   &lt;section&gt; 
      ... 
      &lt;text&gt;Pramoxicol SM is &lt;content ID="cmt123"&gt;the cure for hair loss&lt;/content&gt;.&lt;/text&gt; 
      ... 
      &lt;subjectOf&gt; 
         &lt;comment&gt; 
            &lt;text&gt;This is a unfounded hype, you need to strike this&lt;/text&gt; 
            &lt;statusCode code="active"/&gt; 
            &lt;effectiveTime .../&gt; 
            &lt;subject&gt; 
               &lt;textFragmentReference&gt; 
                  &lt;text&gt; 
                     &lt;reference url="#cmt123"/&gt; 
                  &lt;/text&gt; 
               &lt;/textFragmentReference&gt; 
            &lt;/subject&gt; 
         &lt;/comment&gt; 
      &lt;/subjectOf&gt; 
      ... 
   &lt;/section&gt; 
</pre>
         </p>
         <p>A comment should be attributed to an author but this author is separate from the document author (explicitly not inherited). Even if no specific author is assigned to a Comment, such Comment is not automatically attributed to the document or section author. A Comment is not even considered part of the Section; it only references the Section and can be sent along with a Section but might be stripped from the Section without such stripping being considered an alteration of the Section.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Comment.text:</b> The free text of the comment. Uses the same Narrative Block schema as the Section.text itself.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Comment.statusCode:</b> Distinguishes comments that are open issues (active) from those that had been resolved (complete).</p>
         <p>
            <b>SequelTo:</b> Links to an earlier comment, such that one commenter can respond to another comment. When linking comments, the response to a comment is nested as a sequel/comment inside the comment element to which it responds.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Specific Subject of a Comment (Subject9):</b> Allows narrowing the subject of the comment down to a specific fragment inside the Section.text.</p>
         <p>
            <b>TextFragmentReference:</b> References a specific fragment in the section text using the XML ID attributes on the content element in the section.</p>
         <p>
            <b>TextFragmentReference.text:</b> The reference to the text, using the referencing function of the ED data type, i.e., as a URL with a fragment reference, where the fragment is typically created by a content element with an XML ID attribute as defined in the Narrative Block schema (see Section.text).</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>Medicine Description Data Structures</head>
         <p>
            <b>Medicine:</b> 
The medicine is the primary unit which is manufactured and the object of an intended substance administration and is not just packaging. Examples are tablet, capsule, solution for injection, powder.
</p>
         <p>Conversely, vial and bottle are containers, which though necessary for handling of the medicine, are not administered to the patient, but emptied into some other solution, or used with an injection or inhalation device. Notice, even though a capsule can be considered a container holding granules, capsules are still considered primary Medicines not PackagedMedicines, because the capsule is the unit normally intended for administration, and so the capsule is the medicine. In this way, a solution packaged in an administration unit, such as a dragee or a prefilled syringe may be considered primary Medicines rather than PackagedMedicines, if it is intended to be applied completely as one unit, and not subdivided. This requires that the ingredients of such medicines are specified as a total amount per complete application rather than as a concentration.</p>
         <p>A kit, which is a collection of parts which are administered together or used in some intricate way are sometimes also described as primary Medicine with parts. The key criterion is that the kit as a whole is considered the object of a SubstanceAdministration.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Medicine.name:</b> The proprietary or brand name.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Medicine.formCode:</b> The dosage form of the drug. Values may be drawn from the MaterialForm HL7 vocabulary table or from other external code value sources. Notice the difference between an (Administered) Medicine and a PackagedMedicine. Both have formCodes. A box or vial is usually not a Medicine.formCode, unless the entire box or the entire vial is meant for direct administration as a single unit.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ManufacturedProduct:</b> A Role of the Medicine as a ManufacturedProduct is taken as the principal role for the SPL medication model.</p>
         <class name="Subject5" title="Product as Subject of a Section" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>EntityWithGeneric:</b> Relationship that links to the non-proprietary, generic substance as which the same medicines is known in the literature independent of a specific manufacturer.</p>
         <p>
            <b>GenericMedicine:</b> The non-proprietary, generic substance as which the same medicines is known in the literature independent of a specific manufacturer.</p>
         <p>
            <b>GenericMedicine.name:</b> The non-proprietary, generic, or "established" name.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveIngredient:</b> A therapeutically active ingredient (player) in a mixture (scoper), where the mixture is typically a manufactured pharmaceutical.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveIngredient.id:</b> 
An identifier to establish mostly internal references as a SubstanceAdministration.consumable for the unambiguous specification of dose quantity without having to repeat the entire content. Example:
</p>
         <p>
            <pre>
   &lt;section ... DESCRIPTION ...&gt;
      &lt;subject&gt;
         &lt;manufacturedProduct&gt;
             &lt;manufacturedMedicine&gt;
                 &lt;activeIngredient&gt;
                    &lt;id root="60a4db80-573d-11db-b0de-0800200c9a66"/&gt;
   		 &lt;quantity .../&gt;
   		 &lt;activeIngredientSubstance .../&gt;
   	      &lt;/activeIngredient&gt;
   	  &lt;/manufacturedMedicine&gt;
         &lt;/manufacturedProduct&gt;
      &lt;/subject&gt;
   &lt;/section&gt;
   ...
   &lt;section ... DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ...&gt;
      &lt;excerpt&gt;
         &lt;highlight&gt;
   	 &lt;substanceAdministration&gt;
   	    ...
   	    &lt;consumable&gt;
   	       &lt;activeIngredient&gt;
                    &lt;id root="60a4db80-573d-11db-b0de-0800200c9a66"/&gt;
   	       &lt;/activeIngredient&gt;
   	    &lt;/consumable&gt;
   	    ...
   	 &lt;/substanceAdministration&gt;
         &lt;/highlight&gt;
      &lt;/excerpt&gt;
   &lt;/section&gt;
</pre>
         </p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveIngredient.quantity:</b> A ratio specifying the strength of the ingredient as amount of ingredient (numerator) in amount of medicine (denominator).</p>
         <p>
            <b>InactiveIngredient:</b> Relates a mixture (scoper) to an ingredient (player), where the ingredient is not considered the ActiveIngredient.</p>
         <p>
            <b>InactiveIngredient.quantity:</b> A ratio specifying the strength of the ingredient as amount of ingredient (numerator) in amount of medicine (denominator).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Substance:</b> A chemical substance used as ingredient in medicines.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Substance.code:</b> The code for an ingredient from a controlled vocabulary (e.g., the U.S. FDA UNII code).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Substance.name:</b> The established name of an ingredient. A Substance may be active ingredient or inactive ingredient depending on the Role of the respective name connecting the Substance with the Medicine.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveMoiety:</b> Links to the molecule or ion that is responsible for the intended pharmacological action of the drug substance.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveMoietyEntity:</b> 
The molecule or ion that is responsible for the intended pharmacological action of the drug substance, excluding those appended or associated parts of the molecule that make the molecule an ester, salt (including a salt with hydrogen or coordination bonds), or other noncovalent derivative (such as a complex, chelate, or clathrate).
</p>
         <p>Examples: heparin-sodium and heparin-potassium have the same active moiety, heparin; the active moiety of morphine-hydrochloride is morphine.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveMoietyEntity.code:</b> A code from a controlled vocabulary.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ActiveMoietyEntity.name:</b> The name of the active moiety of the active ingredient.</p>
         <class name="Consumable4" hide="yes"/>
         <class name="Consumable3" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration for the Route Code (SubstanceAdministration):</b> The only purpose of the SubstanceAdministration class in the Medicine model is to represent the labeled route.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration.routeCode:</b> Labeled route of administration.</p>
         <class name="SpecializedKind" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>PharmaceuticalClass:</b> A generalization of Medicine, Substance and ActiveMoiety, can specify any or all of (a) cellular/molecular action (e.g., Ca-channel blocker); (b) physiologic action (e.g., vasodilator); and (c) molecular/chemical class (e.g. aminopenicillin).</p>
         <p>
            <b>PharmaceuticalClass.code:</b> One systematic terminology for the pharmaceutical classes is the U.S. Veteran Adminstration's National Drug File (NDF-RT).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content:</b> A role representing the relationship between the medicine and its package.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content.quantity:</b> A ratio which specifies how many small entities (numerator) are in a big entity (denominator).</p>
         <p>
            <b>PackagedMedicine:</b> A medicine in a container, or package.</p>
         <p>
            <b>PackagedMedicine.code:</b> Specifies the product code for a packaged product (e.g., National Drug Code [NDC] in the U.S.)</p>
         <p>
            <b>PackagedMedicine.formCode:</b> The package type, such as "box" or "bottle".</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content3:</b> 
A role representing the relationship between an (inner) package and its larger (outer) package,
</p>
         <p>The ability to go from a smaller package to a larger package is new in SPL release 3 and is the standard way to describe "intermediate" packaging, which regularly occur with non-solid medicines. For example, a solution for injection (Medicine) is packaged in a vial (a primary package or sometimes called "intermediary" package) and then several such vials are packed in a carton. Notice that the vial is not the Medicine, it is the content in the vial which is the medicine; the vial is just a necessary packaging to hold the liquid.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content3.quantity:</b> A ratio which specifies how many small entities (numerator) are in a big entity (denominator).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Part:</b> A component of a multiple component product [e.g., estrogens, progestins and inert tablets of a contraceptive product.  Multicomponent products such as contraceptives (e.g., separate estrogens and progestins in a single container), can be represented where each drug would be a Part of the parent contraceptive medicine, and the quantity of each represented as a Part.quantity. (The quantity of the parent Medicine would be "1" for a single wheel containing both medications in this example.)</p>
         <p>
            <b>Part.quantity:</b> A ratio specifying the amount of a part (numerator) in an amount (denominator) of the whole Medicine. It is important to note that as all Role quantities the numerator and denominator stand for the amount of the exact kind of entity specified as the part and whole respectively, and not something else. For example, when the medicine is a kit with tablets being the parts, the numerator numbers the amount of tablets of the same kind in the kit. However, if the kit consists of 2 vial-packaged liquids, each vial holding 3 mL, the part quantity specifies the total amount of this liquid (e.g. 6 mL), not 2 (vials). Thus all quantities have the exact same interpretation which is important to draw any quantitative inference from these relationships (e.g. "how much ingredient is in a package?")</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content2:</b> 
A role representing the relationship between a package and its contained smaller packages (deprecated).
</p>
         <p>This third variant of packaging relationship is deprecated and replaced by the part-relationship introduced in release 2. It is retained for a limited time for backwards compatibility as it was present in SPL release 1. This would allow specifying sub-containers of a larger container. However, using this method, there would be no way to specify the content of those sub-containers. The use case for this has now been addressed with the Part role which is used to show parts of the overall product where each part can have its own packaging.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Content2.quantity:</b> A ratio which specifies how many small entities (numerator) are in a big entity (denominator).</p>
         <class name="Subject7" hide="yes"/>
         <class name="Subject6" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>Policy:</b> The purpose of this element is to capture the controlled substance classification or schedule of a drug (e.g., DEA schedule in the U.S.).</p>
         <p>
            <b>Policy.code:</b> The code for the specific controlled substance schedule.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Characteristic:</b> A code-value pair specifying descriptive properties of the medicine, such as color, shape, imprints, etc. The code has a data type of CE and the value has a data type of ANY, which allows codes or numeric values to be specified.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Characteristic.code:</b> 
A code specifying which characteristic of the medicine is being described. The vocabulary domain is MedicationObservationType (a CWE domain which can be extended as necessary). For example, some values that are contained in the SPLLabelData value set within the MedicationObservationType vocabulary domain are listed below:
</p>
         <p>SPLIMPRINTCD - label imprint code - Identifying marks on product</p>
         <p>SPLSIZE - label size - Description of size of the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>SPLSHAPE - label shape - Description of shape of the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>SPLCOLOR - label color - Description of color of the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>SPLCOATING - label coating - Description of the coating of the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>SPLSCORING - label scoring - Description of scoring of the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>SPLSYMBOL - label logo - Description of the logo on the product as called for in regulations</p>
         <p>
            <b>Characteristic.text:</b> A text field that allows entry of free text description of the characteristics.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Characteristic.value:</b> The value of the characteristic, e.g., a code for the specific shape or color, or a physical quantity specification for the size.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Approval:</b> A record of the approval of a Medicine (product) or Substance, signifying that a substance or product is approved for the use specified in the SPL data.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Approval.id:</b> Approval number (which in the U.S. is the New Drug Application (NDA) number)</p>
         <p>
            <b>Approval.statusCode:</b> Tells whether approval was granted (complete) or whether the approval is presently in progress (active).  Thus, a substance or product that is not approved yet but about which an approval is in process and approval number is known can also have the Approval structure but must indicate a status of "active" in the Approval.statusCode.  Likewise, a substance or product whose approval has been withdrawn would have a statusCode of "obsolete".</p>
         <p>
            <b>Author2:</b> The author of the Approval signifies the Territory (country or state) for which approval was granted, with optionally some detail about the approving Agency.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Author2.time:</b> The date when Approval was granted.</p>
         <p>
            <b>TerritorialAuthority:</b> A Role linking the medicinal product oversight Agency (e.g. "U.S. FDA") with its Country of jurisdiction. The purpose of this role is to allow either the Country code alone or the Agency or both to be specified as the author of approvals.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Territory:</b> A country.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Territory.code:</b> The country code</p>
         <p>
            <b>Territory.name:</b> The counry name, if not coded.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Agency:</b> The medicinal product oversight authority.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Agency.name:</b> Name of the agency.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id=""><head>Clinical Use Data Structures</head>
         <p>
            <b>Highlight:</b> 
An abstract or excerpt of a single topic discussed in a single section or sub-section.  This abstract is presented in the form of a short text fragment as well as with structured information.  The highlights are targeted at prescribers and judiciously chosen to present the most important information the prescriber needs to know in order to prescribe a medicine safely and effectively. 
</p>
         <p>The Highlights can be assembled to form a short abstract of the comprehensive prescribing information as a "quick reference" for the prescriber.</p>
         <p>All structured information to specify the clinical use of the drug is connected through the highlights element. The practical purpose of this construct is to focus the coding of information on the most important points guiding the appropriate use of the medicine without attempting to code nuances which would not be part of a concise summary. It also facilitates review of the structured information for correctness. Specific information structures cover the general topics: Indication, Dosage and Administration, Adverse Events, Interactions, Contraindications and other Cautions or Warnings, as well as Monitoring guidelines.</p>
         <class name="ExcerptFrom" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration Defining Appropriate Use (SubstanceAdministration1):</b> Since the clinical medication module is all about appropriate and safe use of the drug, this "use" of the drug, i.e., the central SubstanceAdministration is the pivot of all structured data of the highlights.  This SubstanceAdministration is a definition and defines the key data of a proper use of the medicine.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration1.effectiveTime:</b> 
Timing patterns (e.g., twice a day, every 8 hours, etc.) and timing boundaries (e.g., for 10 days) can be specified for the main SubstanceAdministration and its component SubstanceAdministration.
</p>
         <p>In addition, SubstanceAdministration.effectiveTime can give general timing constraints, such as, "give 1 hour before meal". However, more specific clinical situations in which to give the medicine (e.g., "15 minutes before exercise" or "before sexual intercourse", etc.) must be specified using preconditions to a ClinicalSituationCriterion.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration1.doseQuantity:</b> Amount of the medicine given at one single administration. The medicine in terms of which this dose is specified can be clarified using the consumable participation which leads either to the Medicine or to an ActiveIngredient. This can be specified by means of reference to the ManufacturedProduct.id or the ActiveIngredient.id, without requiring repeating the detail of these roles and entities playing the roles.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration1.maxDoseQuantity:</b> A ratio specifying a "do not exceed" dose, as a maximum dose (see doseQuantity) over a period of time. E.g. maximum amount per any time interval, e.g., 4 g in any 24-hour period.</p>
         <class name="Subject1" title="Highlight to SubstanceAdministration" hide="yes"/>
         <class name="Consumable2" title="SubstanceAdministration to Specific Medicine" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>Indication (Reason):</b> 
An ActRelationship of type "reason" representing the indication of the substance administration by linking to an observation criterion. The typeCode of the reason ActRelationship can be further refined to indicate different motivations, such as therapeutic reason (as a remedy), prophylactic reason (as a means of prevention), or as diagnostic reason (something done to diagnose the disease.
</p>
         <p>
            <b>Reason.typeCode:</b> The typeCode of the reason ActRelationship can be further refined to indicate different motivations, such as therapeutic reason (as a remedy), prophylactic reason (as a means of prevention), or as diagnostic reason (something done to diagnose the disease.</p>
         <p>
            <b>IndicationObservationCriterion:</b> An observation criterion that is specified as the "reason" (ActRelationship) of the SubstanceAdministration.  The observation criterion consists of a code to indicate that the observation is a diagnoses, symptoms, conditions, etc. and a value-code to represent the specific indication, e.g. hypertension, etc.</p>
         <p>
            <b>IndicationObservationCriterion.code:</b> A code indicating that the observation is a diagnoses, symptoms, conditions, etc.</p>
         <p>
            <b>IndicationObservationCriterion.value:</b> A value-code representing the specific indication, e.g. hypertension, etc.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Precondition:</b> An ActRelationship that links ClinicalSitutaionCriteria with the pivotal SubstanceAdministration. A ClinicalSituationCriterion is a choice of either ObservationCriterion, SubstanceAdministrationCriterion or general ActCriterion. These preconditions further limit the indication to a specific population or other clinical situation. Multiple preconditions can be specified. When multiple criteria are specified, they are logically conjoined (AND), i.e., they must all hold true.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Precondition.pauseQuantity:</b> Specifies a certain time constraint between the clinical situation and the use of the drug. E.g., "use 15 minutes before exercise" or "X should be given at least 8 hours after Y".</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationCriterion:</b> The ObservationCriterion is similar to the IndicationObservationCriterion with a code and a value, but the value can express both coded and quantitative data types for clinical conditions as well as, for instance, age ranges.  The clinical situation criteria can be stated positively as requirements (e.g. patient over 12 years of age) or negatively as limitations or exclusion criteria (e.g., not for patient under 12 years of age.)</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationCriterion.code:</b> A code indicating that the observation is a diagnosis, symptom, condition, lab-observation, etc.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationCriterion.value:</b> The value of the observation, i.e. a specific condition code (e.g. hypertension, renal failure, etc.), or, in case of numeric observations a physical quantity.</p>
         <p>
            <b>TherapeuticClass:</b> 
The treatment class allows to give a code that classifies the intent of the treatment, i.e., "antihypertensive". These classifications are sometimes considered properties of the substance and in that case are specified as the classifying codes (generalization) of the substance or product.  However, some substances have multiple purposes, and it is that purpose that eventually determines the proper dosage.  This is sometimes known as indication "grouping".
</p>
         <p>Note: Two mechanisms are specified to represent grouping or classifications of the drug substances on the one hand and their use on the other hand. Pharmacologic class (e.g., aminopenicillin, aminoglycosides, etc.) or mechanism of action (e.g., MAO inhibitor, ACE inhibitor, Ca-channel blocker, beta-2-blocker, etc.) is a classification of drug substances, either of drug products, their active ingredients or active moiety, and all represented by generalization Roles to a PharmaceuticalClass. Classification of treatment intent (e.g., antihypertensive, antiphlogistic, antiinferctive, etc.) are classifications of the SubstanceAdministration act, and represented as a generalization of the treatment act through the generalization ActRelationship to TreatmentClass.</p>
         <class name="Generalization" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>Adverse Situation (Issue):</b> Adverse events, interactions, contraindications and other issues of special caution are represented in one uniform structure. The Pharmacy SIG has established a special kind of Act, called Issue for this purpose.  An Issue has one or more other Acts as subjects and indicate that there is a certain problem requiring special caution with its subject Acts.  In the case of SPL, the subject is the SubstanceAdministration described in the label.  One or more additional subjects can be used to specify additional ClinicalSituationCriteria such as ObservationCriteria or SubstanceAdministrationCriteria.  The latter is used to represent interactions which is an Issue involving the administration of two substances.</p>
         <class name="Subject4" title="SubstanceAdministration to Issue" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>Risk:</b> An ActRelationship linking an Issue to a risk, i.e. a coded ConsequenceObservation criterion with information about severity and frequency of the undesired outcome.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Adverse Outcome (ConsequenceObservation):</b> An observation criterion specifying the adverse outcome as the usual code-value pair of an observation.</p>
         <p>
            <b>CauseOf:</b> The description of the risk can nest to refine to a level of specificity that makes the adverse event actually recognizable.  For example, a risk may be specified as a "hypersensitivity syndrome" but then specific manifestations may be given including "rash," or "Guillain-Barr&#233; Syndrome", or even quantitative measures as "leukopenia with WBC below 1000/mm3."</p>
         <p>
            <b>Severity:</b> A specification of severity of an adverse event as an observation criterion.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Frequency:</b> A specification of frequency of occurrence of an adverse event as an observation criterion.</p>
         <class name="Subject2" title="Adverse Outcome to Serverity and Frequency" hide="yes"/>
         <class name="Subject3" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>ActCriterion:</b> The ActCriterion is a general criterion to give a procedure code or a code of any other clinical service that would be used to limit either positively or negatively the indication of the drug.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministrationCriterion:</b> The SubstanceAdministrationCriterion specifies another treatment and is used by Issue to specify an interacting treatment, and with a Precondition to specify adjunctive treatment.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Consumable1:</b> The participation linking the SubstanceAdministrationCritetion with the specification of the other administered substance.</p>
         <class name="AdministerableMaterial" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>MaterialKind:</b> A specificiation of a medicine or food material.</p>
         <p>
            <b>MaterialKind.code:</b> Code specifiying medicine or food material. This code often uses the same code systems as the PharmaceuticalClass.</p>
         <p>
            <b>MaintenanceGoal2:</b> The indication can be further specified to express an objective as to what the treatment should accomplish.  For instance, if the goal of the treatment is absence of acute asthma attacks, the maintenance goal can describe this.  This is used to allow the treatment effect to be coded and still keep the indication a simple code that is comparable with actual patient problem list data.  For instance, the indication would be "asthma" and the maintenance goal would be "no bronchiospasm" to indicate "prevention of bronchiospasm in patients with asthma".</p>
         <p>
            <b>DerivedFrom:</b> 
Links a SubstanceAdministation to a specified kind of Observation which is used for calculated dosage. An example would be:
</p>
         <p>
            <pre>
   &lt;substanceAdministration&gt;
      ...
      &lt;maxDoseQuantity xsi:type="PQXF" value="57" unit="mg/kg"&gt;
         &lt;factor localVariableName="bodyMass"/&gt;  
      &lt;/maxDoseQuantity&gt;
      ...
      &lt;consumable&gt;
         &lt;activeIngredient ... /&gt;
      &lt;/consumable&gt;
      &lt;derivedFrom&gt;
         &lt;localVariableName&gt;bodyMass&lt;/localVariableName&gt;
         &lt;monitoringObservation&gt;
            &lt;code code="29463-7" codeSystem="&amp;LOINC;" displayName="BODY WEIGHT:MASS:PT:^PATIENT:QN"/&gt;
         &lt;/monitoringObservation&gt;
      &lt;/derivedFrom&gt;
   &lt;/substanceAdministration&gt;
</pre>
         </p>
         <p>Note: the PQXF data type is forthcoming in the next release of the HL7 data type specification.</p>
         <p>
            <b>ObservationDefinition:</b> Specifies a kind of Observation which is used for calculated dosage.</p>
         <class name="Component3" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration2:</b> A subordinate component SusbtanceAdministration which carries the doseQuantity for a step in a complex dosage plan.  This is used for example, to specify a loading dose, or a tapering dose.
</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration2.effectiveTime:</b> Specification of all time aspects of the administration schedule, including frequency and overall duration.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration2.repeatNumber:</b> A regimen with a loading dose is specified using two components, the first representing the initial dose, with repeatNumber = 1 (meaning "once") or any other limitation in number or time.  That first component would be followed by a second component that can repeat for the rest of the duration of the therapy.</p>
         <p>
            <b>SubstanceAdministration2.doseQuantity:</b> The doseQuantity, see the same attribute in the pivotal SubstanceAdministration for detail.</p>
         <p>
            <b>Protocol:</b> Specifies a safe use protocol wherein a substance administration is recommended to be accompanied by monitoring observations, i.e. tests such as drug level tests, pharamacokinetic parameter tests (renal function), or adverse effect tests (hypotension, liver enzymes) required.  This Protocol contains MonitoringObservation steps and maintenance goals as MonitoringObservationCriteria.</p>
         <p>
            <b>MonitoringObservation:</b> Prescribe the tests that should be performed and in what frequency.  MonitoringObservation.code detailing the tests that should be performed (e.g. thrombocytes count, liver enzymes, etc.) The MonitoringObservation.effectiveTime is used to specify the recommended frequency of these tests in the same way as the frequency of SubstanceAdministration is specified.</p>
         <class name="Component1" title="SubstanceAdministration in Protocol" hide="yes"/>
         <class name="Component2" title="Monitoring as Component of Protocol" hide="yes"/>
         <p>
            <b>MaintenanceGoal1:</b> Specifies a criterion (e.g., range) within which certain test results should remain, such as blood levels of the drug or its metabolites should remain to ensure efficacy and avoid toxicity.  MonitoringObservation.code specifies the observations that would be performed (e.g. digoxin level, gentamicin level, etc.) and the MonitoringObservation.value specifies a result-value interval with single bounds (e.g. maximal limits) or two bounds (range) that should be maintained throughout the treatment.</p>
      </div4>
   </div3>
			</descriptive>
			<storydivn identifier="sbs-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Storyboards" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="sbs-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="sstop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="sstop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<story identifier="PORP_ST050001UV03" name="Spl Release Three Structured Product Label Document" familiarName="Publishing a Product Label" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_ST050001UV03-str" sortPrefix="40|STRUCTURED PRODUCT LABEL DOCUMENT" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:19:05" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="purp-PORP_ST050001UV03" name="Purpose" parent="PORP_ST050001UV03-str" id="purp-PORP_ST050001UV03-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:19:05">
						<p>A drug product manufacturer is required by an applicable territorial medicinal product oversight authority to create a product information document at different points in the product life-cycle. This document contain all the approved information about the nature and use of the medicinal product, and has therefore been negotiated with the oversight agency. At the end of that negotiation the manufacturer submits an SPL document to the oversight authority. The oversight authority in turn may submit the document to public information repositories also.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<diagref ref="PORP_ST050001UV03.gif"/>
				</story>
			</storydivn>
			<approledivn identifier="roles-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Application Roles" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="roles-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="arop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="arop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<artree>
					<artreeitem>
						<arref role="included" ref="PORP_AR050002UV03-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Receiver" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Recipient" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR050002UV03"/>
					</artreeitem>
					<artreeitem>
						<arref role="included" ref="PORP_AR050001UV03-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Informer" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Submitter" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR050001UV03"/>
					</artreeitem>
				</artree>
				<approle identifier="PORP_AR050002UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event Receiver" familiarName="Structured Product Label Recipient" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_AR050002UV03-ar" sortPrefix="40|20|99|22|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" hidden="no" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:22:55" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_AR050002UV03" name="Description" parent="PORP_AR050002UV03-ar" id="desc-PORP_AR050002UV03-ar" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:22:55">
						<p>Any person or organization, including the public at large, or an agent of the public (such as a regulatory authority) who is the recipient of product label document.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<intref role="receives" ref="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" class="changed" refIdentifier="PORP_IN050001UV03"/>
				</approle>
				<approle identifier="PORP_AR050001UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event Informer" familiarName="Structured Product Label Submitter" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_AR050001UV03-ar" sortPrefix="40|20|99|25|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" hidden="no" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:23:26" class="inserted">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_AR050001UV03" name="Description" parent="PORP_AR050001UV03-ar" id="desc-PORP_AR050001UV03-ar" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:23:26">
						<p>An organization who is required by law to submit product information document because it is responsible for the creation or marketing of a product, or any other person or organization compelled by other motives to submit information about products, whether originally created or not. This includes, original manufacturers, repackagers, relabelers, and public agencies or private information publishers who submit product information documents.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<intref role="sends" ref="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" class="changed" refIdentifier="PORP_IN050001UV03"/>
				</approle>
			</approledivn>
			<triggerdivn identifier="tes-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Trigger Events" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="tes-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="teop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="teop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<trigger identifier="PORP_TE050001UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event Notification" familiarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_TE050001UV03-te" role="Interaction based" sortPrefix="40|20|99||05|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" class="inserted" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:23:50">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_TE050001UV03" name="Description" parent="PORP_TE050001UV03-te" id="desc-PORP_TE050001UV03-te" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:23:50">
						<p>This event is triggered by the sender's business rules, may be triggered by the completion of a new SPL document or the revision of an exitsing SPL document. This is typically governed by legal statutes which set points such as the completion of a new drug application, the change of product information or annual reports as requiring submission of an SPL document.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<statrans transitionFQN="(interaction)" focalClass="Document">
						<rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="PORP_RM050032UV-rmi" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="PORP_RM050032UV"/>
					</statrans>
					<intref role="fires" ref="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" class="changed" refIdentifier="PORP_IN050001UV03"/>
				</trigger>
			</triggerdivn>
			<rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="rmims-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="rmop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="rmop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<rmim identifier="PORP_RM050032UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event" familiarName="Structured Product Label Document" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_RM050032UV03-rmi" sortPrefix="40|20|99|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" class="inserted" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:08">
					<diagref ref="PORP_RM050032UV.gif"/>
					<hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD050032UV03"/>
				</rmim>
			</rmimdivn>
			<hmddivn identifier="hmds-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="hmds-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="hdop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="hdop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<hmd identifier="PORP_HD050032UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event" familiarName="Structured Product Label Document" parent="PORP_RM050032UV03-rmi" id="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" sortPrefix="40|20|99|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" class="inserted" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:23">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_HD050032UV03" name="Description" parent="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" id="desc-PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:23">
						<p>The hierarchical model which is derived from the RMIM in a straight forward way. As for all HL7 specifications, this hierarchical model determines the hierarchy and order of elements in the final SPL XML schema.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PORP_HD050032UV03"/>
					<rmimref role="parent" ref="PORP_RM050032UV03-rmi" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_RM050032UV03"/>
					<msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT050032UV03"/>
				</hmd>
			</hmddivn>
			<msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="msgs-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<msgtype identifier="PORP_MT050032UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event" familiarName="Structured Product Label Document" parent="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" id="PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" sortPrefix="40|20|99|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" class="inserted" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:30">
					<descriptive identifier="walkthru-PORP_MT050032UV03" name="Design Walk-through" parent="PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" id="walkthru-PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" role="walkThrough" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:30">
						<p>This message type is the ultimate HL7 model structure from which the SPL XML schema is generated automatically. The structure of this "message type" (MT) is identical in to its related hierarchical model (HM).</p>
					</descriptive>
					<msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORP_MT050032UV03"/>
					<hmdref role="parent" ref="PORP_HD050032UV03-hmd" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_HD050032UV03"/>
					<intref role="sentIn" ref="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" class="changed" refIdentifier="PORP_IN050001UV03"/>
				</msgtype>
			</msgtypedivn>
			<interactiondivn identifier="ints-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Interactions" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="ints-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
				<descriptive identifier="inop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Reference" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="inop-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic">
					<p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p>
				</descriptive>
				<interaction identifier="PORP_IN050001UV03" name="Spl Release Three Event Notification" familiarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="40|20|99|05|" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="3" class="changed" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:56">
					<descriptive identifier="desc-PORP_IN050001UV03" name="Description" parent="PORP_IN050001UV03-int" id="desc-PORP_IN050001UV03-int" lastEdit="2008-04-27T12:24:56">
						<p>The SPL document which contains only the XML text. The document may contain references to media files, such as images, which should accompany the SPL document itself. This wrapping of files is not specified, and guidances exist by regulatory authorities who accept SPL.</p>
					</descriptive>
					<arref role="sendrole" ref="PORP_AR050001UV03-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Informer" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Submitter" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR050001UV03"/>
					<arref role="rcvrole" ref="PORP_AR050002UV03-ar" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Receiver" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Recipient" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_AR050002UV03"/>
					<teref role="trigger" ref="PORP_TE050001UV03-te" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Spl Release Three Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Structured Product Label Document Submission" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_TE050001UV03"/>
					<msgref role="msgtype" ref="PORP_MT050032UV03-msg" sectID="hmporp" sectType="SB" refName="Structured Product Label Document" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORP_MT050032UV03"/>
				</interaction>
			</interactiondivn>
			<annexdivn identifier="annx-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Implementation Guide" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="annx-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" role="IG" baseClass="SplReleaseThree" ballotStatus="InformativeStandard" ballotNumber="3">
				<descriptive identifier="annxInt-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree" name="Introduction" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" id="annxInt-PORP_DO000001UV-SplReleaseThree-ic" lastEdit="2006-10-26T14:24:59">
					<p>This Annex holds an Implementation Guide that has been developed to support the Implementation of Structured Product Labeling (SPL), Release 3, an HL7  approved standard. </p>
					<p>This document is currently in a "stand-alone" format.  HL7 currently has no approved format for implementation guides.  When such a format becomes available, this document will be converted so that it can be represented here directly as domain content.  <artref ref="file:SPL-R3-ImplementationGuide.zip" alt="Click here to download a copy of the approved document."/>
					</p>
				</descriptive>
			</annexdivn>
		</subdivn>
		<indexdivn identifier="cindx-PORP_DO000001UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="cindx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic">
			<indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-icc1id"/>
			<indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-icc2id"/>
		</indexdivn>
		<indexdivn identifier="indx-PORP_DO000001UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="indx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic">
			<indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-ic1id"/>
			<indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-ic2id"/>
			<indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-PORP_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORP_DO000001UV-ic3id"/>
		</indexdivn>
	</body>
</spec>
