<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/3/2008 3:47:00 PM">
	<header>
		<title>Glossary</title>
		<version>0</version>
		<date>6/3/2008</date>
	</header>
	<body>
		<div1 id="glossary">
			<head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head>
			<div2 id="glossary-PORP_DO000001UV">
				<head>PORP_DO000001UV Glossary</head>
				<glist role="additionalterms">
					<gitem id="document" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:00:13">
						<label>Document</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T17:00:13">
							<p>Regulatory processes require the submission of documents from the Applicant to the Regulatory Authority. These documents are varied in focus and are often defined by the field of study (i.e., GLP or GCP guidelines) or by the regulatory application requirements of the region or Regulatory Authority (e.g., Integrated Summary of Safety, Pharmacokinetics Written Summary). The RPS message specification provides for the defining of documents in the message.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="submission" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:57:30">
						<label>Submission</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:57:30">
							<p>A compilation of the contents of one or more submission units supporting a specific regulatory purpose or decision. In most cases, the compilation of the submission units is utilized in the assessment of a product's quality, safety and effectiveness.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="application" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:56:27">
						<label>Application</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:56:27">
							<p>All submissions that are grouped together for regulatory purposes.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="logical_document" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:58:54">
						<label>Logical Document</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:58:54">
							<p>When a document is provided as a collection of files, the terms document and file are no longer synonymous. Thus, the term logical document is used to explicitly differentiate a file from a document and to provide a consistent concept that embraces a document as a collection of files.  The files comprising the logical document, when organized together, constitute the document. The RPS message specification provides for the defining of a document in the message using a keyword value; in the case of a logical document, all files will share the same keyword value.</p>
							<p>Examples of Logical Documents:</p>
							<p>Example 1: The report on the findings of a study may consist of written documentation (e.g., report.pdf), supporting data (e.g., datasets.xpt) and other electronically transmitted information (e.g., images.pdf or ecgs.xml). All the information provided in support of the evaluation of the study comprise the logical document of the study report. A logical document may contain other logical documents (e.g., study protocol, case report form).</p>
							<p>Example 2:  The protocol for a study is initially provided as a single PDF file. Over time, the protocol may be modified through amendments or other administrative attachments creating the situation where the complete protocol is no longer a single PDF file. The files comprising the protocol at this latter stage of the protocols lifecycle comprise the logical document of the protocol.</p>
							<p>Example 3: In an eCTD submission, CMC information on the drug substance is to be provided by manufacturer. Thus, all the regulatory files defined by the CMC section of the eCTD for the manufacture of a specific drug substance by a particular manufacturer comprise the logical document of that substance-manufacturer information.  </p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="submission_unit_message" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:59:20">
						<label>Submission Unit Message</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:59:20">
							<p>An XML construct containing all file references (not including the files) in a submission unit which describe the properties of the files (attributes and metadata information), the links that cross reference files and the operations to perform on files.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="submission_unit" lastEdit="2006-03-01T14:46:48">
						<label>Submission Unit</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-01T14:46:48">
							<p>A package of files as well as all file references shipped to the agency at one time. The file references are collectively called the submission unit message.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
					<gitem id="file" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:57:03">
						<label>File</label>
						<def domainid="PORP_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-03-20T16:57:03">
							<p>A physical document unit prepared by a Applicant for review by the Regulatory Authority (e.g., a PDF file).  A document may be provided as a single file or as a collection of files. When a document is provided as a single file, the terms file and document are often used interchangeably; it is critical to the understanding of the RPS electronic message construct to differentiate a file from a document. A file referenced in a submission message. Lifecycle occurs on the files reference not on the file.</p>
						</def>
					</gitem>
				</glist>
			</div2>
		</div1>
	</body>
</spec>
