<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="6/5/2008 5:12:21 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>6/5/2008</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-PORT_DO000001UV"><head>PORT_DO000001UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="types_of_annotation_to_region_relationships" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:43:57"><label>Types of Annotation to Region Relationships</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:43:57"><p>There are some annotation codes that can mean slightly different things depending on the context.  For example, the annotation "Atrial Fibrillation (AFib)" could mean two different things when related to a region: "The subject was in AFib here.", or "The subject experienced an episode of AFib from here to there." There are 2 act relationships in HL7 to distinguish between these two types of annotations.  The "has support" relationship is the more general one to be used for "there is AFib here" types of annotations.  The "has bounded support" relationship can be used to declare the boundaries of the annotation, "there is a (bounded) episode of AFib here."</p></def></gitem><gitem id="median_beat_waveforms" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:42:08"><label>Median Beat Waveforms</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:42:08"><p>Computer algorithms can derive a representative beat from a series of beats having the same morphology (same focus, etc.).  Sometimes a trial protocol will specify the usage of a "median beat" for taking measurements. If a median beat is used, and the rhythm data from which it is derived is wanted by the FDA, the median beat is related to the rhythm waveforms via an analysis region.  The median is typically composed of as many leads as the rhythm waveforms from which it was derived.  The relative time represents time within the representative cycle, not time relative to the beginning of the rhythm waveforms.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="region_specification" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:43:21"><label>Region Specification</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:43:21"><p>There are 2 basic types of regions: a fully specified region and a partially specified one.  The fully specified region is one where each dimension within the Observation Series to be included in the region has a boundary defined.  For example, if an episode of ST elevation is observed in leads V4 and V5, a fully specified region would contain 3 boundaries: one for time, one for V4, and one for V5.  The boundary in time would be specified with an interval in time (IVL&lt;PQ&gt;).  The boundaries on V4 and V5 would be infinite intervals (the entire range of voltages for both leads are to be included in the region for ST elevation). A partially specified region assumes all dimensions in the Observation Series are included in the region except for the boundaries specified.  For example, if a global QRS onset is observed, only a boundary for time is required.  All the other dimensions (leads) would be included in the partially specified region.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="waveform_encoding" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:44:35"><label>Waveform Encoding</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:44:35"><p>The rhythm waveforms are encoded as an Observation Series in HL7.  The series contains one or more Correlated Observation Sequences ("correlation" for short).  Each correlation encodes the leads that were sampled together and correlated with the same relative time points. If all 12 leads were sampled together (assuming a 12-lead ECG), only one correlation is required.  This correlation would contain a sequence for relative time and 12 sequences for the 12 different leads.  If time was evenly sampled (as it usually is), a GLIST&lt;&gt; is used for generating the sequence of time points from a few parameters.  The lead sequences would use the SLIST&lt;&gt; for encoding the voltages.  The SLIST&lt;&gt; can factor out a common offset and scale factor (if the raw integer A/D values encoded).  The offset and scale factor can be used for converting the stored values to real physical quantities. If a 12-lead ECG is recorded on a device that only samples 3 leads at a time, for example, the Observation Series would contain 4 correlations.  Each correlation would encode the leads that were sampled together.  Each correlation would contain one sequence for time relative to the beginning of the recording, and 3 sequences for the 3 leads sampled.  If the device has a few more channels and records one or more rhythm leads during the whole recording, the rhythm leads would appear in each correlation as well.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="rhythm_waveforms" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:40:03"><label>Rhythm Waveforms</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:40:03"><p>These are the waveforms directly collected from the subject and used for clinical trial research.  If measurements were taken from these, annotations should show the fudicial markings for those measurements.  The specific set of fudicial markings is specified by the trial protocol. If the waveforms have been enhanced to facilitate the measurement process, control variables should indicate what enhancements were made.  For example, filtering, etc.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="rhythm_waveform_annotations" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:41:35"><label>Rhythm Waveform Annotations</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:41:35"><p>Some annotations will be specific to areas in time but will apply to all the leads.  For example, the presence of an arrhythmia, or a period of time where the patient was performing some activity that affects the ECG.  Pacer spikes and perhaps beat locations are also indicated as points or areas in time.  Fudicial markings made by superimposing all the leads would also fall into this category. *	Rhythm annotation example *	Patient activity example *	Pacer spikes example *	Beat location example *	Beat classification example *	Global fudicial markings example Other annotations will be specific to areas in time AND one or more leads.  Annotations falling into this category include fudicial markings for beat measurements made on particular leads, lead-specific episodes such as ST elevation, etc. *	Fudicial markings example *	Isoelectric example *	ST elevation example</p></def></gitem><gitem id="analysis_region" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:41:15"><label>Analysis Region</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:41:15"><p>The analysis region defines an area in time upon which algorithms performed some analysis.  The analysis may be for the derivation of a median beat, and/or interpretation statements, global measurements, etc.  If the rhythm waveforms are long enough to require (local) analysis in multiple places, a region will define each.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="median_beat_annotations" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:42:51"><label>Median Beat Annotations</label><def domainid="PORT_DO000001UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2002-12-15T23:42:51"><p>Just like annotations on the rhythm data, annotations can be made on the median beat.  Fudicial markings related to the measurements specified by the trial protocol can be made globally (on all leads) or locally (on some leads).  Episode annotations (such as arrhythmias, ST elevation episodes, etc.) would not be made on the median beat (for obvious reasons). Refer to examples from rhythm waveforms annotations.</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

