<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" sectionCode="AMPRSC" lastEdit="6/5/2008 5:23:04 PM" rendered="6/5/2008 5:23:31 PM"><header><title>Domain: Scheduling</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="1"/><date>6/5/2008</date><authlist><author><role>Scheduling &amp; Logistics Co-Chair</role><name key="Benson, Anita">Anita Benson</name><affiliation>Datascene</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="de Jong, Tom">Tom de Jong</name><affiliation>ChipSoft B.V.</affiliation></author><author><role>Scheduling &amp; Logistics Co-Chair</role><name key="Foard, Jane">Jane Foard</name><affiliation>McKesson Information Solutions</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="Reynolds, Melvin">Melvin Reynolds</name><affiliation>AMS Consulting</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="prefNotes"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>This first release of Scheduling supports the simple scenario of a scheduling application sending basic notifications to an auxiliary application.  The intent is to establish a standard for the minimum functionaity that is useful and comprehensive enough to explore the important concepts.  This miimum functionality is notifications of new appointments, revised appontments, cancelled appointments, and rescheduled appointments.  Later releases will build upon this basic set of interactins to include requests and queries.  In addition to appointments, Scheduling also includes the concepts of resource time slots. Slots will also be supported in later releases.</p></div1><div1 id="prefAck"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>In addition to the authors, the Scheudling and Logistics Techinical Committee would like to thank Dave McDowell of Chartlinks for his cotributions in the early days and later the helpful comments from the VA and Oracle.</p></div1><div1 id="prefAssump"><head>Prerequisites, Assumptions &amp; Conventions</head><p>The following prerequisites, assumptions, and conventions apply to this first release of Scheduling.</p><div2 id="prefPrereq"><head>Prerequisites</head><p>A Scheduling message can specify individual resources associated with an appointment.  A prerequisite for exchanging messages about resources is a synchronized catalog of locations, equipment, supply items, and staff.  These resources can be identified by ID, name or type.</p></div2><div2 id="prefAssumpts"><head>Assumtions</head><p>Scheduling messages are genereic and can be used to schedule any type of activity.  The basic assumption behind Scheduling messages is that these messages can be customized.  Therefore, the class code and Act.code for the Appointment is not constrained.  The assumption is that they will be specified during implementation or at run time according to the type of activity being scheduled.</p></div2><div2 id="prefConven"><head>Conventions</head><p>There are some conventions used by Scheduling that are slightly different from other domains.  Since Scheduling is active before the actual service is performed, some of the prototypical state and transition names are misleading when used within the Scheduing context.  Therefore, Scheduling follows the convention of using New rather than Activate to indicate that a new appointment has been booked.  Also, Scheduling uses Cancel rather than Abort to indicate that an appoiintment is no longer booked.</p><p>In addition to naming conventions, revising the time of an appointment is a frequent and special case of appointment revisions.  For this reason, there is a separate trigger event and interaction for Reschedule Appointment in addition to Revise Appointment.</p><p>Another convention is the use of the participation effective times to indicate when a resource is needed before or after the actual Appointment time.  In other domain messages, activity time may be used for this purpose.  The effective time in the Appointment is the default and usually, the patient's time.</p></div2></div1><div1 id="prefIssue"><head>Known Issues &amp; Planned Changes</head><p>There are two known issues that have been discovered since Release 1 was finalized.  The first is the timing of participations in the Reschedule Appointment message.  Since each participation may have a different effective time from the effective time of the Appointment, the Reschedule message must contain these participation times also.  The second issue is the lack of a Supply Order ID.  These issues are easily remedied without viololating backwards compatibility and will be part of Release 2. </p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Full Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="New Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010100UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PRSC_MT010101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010101UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Revise Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010200UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PRSC_MT010201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010201UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Minimum Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Cancel Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020100UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PRSC_MT020101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020101UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PRSC_HD020200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Reschedule Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020200UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PRSC_MT020201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020201UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2005-06-13T01:28:53"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p>In Version 3, Scheduling is both a domain and a process.  As a domain, Scheduling offers a generic set of messages and behavior to implement any number of Scheduling scenarios. As a process, Scheduling offers an abstract data model and a set of operations to any domain within HL7 that utilizes scheduling concepts.  We can consider Scheduling as a <emph>service</emph> and the use of that service as an <emph>interface</emph>.  This release of V3 contains generic scheduling messages that can be implemented by themselves or they can be used as a pattern for domain-specific messages.</p><p>The scheduling  messages in this section are designed to communicate various events related to the scheduling of generic appointments for healthcare services.  There are three basic types of interactions defined in the scheduling domain:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Request messages and their responses </p></item><item><p>Query messages and their responses, and </p></item><item><p>Unsolicited notifications </p></item></list><p>Request transactions communicate requests for the scheduling of appointments for healthcare services or for the booking of resource slots.  These transactions occur between placer (requesting) applications and fulfiller (scheduling) applications.  The query transactions allow any application to query the current schedule of booked and available slots or booked appointments.  Unsolicited transactions provide for the notification of scheduling information between systems.</p><p>For this publication of the HL7 Scheduling standard, we are limiting the scope to four basic appointment notification interactions:  New Appointment, Revise Appointment, Cancel Appointment. and Reschedule Appointment  Future releases will expand the scope to include additional scenarios, including requests, queries and slot management.</p><p><emph role="strong">Scheduling as an Interface to Services</emph></p><p>To understand Scheduling as a service, consider the Unified Modeling Language (UML) concept of an interface in the graphic below.  In object terminology, an <emph>interface</emph> is a collection of operations that are used to specify a <emph>service</emph> of a class or component.  In HL7 Version 3, the ActAppointment class is the focus class for all scheduling notification messages.  The initial operations offered by the ActAppointment class are the four interactions listed above.  The domain classes that might interface to Scheduling are Encounter, Procedure, Observation, etc. as listed along the right-hand side of the graphic.</p><p><graphic source="PRSC_NA000003.gif" alt="Scheduling is a Service offered by the generic ActAppointment class."></graphic></p><p>The interface concept defines a service that is realized by an object through its operations.  These operations are the interactions listed inside the <emph>interface</emph> object in the graphic.  </p><p><emph role="strong">Definitions and Relationships</emph></p><p>In this section, a generic scheduling service is defined using abstract concepts that apply equally well to any scheduling activity.  While some of the following concepts are not supported in this first release, it is important to understand the entire Scheduling domain first by reviewing the definitions.  In addition to the Patient, which is defined as elsewhere in this standard, the following terms have a special meaning within the context of HL7 V3 Scheduling:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Schedules</emph> control the allocation of slots to certain services and the use of particular resources.  They consist of a set of open, booked, reserved, and blocked slots for one particular service or resource.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Slots</emph> are identifiable periods of time that can be scheduled. 		</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Open slots</emph> are periods of time on a schedule during which a service may occur and/or a resource is available for use.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Booked slots</emph> are periods of time on a schedule that have already been reserved.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Reserved slots</emph> are periods of time on a schedule that have been tentatively or generally reserved (for example, a block of time set aside for new patients)</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Blocked slots</emph> on a schedule are periods of time during which a service or resource is unavailable for reasons other than booked appointments (for example, a piece of equipment may be unavailable for maintenance reasons).</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointments</emph> occupy sets of one or more booked slots on a schedule.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Repeating appointments</emph> are repetitions of the same appointment occurring at later slots but sharing the same patient, service and resource characteristics as the first appointment in the repeating series.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Services</emph> are real-world events, such as clinic appointments, the performance of which is controlled by a schedule. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Resources</emph> are tangible items whose use is controlled by a schedule.  These items are often people, locations, or things low in supply but high in demand.</p></item></list><p>This Scheduling standard supports both closely and loosely-coupled systems.  In general, closely-coupled systems will need to exchange slot information frequently in order to stay synchronized, while more loosely-coupled systems can exchange appointment information without needing to be constantly synchronized.  The Patient can be identified with an ID or by name and the resources can be specified by ID or by type.</p><p><emph role="strong">Application Roles</emph></p><p>Many application roles have been identified within the scheduling process.  Shown below are the definitions of these application roles.  For this publication of the HL7 Scheduling standard, all application roles are not supported due to the limited scope.  It is important to note that a scheduling application can fulfill multiple roles.  For example, the application can be both an informer of an appointment as well as a requestor for an appointment from another application.  .</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Informer</emph> - In this role, the application notifies a tracking system that an appointment has been booked or modified in some way.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Tracker</emph> - In this role the application is only a receiver of scheduling information.  In other words, the application does not generate any messages, but receives notifications.</p></item></list><p>The following application roles are planned for future releases:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Slot Requester</emph> - In a tightly-coupled environment where applications share knowledge about slots, the requesting application can request booking by slots.  In this application role, a system can request a new appointment, modify an appointment, or request slot status changes.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Slot Request Responder</emph> - In this role, the owner of the schedule or an intermediary responds to a request to book an appointment by specific slots.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Slot Informer</emph> - In the role of Slot Notifier, the owner of the schedule or an intermediary sends out unsolicited notifications about changes in slot status information.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Slot Tracker</emph> - In this role, the application is receiviing unsolicited information about slots.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Requestor</emph> - In this role, the application requests a new appointment or modifications to an existing appointment from the request responder.  Usually, the request responder is the owner of the schedule.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Request Responder</emph> - The schedule owner or an intermediary responds to a request from another application.  For example, another application sends an appointment request and the request responder returns with a confirmed appointment or a denial.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Inquirer</emph> - In this role, the application makes inquires to the schedule owner application.  For example, it inquires for a list of all patients booked from 8 AM till 5 PM, for hearing examinations.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Query Responder</emph> - In this role,  the schedule owner or intermediary responds to a query submitted by an Appointment Inquirer role.  An example of the inquiry responder role is the case where an application requests a list of all booked slots for Dr. Miller and the Appointment Query Responder responds with that information.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Types of Interactions</emph></p><p>There are three basic types of interactions in the Scheduling domain:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Notifications</emph> are unsolicited messages from an Informer application notifying a Tracking application of changes in the owner's schedule.  In the case of notifications, the only obligation of the tracker is to acknowledge receipt of the message. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Requests/responses</emph> are the messages and trigger events used between requesting applications and the schedule owner.  The requesting application initiates a message requesting that the schedule owner modify its schedule with the given trigger event and information.  The schedule owner  responds to these requests to either grant or deny the request and to supply additional details about the confirmed request.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Queries/responses</emph> are the messages and trigger events used between querying applications and schedule owner applications.  Querying applications initiate the interaction by sending a query transaction.  The owner or an intermediary then responds to the query with the appropriate appointment ot slot information.</p></item></list><p>As mentioned above, this first release only supports Notifications for New, Revised, Cancelled, and Rescheduled Appointments..</p><p><emph role="strong">Relationship Between Order, Appointment and Encounter or Service</emph></p><p>An order is what begins the entire scheduling process.  An order may cause one or more requests for the booking of resources.  When the scheduling application receives the request(s), it creates the appointment by booking slot(s) in the schedule associated with the particular resource.  Now the appointment has been booked.</p><p>In an outpatient scenario, when the patient arrives for an appointment with the physician, the outpatient encounter starts and the appointment is complete.  If the patient does not arrive, the appointment is marked as a no show.  When the visit is complete, the encounter is completed.</p><p>In the case of an inpatient visit, where multiple services are required, when the patient arrives at the hospital, the inpatient encounter is started, but the encounter is not complete until all necessary services have been rendered and the patient is discharged from the hospital.</p><p>Procedures and observations, as well as other clinical and non-clinical activities may be controlled by a schedule.  In cases where the target of the scheduling process is a clinical activity, it may be preceded by an order or it may be part of a larger ordered service.  In either case, the order would precede the appointment request, which in turn, would precede the appointment.  When the service begins, the appointment is complete.</p><p><emph role="strong">Scheduling Status Codes Mapped to V3 Act Status Codes</emph></p><p>The prototypical status codes for Act.status_cd in the RIM may be interpreted as shown in the following tables:</p><p><emph role="strong">Appointment Status Code                            RIM Status Codes</emph></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td width="153">Complete</td><td width="183">Complete</td></tr><tr><td width="153">Delete</td><td width="183">Nullify</td></tr><tr><td width="153">Discontinue</td><td width="183">Abort</td></tr><tr><td width="153">Cancelled</td><td width="183">Abort</td></tr><tr><td width="153">Booked</td><td width="183">Active</td></tr><tr><td width="153">To Be Rescheduled</td><td width="183">Hold</td></tr><tr><td width="153">No Show</td><td width="183">Complete</td></tr></tbody></table><p>In V2, two additional status codes exist:  Pending and Waitlist. The corresponding V3 messages are not included in the scope of this publication, but will be included in a future V3 release.   The V2 'Pending' filler status code will be equivalent to the V3 Appointment Request status code of 'Active'.  The V2 Waitlist filler status code will be equivalent to the V3 Appointment Request status of 'Suspend'.</p></div2></div1><storydivn identifier="dlsbs-PRSC_DO000002UV" name="Storyboards" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="dlsbs-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic"><descriptive identifier="dstop-PRSC_DO000002UV" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="dstop-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="DOSC_ST000001UV01" name="Appointment Introduction" familiarName="Appointment Introduction" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="DOSC_ST000001UV01-str" sortPrefix="01|INTRODUCTION" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-03-13T01:02:42"><descriptive identifier="purp-DOSC_ST000001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="DOSC_ST000001UV01-str" id="purp-DOSC_ST000001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2005-03-13T01:02:42"><p>The Scheduling domain storyboards are structured according to the focus of the interaction:  Appointments or Resource Slots.  If the applications are tightly-coupled, they will want to synchronize schedules at the slot level, while more loosely-coupled applications will stay at the appointment level.</p><p>In this second release of Version 3, the Scheduling and Logistics TC is publishing Appointment Notifications and Slot Booking interactions.  More interactions, including Appointment Requests without slots and Queries are planned for subsequent releases.</p><p>Scheduling interactions assume there is one owner or manager of a schedule that knows the current status of an appointment or the availablity of a resource slot.  Depending on the focus of the message, this is either the <emph role="strong">Appointment Manager</emph> or the <emph role="strong">Slot Manager</emph>.  The Manager has sub-roles depending on the type of interaction.  For Notifications, the sub-role is <emph role="strong">Informer</emph>.  For Requests and Queries, the sub-roles are <emph role="strong">Request Responder</emph> and <emph role="strong">Query Responder</emph> respectively.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="DOSC_SN100002UV01" name="Appointment Notifications" familiarName="Appointment Notifications" parent="DOSC_ST000001UV01-str" id="DOSC_ST000001UV01-DOSC_SN100002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|INTRODUCTION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2004-12-06T02:38:12"><p>The scheduling process is not limited to any specific domain in healthcare, but applies to any situation where reservations for scarce resources have to be made in advance. All kinds of healthcare activities can be scheduled such as in- and outpatient encounters, procedures, observations, food and transportation services.</p><p>The storyboards in this domain illustrate several different scenarios for scheduling. The scenarios illustrated under the Appointment topic are typical loosely-coupled applications communicating for mutual benefit, but with a minimum of required responsibility.  In these scenarios, various systems may be interested in maintaining the status of a certain category of patient appointments. The appointment data may be used as auxiliary information within their database, or serve as input for their software process (external triggers).
</p><p>The scenario under the Slot topic is for a tightly-coupled cinfiguration where systems must maintain scheduling information in near-real time.  Schedules of slots are maintained in separate systems and synchronized through frequent communication.  Slots are requested for booking and the response must be timely.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="DOSC_ST000001UV01.gif"/></story></storydivn><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-PRSC_DO000002UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="dmims-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic"><dmim identifier="PRSC_DM000000UV" name="Scheduling Domain Model" familiarName="Scheduling Domain Model" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DM000000UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|SCHEDULING DOMAIN MODEL" lastEdit="2005-06-14T01:51:09"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_DM000000UV" name="Description" parent="PRSC_DM000000UV-rmi" id="desc-PRSC_DM000000UV-rmi" lastEdit="2005-06-14T01:51:09"><p>The Scheduling DMIM has a central focus on the ActAppointment class.  This class represents the activity being scheduled.  It has a mood of APT for Appointment and a class_code of ACT for any kind of Act.  This is a generic appointment and can be used for any sub-class of Act, including Encounters, Procedures, and Observations, among others.  An appointment can also be a battery where multiple services are scheduled as a group.  This is accomplished through the recursive act-relationship of an ActAppointment with itself.</p><p>This generic model represents the arguments of a Scheduling service.  In other words, if a specialization of Act in another domain wants to realize scheduling services, this abstract model describes the data needed to perform scheduling operations.  Another domain may also wish to associate domain-specific information with the appointment messages.  This can be accomplished by enhancing one of the Scheduling RMIMs and publishing those enhancements within the other domain.</p><p>ActAppointment is a booked appointment.  It may have been previously requested by a "placer application" in an ActAppointmentRequest. Additionally, the originating Order  may also be referenced from a booked appointment.  The difference between the ActOrder and the ActAppointmentRequest is that the order is authored by a healthcare practitioner and carries a professional  responsibility while the request is merely asking to reserve the resources.  Not all appointments are initiated by orders, as in the case of a patient-initiated request.  This chain of references is for identification purposes only and does not contain detailed information about the request or the order. </p><p>The subject (usually the patient) participates directly or indirectly in the appointment.  The cardinality is 1..* patients to allow for group appointments and the Participation.modeCode is included to allow for appointments where the patient is not physically present.  The subject Participation.time attribute allows the patient's appointment start time and duration to take place within the start time and duration for the whole appointment.  Both the subject and the performer participations have a modeCode attribute to indicate a physical or remote presence.</p><p>The performer, location, and reusable device participations associate the resources being reserved in this appointment.  These are practitioners and high-use items that are typically controlled by a schedule.  Each resource can have its own effective time interval or it can default to the time interval of the appointment.  The Participation.performInd is a boolean indicating that this participation is controlled by a schedule and must be reserved before use.  A participation that does not have this indicator set is not actively scheduled, i.e., for information purposes only.  Consumables can also be associated with the appointment.  The Supply Order allows for a quantity of consumables (i.e., manufactured material) to be specified either by name, id, or optionally, the manufacturer.  </p><p>The author is the person who originated the appointment and who must confirm changes or substitutions.  This participation is optional and should be a duplicate of the author participation in the Control Act wrapper for a new appointment.  For all other interactions, the author of the Control Act could be different from the author of the Appointment.  Of course, they could also be the same.</p><p>A Schedule is a set of slots associated with a resource and may be used here to designate which schedule(s) the appointment is occupying (for example, a physician's OR session schedule and his/her office schedule.  A Schedule may also be used for any time block which is further divided into slots.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="PRSC_DM000000UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Appointment Topic" familiarName="Appointment" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="01" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Introduction" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="intro-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" lastEdit="2004-08-09T07:43:32"><p>An Appointment is an agreement between participating resources and usually, but not necessarily, a patient to schedule intervals of time for some purpose.</p></descriptive><storydivn identifier="sbs-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Storyboards" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="sbs-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="sstop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="PRSC_ST000002UV01" name="Appointment Notification" familiarName="Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:21:47" class="changed"><descriptive identifier="purp-PRSC_ST000002UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="purp-PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:21:47"><p>This storyboard describes situations in which a scheduling system (<artref ref="PRSC_AR010100UV01" alt="Appointment Informer"></artref>) notifies interested parties (<artref ref="PRSC_AR020000UV01" alt="Appointment Trackers"></artref>) about planned appointments. The scheduling system maintains a set of schedules related to certain resources, managing the process of booking appointments.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PRSC_SN010002UV01" name="Appointment" familiarName="Physician Arranges For An Inpatient Stay" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-PRSC_SN010002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:22:39" class="changed"><p>Orthopedic surgeon Dr. Sara Specialize determines, during an initial outpatient assessment, that our patient Mr. Adam Everyman is a good candidate for a total hip replacement.</p><p>Dr. Specialize arranges for Mr. Everyman to be put on the wait list for orthopedic surgery in the Good Health Hospital. The expected duration for the inpatient stay will be 6 days. The operation is to be performed by Dr. Specialize herself, approximately two months from now. In the meantime, all the necessary administrative requirements (e.g. insurance authorization) and medical tests (pre-operation screening) can be arranged by the GHH for Mr. Everyman.</p><p>After authorization and screening have been OK-ed, the inpatient planner for the Good Health Hospital schedules a 6-day admission for Mr. Everyman, taking into account the availability of a hospital bed in the surgical care unit in combination with the required session time in Dr. Specialize's OR schedule on the second day of the admission. As a result of the scheduled admission the following actions are automatically triggered by the hospital information system of the Good Health Hospital (which handles inpatient scheduling)  <artref ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01" alt="Interaction: Appointment New Notification"></artref>:</p><p>A new entry is created in the GHH Electronic Patient Record for Mr. Everyman.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The<emph role="strong"> Electronic Patient Record</emph> provides a general view of all patient-related data to care providers within the Good Health Hospital, including specialists who use the system to prepare themselves for treating patients and to store their notes on a patient's medical history, evaluation and prognosis. Part of the patient record is an overview of all prior and planned admissions for a patient, as for outpatient encounters and other healthcare activities.</p></item></list><p>A request for his medical chart is sent to the central medical archive, which will deliver the chart on its regular delivery round 2 days prior to the scheduled visit. </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The central medical archive runs an <emph role="strong">Archive Management system</emph>, that uses planned admissions to provide 'pick lists' for delivering patient charts from the archive (or from temporary locations where the chart resides) to the appropriate department on time. The data for the scheduled inpatient stay is used to provide the necessary information for selecting the right chart (e.g. general inpatient chart) and knowing when and where it should be available.</p></item></list><p>The associated operation is placed in Dr. Specialize's OR session for day 2 of the stay.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>There is a close relationship between inpatient logistics and the <emph role="strong">OR Management system</emph>, at least for patients with a scheduled operation during their stay. The way planning for the care units and the operating rooms are coordinated may differ among hospitals, but when the inpatient stay is scheduled this usually results in a status change for the associated operation. This is placed in a specific OR session, for which ordering and planning may be refined later.</p></item></list><p>The hospital kitchen is informed of the dietary requirements for Mr. Everyman.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">Food Management system</emph> is tightly linked to inpatient logistics, to make sure that sufficient meals are available for inpatients and that dietary requirements are met. Therefore the scheduled admission might be communicated to the food management system in order to provide input for personnel planning and/or the ordering of ingredients. Note that the actual preparation of meals is usually bound to the eventual admission of the patient.</p></item></list></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PRSC_SN010003UV01" name="Appointment" familiarName="Patient Reschedules Outpatient Appointment" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-PRSC_SN010003UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:23:04" class="changed"><p>Mr. Adam Everyman has a conflict with the time that the new appointment was scheduled for the outpatient assessment of his right hip.  Mr. Everyman calls the office of Dr. Specialize to reschedule the appointment for the outpatient assessment. Dr. Specialize's assistant reschedules the 10-minute slot to another 10-minute slot on the same day as the previously booked appointment. The appointment is rescheduled in Dr. Specialize's schedule for one of the outpatient clinics associated with the Good Health Hospital. As a result of the rescheduled appointment the following actions are automatically triggered by the hospital information system of the Good Health Hospital (which contains the outpatient scheduling system for this schedule) <artref ref="PRSC_IN020201UV01" alt=" Interaction: Appointment Reschedule Notification"></artref>:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The time for the previously scheduled appointment is updated in the GHH Electronic Patient Record for Mr. Everyman for the rescheduled appointment.</p></item><item><p>The request for his medical chart sent to the central medical archive, will be updated with the rescheduled time. </p></item><item><p>The request for the recent orthopedic x-ray images sent to the radiology PACS, will be updated with the rescheduled time. </p></item><item><p>The rescheduled appointment is sent to the patient tracking system to update its schedules.</p></item></list></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PRSC_SN010004UV01" name="Appointment" familiarName="Patient Revises Outpatient Appointment" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-PRSC_SN010004UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:22:01" class="changed"><p>Mr. Everyman calls the office of Dr. Specialize to communicate the fact that he will be staying with his daughter until the scheduled appointment.  If they need to contact him, they should call his daughter.  Dr. Specialize's assistant revises the previously booked appointment with the new contact person's name and phone number. The appointment is revised in Dr. Specialize's schedule for the outpatient clinic where the appointment was booked. As a result of the revised appointment the following actions are automatically triggered by the hospital information system of the Good Health Hospital (which contains the outpatient scheduling system for this schedule) <artref ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01" alt=" Interaction: Appointment Revise Notification"></artref>:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The entry of the scheduled appointment is revised to update Mr. Everyman's daughter's phone number in the GHH Electronic Patient Record for Mr. Everyman.</p></item><item><p>The revised appointment is sent to the patient tracking system to update its schedules.</p></item></list></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PRSC_SN010005UV01" name="Appointment" familiarName="Physician Cancels Inpatient Stay for Patient" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-PRSC_SN010005UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:22:49" class="changed"><p>Mr. Everyman calls the office of Dr. Specialize to report that his pain is much less and he would like to postpone the surgery.  Dr. Specialize examines Mr. Everyman (after a suitably scheduled out-patient appointment) and agrees that he does not need surgery at this time.  Her assistant calls GHH to cancel the previously booked inpatient encounter appointment.  As a result of the canceled appointment, the hospital information system of the Good Health Hospital notifies all interested parties of the current status.<artref ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01" alt=" Trigger Event Appointment Cancel Notification"></artref>.  Each receiver then triggers internal processes to perform the following actions:
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The entry of the scheduled appointment is canceled in Dr. Specialize's OR session schedule.</p></item><item><p>The medical chart archives cancel the request for Mr. Everyman's medical chart. </p></item><item><p>The radiology PACS cancels the request of Mr. Everyman's recent orthopedic x-ray images. </p></item><item><p>The patient tracking system updates its schedules.
</p></item></list></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PRSC_SN010101UV01" name="Appointment" familiarName="Patient Makes Outpatient Appointment" parent="PRSC_ST000002UV01-str" id="PRSC_ST000002UV01-PRSC_SN010101UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="01|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Appointment" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:22:20" class="changed"><p>Mr. Adam Everyman, suffering from severe chronic pain in his right hip, was not relieved by the anti-inflammatory medication prescribed by his primary care provider, Dr. Primary.</p><p>Dr. Primary decided to refer Mr. Everyman to an orthopedic surgeon, Dr. Sara Specialize, for evaluation. Mr. Everyman calls the office of Dr. Specialize to schedule an appointment for an outpatient assessment. Dr. Specialize's assistant books a 10-minute slot for a first visit in about four weeks. The appointment is booked in Dr. Specialize's schedule for one of the outpatient clinics associated with the Good Health Hospital. </p><p>As a result of the appointment the following actions are automatically triggered by the hospital information system of the Good Health Hospital (which contains the outpatient scheduling system for this schedule) <artref ref="PRSC_SN010101UV01" alt="Interaction: Appointment New Notification"></artref>: </p><p>A new entry is created in the GHH Electronic Patient Record for Mr. Everyman.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The <emph role="strong">Electronic Patient Record</emph> provides a general view of all patient-related data to care providers within the Good Health Hospital, including specialists who use the system to prepare themselves for treating patients and to store their notes on a patient's medical history, evaluation and prognosis. Part of the patient record is an overview of all past and future appointments that a patient has, both for encounters and other healthcare activities. </p></item></list><p>A request for his medical chart is sent to the central medical archive, which will deliver the chart on its regular delivery round 2 days prior to the scheduled visit. </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The central medical archive runs an <emph role="strong">Archive Management system</emph>, that uses planned appointments to provide 'pick lists' for delivering patient charts from the archive (or from temporary locations where the chart resides) to the appropriate department on time. The appointment data is used to provide the necessary information for selecting the right chart (e.g. specialty-based outpatient chart) and knowing when and where it should be available.</p></item></list><p>A request for recent orthopedic x-ray images is sent to the radiology <emph role="strong">Picture Archival and Communication System</emph> (PACS), which will pre-fetch the image files (from optic media) 2 days prior to the scheduled visit. </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The radiology department in the Good Health Hospital runs a digital imaging system, which has an image database managed by a PACS. The images on the PACS have a relatively long retrieval time, but can be pre-fetched for fast access by a specialist that wants to inspect them before or during a patient encounter. The appointment data is used to select the appropriate images and make them available on time.</p></item></list><p>The appointment is sent to the patient tracking system to update its schedules.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>A <emph role="strong">Patient Tracking system</emph> maintains copies of certain schedules to serve as a basis for providing routing information to patients and monitoring their status during visits. These systems often have displays in the entrance hall and the waiting rooms to provide patients information. Also, by relating scheduled and actual encounter times, they generate important statistical information about the service level of the outpatient logistics of the hospital.</p></item></list></descriptive><diagref ref="PRSC_ST000002UV01.gif"/><intref ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01" sequence="1"/><intref ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01" sequence="3"/><intref ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01" sequence="4"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Application Roles" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="roles-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="arop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Appointment Informer" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR010100UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Tracker" refFamiliarName="Appointment Tracker" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR020000UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="PRSC_AR010100UV01" name="Appointment Intent Informer" familiarName="Appointment Informer" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" sortPrefix="01|15|99|25|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2005-06-13T01:39:01"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_AR010100UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" id="desc-PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" lastEdit="2005-06-13T01:39:01"><p>In this role, the application notifies a tracking system that an appointment has been booked or modified in some way.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01"/><intref role="sends" ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01"/><intref role="sends" ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="PRSC_AR020000UV01" name="Appointment Intent Tracker" familiarName="Appointment Tracker" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" sortPrefix="01|15|99|30|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2005-06-13T01:40:57"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_AR020000UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" id="desc-PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" lastEdit="2005-06-13T01:40:57"><p>In this role the application is only a receiver of scheduling information.  In other words, the application does not generate any messages, but receives notifications.</p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Trigger Events" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="tes-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="teop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="PRSC_TE010100UV01" name="Appointment Intent New Notification" familiarName="New Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_TE010100UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="01|15|05||05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:26:50"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_TE010100UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_TE010100UV01-te" id="desc-PRSC_TE010100UV01-te" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:26:50"><p>The Appointment Informer sends the Appointment Tracker  a notification that a new appointment has been scheduled.  This trigger event maps to the V2 S12 trigger event, Notification of New Appointment Booking.</p></descriptive><statrans transitionFQN="Null to Active" focalClass="ActAppointment"><rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01"/></statrans><intref role="fires" ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="PRSC_TE020100UV01" name="Appointment Intent Cancel Notification" familiarName="Appointment Cancel Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_TE020100UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="01|15|10||05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:27:03"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_TE020100UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_TE020100UV01-te" id="desc-PRSC_TE020100UV01-te" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:27:03"><p>The Appointment Informer sends the Appointment Tracker a notification that an appointment has been cancelled.  This trigger event maps to the V2 S15 trigger event, Notification of Appointment Cancellation.</p></descriptive><statrans transitionFQN="Active to Aborted" focalClass="ActAppointment"><rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01"/></statrans><intref role="fires" ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="PRSC_TE020200UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule Notification" familiarName="Appointment Reschedule Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_TE020200UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="01|15|22|RESCHEDULE|05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:29:43"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_TE020200UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_TE020200UV01-te" id="desc-PRSC_TE020200UV01-te" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:29:43"><p>The Appointment Informer sends the Appointment Tracker  a notification that the appointment has been rescheduled.  This trigger event maps to the V2 S13 trigger event, Notification of Appointment Rescheduling.</p></descriptive><statrans transitionFQN="Active to Active" focalClass="ActAppointment"><rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01"/></statrans><intref role="fires" ref="PRSC_IN020201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification Reschedule" refFamiliarName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020201UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="PRSC_TE010200UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" familiarName="Appointment Revise Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_TE010200UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="01|15|22||05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:27:10"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_TE010200UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_TE010200UV01-te" id="desc-PRSC_TE010200UV01-te" lastEdit="2004-12-05T18:27:10"><p>The Appointment Informer sends the Appointment Tracker a notification that the appointment has been revised.  This trigger event maps to the V2 S14 trigger event, Notification of Appointment Modification.</p></descriptive><statrans transitionFQN="Active to Active" focalClass="ActAppointment"><rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01"/></statrans><intref role="fires" ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="rmims-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="rmop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01" name="Appointment Intent Full" familiarName="Full Appointment RMIM" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="01|15|99|FULL" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-06-14T02:04:32"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_RM010000UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" id="desc-PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2005-06-14T02:04:32"><p>The Appointment Full RMIM is the complete Appointment model.  It includes all the attributes and associations that can be specified when a new appointment is booked.  Similarly, when an existing appointment is revised, all these fields can be changed.  Therefore, the same RMIM generates both the Appointment New and the Appointment Revise HMDs.</p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_DM000000UV-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Scheduling Domain Model" refFamiliarName="Scheduling Domain Model" refIdentifier="PRSC_DO000002UV"/><diagref ref="PRSC_RM010000UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New" refFamiliarName="New Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010100UV01"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010200UV01"/></rmim><rmim identifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01" name="Appointment Intent Minimum" familiarName="Minimum Appointment RMIM" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="01|15|99|MINIMUM" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:31:32"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_RM020000UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" id="desc-PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:31:32"><p>The Appointment Minimum RMIM is used to create very simple status change types of messages where only the id, status, and time are needed.  The effective_time attribute is present to allow this RMIM to also be used for rescheduling an appointment.  The Control Act wrapper contains the reason observation that is used to transmit the reason for the status change or rescheduling action.</p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_DM000000UV-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Scheduling Domain Model" refFamiliarName="Scheduling Domain Model" refIdentifier="PRSC_DO000002UV"/><diagref ref="PRSC_RM020000UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Cancel" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020100UV01"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PRSC_HD020200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule" refFamiliarName="Reschedule Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020200UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="hmds-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="hdop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="PRSC_HD010100UV01" name="Appointment Intent New" familiarName="New Appointment" parent="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" id="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|15|05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:25:19"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_HD010100UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" id="desc-PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:25:19"><p>Attributes included in a new appointment booking notification.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_HD010100UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Full" refFamiliarName="Full Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PRSC_MT010101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010101UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="PRSC_HD020100UV01" name="Appointment Intent Cancel" familiarName="Cancel Appointment" parent="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" id="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|15|10|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:32:34"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_HD020100UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" id="desc-PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:32:34"><p>Attributes included in a cancelled appointment notification.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_HD020100UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Minimum" refFamiliarName="Minimum Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PRSC_MT020101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020101UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="PRSC_HD010200UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise" familiarName="Revise Appointment" parent="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" id="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|15|22|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:27:47"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_HD010200UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" id="desc-PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:27:47"><p>Attributes included in a modified appointment notification.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_HD010200UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_RM010000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Full" refFamiliarName="Full Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM010000UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PRSC_MT010201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Full" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010201UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="PRSC_HD020200UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule" familiarName="Reschedule Appointment" parent="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" id="PRSC_HD020200UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="01|15|22|RESCHEDULE|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-06-14T02:40:23"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_HD020200UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PRSC_RM020000UV01-rmi" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Minimum" refFamiliarName="Minimum Appointment RMIM" refIdentifier="PRSC_RM020000UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PRSC_MT020201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule" refFamiliarName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020201UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="msgs-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><msgtype identifier="PRSC_MT010101UV01" name="Appointment Intent New Notification" familiarName="New Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" id="PRSC_MT010101UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|15|05|NOTIFICATION|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-07T00:21:18"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_MT010101UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PRSC_HD010100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New" refFamiliarName="New Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010100UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="PRSC_MT010201UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Full" familiarName="Revise Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" id="PRSC_MT010201UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|15|22|FULL|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:29:32"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_MT010201UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PRSC_HD010200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD010200UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="PRSC_MT020201UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule" familiarName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_HD020200UV01-hmd" id="PRSC_MT020201UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|15|22|RESCHEDULE|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-06-14T02:42:23"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_MT020201UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PRSC_HD020200UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule" refFamiliarName="Reschedule Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020200UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PRSC_IN020201UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification Reschedule" refFamiliarName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020201UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="PRSC_MT020101UV01" name="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" familiarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" id="PRSC_MT020101UV01-msg" sortPrefix="01|15|35|NOTIFICATION|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-12-07T00:36:39"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PRSC_MT020101UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PRSC_HD020100UV01-hmd" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Cancel" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment" refIdentifier="PRSC_HD020100UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" refFamiliarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Interactions" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="ints-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment" name="Reference" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="inop-PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="PRSC_IN010101UV01" name="Appointment Intent New Notification" familiarName="New Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="01|15|05|05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-06-13T23:30:56"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_IN010101UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" id="desc-PRSC_IN010101UV01-int" lastEdit="2005-06-13T23:30:56"><p>An unsolicited message from a Scheduling application giving the particulars about a new appointment booking</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Appointment Informer" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR010100UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Tracker" refFamiliarName="Appointment Tracker" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR020000UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PRSC_TE010100UV01-te" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent New Notification" refFamiliarName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_TE010100UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PRSC_MT010101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="New Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010101UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="PRSC_IN010201UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" familiarName="Revise Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="01|15|22|05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:44:57"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_IN010201UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" id="desc-PRSC_IN010201UV01-int" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:44:57"><p>An unsolicited message from a Scheduling application giving new information about a revised appointment booking.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Appointment Informer" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR010100UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Tracker" refFamiliarName="Appointment Tracker" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR020000UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PRSC_TE010200UV01-te" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Appointment Revise Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_TE010200UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PRSC_MT010201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Revise Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT010201UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="PRSC_IN020201UV01" name="Appointment Intent Revise Notification Reschedule" familiarName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_IN020201UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="01|15|22|05|RESCHEDULE|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2005-06-14T03:01:48"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_IN020201UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_IN020201UV01-int" id="desc-PRSC_IN020201UV01-int" lastEdit="2005-06-14T03:01:48"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PRSC_TE020200UV01-te" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Revise Reschedule Notification" refFamiliarName="Appointment Reschedule Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_TE020200UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PRSC_MT020201UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Reschedule Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020201UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="PRSC_IN020101UV01" name="Appointment Intent Abort Notification" familiarName="Cancel Appointment Notification" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-Appointment-ic" id="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="01|15|35|05|" baseClass="Appointment" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:45:28"><descriptive identifier="desc-PRSC_IN020101UV01" name="Description" parent="PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" id="desc-PRSC_IN020101UV01-int" lastEdit="2004-08-12T23:45:28"><p>An unsolicited message from a Scheduling application giving the particulars about a canceled appointment booking.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PRSC_AR010100UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Appointment Informer" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR010100UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PRSC_AR020000UV01-ar" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Tracker" refFamiliarName="Appointment Tracker" refIdentifier="PRSC_AR020000UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PRSC_TE020100UV01-te" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Appointment Intent Cancel Notification" refFamiliarName="Appointment Cancel Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_TE020100UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PRSC_MT020101UV01-msg" sectID="amprsc" sectType="SB" refName="Cancel Appointment Notification" refIdentifier="PRSC_MT020101UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-PRSC_DO000002UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="cindx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-PRSC_DO000002UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="indx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-PRSC_DO000002UV-ic" id="PRSC_DO000002UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

