<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="POSP_DO000000UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPOSP" lastEdit="6/5/2008 5:32:09 PM" rendered="6/5/2008 5:32:53 PM"><header><title>Domain: Specimen Domain</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="InformativeStandard" number="1"/><date>6/5/2008</date><authlist><author><role>Laboratory SIG Co-chair</role><name key="1">Austin Kreisler</name><affiliation>SAIC</affiliation></author><author><role>Laboratory SIG Co-chair</role><name key="2">Ken McCaslin</name><affiliation>Quest Diagnostics Incorporated</affiliation></author><author><role>Laboratory SIG Co-chair</role><name key="3">Craig Robinson</name><affiliation>Siemens Medical Solutions Health Services</affiliation></author><author><role>Laboratory SIG Modeling Facilitator</role><name key="4">Sarah Glamm</name><affiliation>Epic Systems Corporation</affiliation></author><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key="5">Jeff Sutherland</name><affiliation>PatientKeeper, Inc.</affiliation></author><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key="6">Hans Buitendijk</name><affiliation>Siemens Medical Solutions Health Services</affiliation></author><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key="6">Gunther Schadow, M.D., PhD.</name><affiliation>Regenstrief Institute for Health Care</affiliation></author><author><role>Editor</role><name key="7">Sarah Glamm</name><affiliation>Epic Systems Corporation</affiliation></author><author><role>Editor</role><name key="8">Ken McCaslin</name><affiliation>Quest Diagnostics Incorporated</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="spec-preface"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p><emph role="strong">Specimen Domain Notes to Reader</emph></p><p>This is an informative document defining the Specimen Domain.  This is a new domain previously balloted within the laboratory domain.  It became an Informative HL7 Document in September, 2005. In this release this domain has no messages or interactions of its own. However, there will certainly be CMET's and potentially other messages created in this domain in the future.</p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"/></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" ballotStatus="InformativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-04-20T15:51:28"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p><emph role="strong">Specimen Domain </emph></p><p>The Specimen Domain comprises the models and artifacts that are needed to support the creation of messaging related to specimen.  This provides the requirements needed to understand all aspects of the specimen, the subject the specimen was derived from, and the characteristics of the container and contents within before, during, and/or after the specimen was placed within it.  This will create CMETs for the management of specimen.</p><p>It is important to note the domain supports the notion of living person, non-person living subject, natural substance as well as a manufactured specimen.  Further specializations support the definition of the specimen becoming the whole person (as in an autopsy), a derived single specimen from an entire herd, or single specimen from an entity.  Many identifiers and timing parameters are provided for the full reference and identification of the specimen.   </p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-POSP_DO000000UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="dmims-POSP_DO000000UV-ic"><dmim identifier="POSP_DM000000UV" name="Specimen" familiarName="Specimen" parent="POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DM000000UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|SPECIMEN" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:32:09"><descriptive identifier="desc-POSP_DM000000UV" name="Description" parent="POSP_DM000000UV-rmi" id="desc-POSP_DM000000UV-rmi" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:32:09"><p><emph role="strong">Specimen D-MIM Walk Through</emph></p><a name="POSP_ANCH-Beginning"></a><p><emph>Overview</emph></p><p>The Specimen Domain Information Model (D-MIM) captures information regarding a specimen and its container. Both the specimen and the source of the specimen are scoped by a specimenEntity which may be located in a container. The specimen itself may be the result of a process and can be acted on by any number of processes in order to handle both the specimen and the container.</p><p><graphic alt="Simplified Specimen Domain" source="POSP_NA000001.gif"></graphic></p><p><emph>Description: </emph>A substance, extracted from a person, non-person living thing, or environmental site which is tested in order to make an observation. It is often a small sample or part taken to show the nature of the whole. The Specimen role is structured as follows: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph>Specimen:</emph> The specimen as a role. Examples include specimen, aliquot, isolate, etc.   </p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph>Participations:</emph> Specimen includes the following participations:</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph>productOf:</emph> The specimen role is a product of a specimen collection process. This captures information regarding any procedure to produce the specimen. For example, this would document a biopsy performed to obtain tissue needed for laboratory testing.
							<p><xspecref spec="UVSP" alt="Attributes of Process" ref="POSP_ANCH-PROCESS_TABLE"></xspecref></p><list role="unordered"><item><emph>precondition: </emph>The process to collect the specimen may have any number of Criterion Observations as a precondition, such as fasting before a glucose tolerance test.<p><xspecref alt="Attributes of Criterion" ref="POSP_ANCH-CRITERION_TABLE" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item><item><emph>performer:</emph>An R_AssignedEntity [universal] CMET captures information regarding the performer of the specimen collection.</item></list></item><item><emph>subjectOf1:</emph> A specimen can be the subject of any number of observations to record information about the state of the specimen in a human readible format such as temperature and dilution. A constraint has been placed on the datatype of the value attribute that is dependent on the type of observation that is being performed. For instance, if the dilution of the specimen is being recorded the value attribute must be a ratio or a coded value.<p><xspecref alt="Attributes of SpecimenObservationEvent" ref="POSP_ANCH-SPECOBSERVATION_TABLE" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item><item><emph>subjectOf2:</emph> The specimen or its container may be the subject of any number of ProcessStep Acts. This is defined as any process that can act on a specimen or its container such as specimen accession, specimen treatment or container registration. The inclusion of this observation is intended to illustrate that an observation has taken place but not the value or the outcome of that observation. For instance, when Cold Agglutinins are discovered in the specimen during the processing of a CBC test the specimen is placed in a 37 degree wash for two hours. This observation would record that this was had been performed.<p><xspecref alt="Attributes of ProcessStep" ref="POSP_ANCH-PROCSTEP_TABLE" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p><list role="unordered"><item><emph>authorOrPerformer:</emph> Zero to many R_AssignedEntity [universal] CMETs to capture information regarding the author or performer of the process step. In the above example this would identify the medical technician that performed the wash of the specimen.</item><item><emph>subject: </emph>IdentifiedEntity2 defines the identifiers for a holder that is the subject of the ProcessStep, such as during container registration.</item><item><emph>subject1: </emph>IdentifiedEntity defines the identifiers for a container that is the subject of ProcessStep.</item></list></item></list></item><item><p><emph>sourceEntity(scoping entity): </emph>The Specimen role is scoped by specimenEntities which is a choice of entities. These entities represent the possible sources of the specimen:   </p><list role="unordered"><item><emph>Natural:</emph> A generic entity which can be anything, for example a parent specimen can be the source of a specimen. 
							<p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-NATURAL_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Natural Entity" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item><item><p><emph>Manufactured: </emph>The source of a specimen can be a manufactured material</p><p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-MATERIAL_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Manufactured Material" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph>ManufacturedProduct:</emph> a role scoped by the E_organization [universal] CMET capturing information regarding the source of the manufactured material.</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph>NonPersonLivingSubject:</emph>The specimen may be from a living subject of some sort that is not human.  For example an isolate or animal subject.</p><p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-NONPERSON_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Non-Person Living Subject" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item><item><p><emph>Person:</emph> The specimen may be from a human subject.  In the case of specimens from a patient, this is the identifier for the patient that the specimen was taken from.   </p><p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-PERSON_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Person Subject" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item></list></item><item><emph>specimenEntity(playing entity): </emph>The specimen role is played by specimenEntities which is a choice of entities. It's the same four entities defined above but the meanings are slightly different.<list role="unordered"><item><emph>Natural:</emph> The specimen is defined as some natural substance, such as blood, urine, water or soil. </item><item><emph>Manufactured:</emph> The specimen is defined as a manufactured product which may be used to perform QC or QA. </item><item><emph>NonPersonLivingSubject:</emph> The specimen may be an entire non-human subject such as an animal or an isolate.</item><item><emph>Person:</emph> A whole human being such as in the case of an autopsy. </item></list></item><item><emph>specimenEntities: </emph>This is a choice of entities that can either be the source of specimens or the specimens themselves. This choice of entities can scope an additive role, as well as play the role of content for a container. <list role="unordered"><item><emph>SpecimenStub:</emph> if the specimen source itself is a parent specimen, the specimen stub identifies the source specimen of the parent specimen.<list role="unordered"><item><emph>SpecimenAlternateIdentifier: </emph>This role provides storage for non-specimen identifiers,  such as patient MRNs.  This role is scoped by the E_Organization [universal] CMET.</item></list></item><item><emph>additive:</emph> Additive mixed into the specimen, e.g., in an aliquot of citrate blood. <p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-ADDITIVE_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Additive" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p></item><item><emph>containedEntity(played): </emph>The specimenEntities play the role of content for a container. <list role="unordered"><item><emph>Content1:</emph> The container for the specimen. Scoped by a Container entity. <list role="unordered"><item><emph>Container:</emph> The container entity contains the specimen and may also itself be the content of a holder, such as a vial containing a specimen that is placed in a carrier.
											<p><xspecref ref="POSP_ANCH-CONTAINER_TABLE" alt="Attributes of Container" spec="UVSP"></xspecref></p><list role="unordered"><item><emph>Additive2:</emph> Additive in container, e.g., a blood specimen tube with EDTA or citrate in it. Content2 role is played by an AdditiveMaterial (MAT) entity to identify the material being added to the specimen, which in turn plays the role of Additive</item><item><emph>Content3: </emph>Container in holder, e.g., a specimen container in a carrier. Content3 is scoped by Holder (an entity).</item><item><emph>R_LocationLocatedEntity [universal] CMET: </emph>The location of a container.</item><item><emph>IdentifiedEntity:</emph> The identifier for the container.</item></list></item></list><list role="unordered"><item><emph>Holder:</emph> Entity which contains either a container or another holder. Scopes and plays the role of Content4 (holder in a holder, e.g, a carrier on a tray). <list role="unordered"><item><emph>R_LocationLocatedEntity [universal] CMET: </emph> This identifies the location of the holder or the container. Also plays the role of identifiedEntity. The identifiedEntity may be the subject of a ContainerRegistration. </item></list></item></list></item></list></item></list></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Natural Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-NATURAL_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>ENT</td><td>Signifies that a specimen can be virtually anything</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>One specific occurrence of anything</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>EntityCode</td><td>Serum, soil, water, or any natural substance</td></tr><tr><td>riskCode</td><td>EntityRisk</td><td>Identifies any risk associated with the specimen or handling the specimen such as an infectious agent.</td></tr><tr><td>handlingCode</td><td>EntityHandling</td><td>Ways to handle a specimen.  For example, protect from air or keep frozen.</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Manufactured Material Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-MATERIAL_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>MMAT</td><td>A manufactured material</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>Single occurrence of a manufactured material</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>EntityCode</td><td>Quality Control serum or unknown medication</td></tr><tr><td>quantity</td><td></td><td>The amount of the material</td></tr><tr><td>desc</td><td></td><td>Free text attribute to describe the manufactured material</td></tr><tr><td>riskCode</td><td>EntityRisk</td><td>Identifies any risk associated with the specimen or handling the specimen such as a radioactive material.</td></tr><tr><td>handlingCode</td><td>EntityHandling</td><td>Ways to handle a specimen.  For example, protect from air or keep frozen.</td></tr><tr><td>lotNumberText</td><td></td><td>Free text attribute identifying the material's lot number</td></tr><tr><td>expirationTime</td><td></td><td>Interval Time Stamp describing the expiration date and time of the material</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Non-Person Living Subject Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-NONPERSON_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>NLIV</td><td>Non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>Single occurrence of a non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>EntityCode</td><td>Any entity such as a dog, a tick, or mold</td></tr><tr><td>quantity</td><td></td><td>The amount of the material</td></tr><tr><td>name</td><td></td><td>Free text attribute naming the non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>desc</td><td></td><td>Free text attribute describing the non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>statusCode</td><td>EntityStatus</td><td>Codes describing the states of a non-person living subject.  Codes include normal, active, terminated or nullified.</td></tr><tr><td>existenceTime</td><td></td><td>The interval of time specifying period in which the non-person living subject existed</td></tr><tr><td>telecom</td><td></td><td>Telecommunication address</td></tr><tr><td>riskCode</td><td>EntityRisk</td><td>Identifies any risk associated with the specimen or handling the specimen such as a dangerous animal.</td></tr><tr><td>handlingCode</td><td>EntityHandling</td><td>Ways to handle a specimen.  For example, keep contained or protect from light</td></tr><tr><td>administrativeGenderCode</td><td>AdministrativeGender</td><td>The gender of the non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>birthTime</td><td></td><td>Birth date</td></tr><tr><td>deceasedInd</td><td></td><td>Whether or not the non-person living subject is deceased</td></tr><tr><td>deceasedTime</td><td></td><td>Date and time the non-person living subject became deceased</td></tr><tr><td>multipleBirthInd</td><td></td><td>Whether or not the non-person living subject is part of a multiple birth</td></tr><tr><td>multipleBirthOrderNumber</td><td></td><td>The order in which the non-person living subject was born</td></tr><tr><td>organDonorInd</td><td></td><td>Indication that the non-person living subject is available to be an organ donor</td></tr><tr><td>strainText</td><td></td><td>A text string indicating the genotype or phenotype of the non-person living subject</td></tr><tr><td>genderStatusCode</td><td>GenderStatus</td><td>Indication of the presence of reproductive organs</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Person Subject Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-PERSON_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>PSN</td><td>A human beings</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>An occurrence of a person</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>EntityCode</td><td>homo sapiens</td></tr><tr><td>quantity</td><td></td><td>one</td></tr><tr><td>name</td><td></td><td>Name of the person</td></tr><tr><td>desc</td><td></td><td>Description of the person</td></tr><tr><td>statusCode</td><td>EntityStatus</td><td>Codes describing the states of a non-person living subject.  Codes include normal, active, terminated or nullified.</td></tr><tr><td>existenceTime</td><td></td><td>The interval of time specifying period in which the person existed</td></tr><tr><td>telecom</td><td></td><td>Telecommunication address</td></tr><tr><td>riskCode</td><td>EntityRisk</td><td>Risk associated with handling the person such as disposition or infection</td></tr><tr><td>handlingCode</td><td>EntityHandling</td><td>Ways to handle a human body.  For example, handicapped provisions.</td></tr><tr><td>administrativeGenderCode</td><td>AdministrativeGender</td><td>The gender of a person used for administrative purposes (as opposed to clinical gender)  </td></tr><tr><td>birthTime</td><td></td><td>Birth date</td></tr><tr><td>deceasedInd</td><td></td><td>Whether or the person is deceased</td></tr><tr><td>deceasedTime</td><td></td><td>Date and time the person became deceased</td></tr><tr><td>multipleBirthInd</td><td></td><td>Whether or not the person is part of a multiple birth</td></tr><tr><td>multipleBirthOrderNumber</td><td></td><td>The order in which the person was born as part of a multiple birth.</td></tr><tr><td>organDonorInd</td><td></td><td>Indication that the person is able to be an organ donor</td></tr><tr><td>addr</td><td></td><td>Person's address</td></tr><tr><td>disabilityCode</td><td>PersonDisabilityType</td><td>Indicates any current disabilities for the person</td></tr><tr><td>raceCode</td><td>Race</td><td>The race of the person</td></tr><tr><td>ethnicGroupCode</td><td>Ethnicity</td><td>The ethnic group of the person</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Additive Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-ADDITIVE_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>MAT</td><td>An additive</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>An occurrence of the additive</td></tr><tr><td>id</td><td></td><td>The id of the additive</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>MaterialEntityAdditive</td><td>The code of the additive, such EDTA or Citrate</td></tr><tr><td>desc</td><td></td><td>A free text description of the additive</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Container Entity Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-CONTAINER_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>CONT</td><td>The container</td></tr><tr><td>determinerCode</td><td>INSTANCE</td><td>An occurrence of a container</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>EntityCode</td><td>The type of container</td></tr><tr><td>desc</td><td></td><td>A free text description of the container</td></tr><tr><td>riskCode</td><td>EntityRisk</td><td>Risk associated with the container or material contained in the container</td></tr><tr><td>handlingCode</td><td>EntityHandling</td><td>Ways to handle the container, such as frozen or room temperature</td></tr><tr><td>capacityQuantity</td><td></td><td>The capacity of the container</td></tr><tr><td>heightQuantity</td><td></td><td>The height of the container</td></tr><tr><td>diameterQuantity</td><td></td><td>The diameter of the container</td></tr><tr><td>capTypeCode</td><td>ContainerCap</td><td>The code indicating the type of cap used on the container</td></tr><tr><td>separatorTypeCode</td><td>ContainerSeparator</td><td>The code indicating the type of separator used in the container</td></tr><tr><td>barrierDeltaQuantity</td><td></td><td>The difference between the top of the tube and the top of the tube container</td></tr><tr><td>bottomDeltaQuantity</td><td></td><td>The difference between the bottom of the tube and the bottom of the tube container</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">Process Act Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-PROCESS_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>PROC</td><td>A process that acts on a specimen</td></tr><tr><td>moodCode</td><td>x_ActMoodIntentEvent</td><td>The intention or plan to perform a service</td></tr><tr><td>id</td><td></td><td>The id of the observation</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td></td><td>The type of process used to retrieve a specimen</td></tr><tr><td>text</td><td></td><td>The free text describing the process</td></tr><tr><td>statusCode</td><td>ActStatus</td><td>The status of the process such as aborted, cancelled or completed</td></tr><tr><td>effectiveTime</td><td></td><td>The time specimen was collected</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">ObservationEvent (Criterion) Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-CRITERION_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>OBS</td><td>An observation</td></tr><tr><td>moodCode</td><td>EVN.CRT</td><td>An event criterion for the specimen collection process</td></tr><tr><td>id</td><td></td><td>The id of the observation</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>ActCode</td><td>A particular type of an Act that is a precondition observation for the process that creates the specimen, such as fasting</td></tr><tr><td>text</td><td></td><td>A free text description of the the observation</td></tr><tr><td>value</td><td></td><td>The resulting value of the observation such as length of time</td></tr><tr><td>interpretationCode</td><td>ObservationInterpretation</td><td>The interpretation of the observation value</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">SpecimenObservationEvent Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-SPECOBSERVATION_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>SPCOBS</td><td>A specimen observation</td></tr><tr><td>moodCode</td><td>EVN</td><td>An event</td></tr><tr><td>id</td><td></td><td>The id of the specimen observation</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>ActSpecObsCode</td><td>Identifies the type of observation that is made about a specimen that may affect its processing, analysis or further result interpretation, such as a hemolyzed serum sample for potassium analysis</td></tr><tr><td>text</td><td></td><td>A free text description of the the observation, such as serum hemolyzed</td></tr><tr><td>statusCode</td><td>ActStatus</td><td>The status of the specimen observation such as aborted, cancelled or completed</td></tr><tr><td>effectiveTime</td><td></td><td>The time the specimen observation took place</td></tr><tr><td>value</td><td></td><td>The value of the specimen observation such as dilution, volume or temperature</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">ProcessStep Attributes</emph><a name="POSP_ANCH-PROCSTEP_TABLE"></a></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Attribute</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Vocabulary</emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description</emph></td></tr><tr><td>classCode</td><td>x_LabProcessClassCodes</td><td>The type of process that is currently acting on the specimen or container, such as container registration or specimen accession.</td></tr><tr><td>moodCode</td><td>EVN</td><td>The act is an event</td></tr><tr><td>id</td><td></td><td>The id of the process</td></tr><tr><td>code</td><td>x_LabProcessCodes</td><td>The Code for the current process that is acting on the specimen or container, such as container registration procedure.</td></tr><tr><td>text</td><td></td><td>The free text describing the process</td></tr><tr><td>statusCode</td><td>ActStatus</td><td>The status of the procedure such as aborted, cancelled or completed</td></tr><tr><td>effectiveTime</td><td></td><td>The time the process is effective</td></tr></tbody></table><indent></indent></descriptive><diagref ref="POSP_DM000000UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-POSP_DO000000UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="cindx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DO000000UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DO000000UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-POSP_DO000000UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="indx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DO000000UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DO000000UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-POSP_DO000000UV-ic" id="POSP_DO000000UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

