<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPOTD" lastEdit="6/4/2008 10:51:25 AM" rendered="6/4/2008 10:51:44 AM"><header><title>Domain: Therapeutic Devices</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="2"/><date>6/4/2008</date><authlist><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key=" Buitendijk, Hans">Hans Buitendijk</name><affiliation>Siemens Medical Solutions Health Services</affiliation></author><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key=" Schadow, Gunther">Gunther Schadow, M.D., PhD.</name><affiliation>Regenstrief Institute for Health Care</affiliation></author><author><role>Orders &amp; Observations Co-Chair</role><name key=" Sutherland, Jeff">Jeff Sutherland</name><affiliation>PatientKeeper, Inc.</affiliation></author><author><role>Implantable Device - Cardiac (IDC) Project Manager</role><name key="Baird, Doug">Doug Baird</name><affiliation>Guidant</affiliation></author><author><role>Implantable Device - Cardiac (IDC) Project Leader</role><name key="Halvorson, Linda">Linda Halvorson</name><affiliation>Guidant</affiliation></author><author><role>Content Contributor</role><name key="Marotz, David">David Marotz</name><affiliation>Accenture</affiliation></author><author><role>Content Contributor</role><name key="Palmer, Pete">Pete Palmer</name></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2008" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.6" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="spec-preface"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p><emph role="strong">Therapeutic Devices Domain Notes to Reader</emph></p><p>The contents of this domain have been created by the "Implantable Device - Cardiac" Project. The current focus has been on messaging surrounding implantable cardiac devices, including pacemakers, implantable cardioverter defibrillators (ICDs), cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) devices, and implantable sensors. Pacemakers, IDCs, and CRT devices are used to provide therapies to people with appropriately indicated heart conditions. In addition to providing therapy, these devices and other devices within this domain capture information about the patient, the device, and therapies delivered by the device. This information is used for the observations that the message model supports.</p><p>The DMIM and associated RMIM for this domain were developed under the guidance of the Orders and Observations Technical Committee. To develop the DMIM and associated RMIM, HL7 members provided input that focused on the extensibility of the models to related areas (e.g., non-cardiac implantable devices, at-home follow-up of implantable devices, etc.).</p><p>As the Therapeutic Devices domain evolves, we anticipate the development of additional RMIMs that will be introduced by groups interested in areas outside of implantable cardiac devices.</p><p>The primary participants in the Implantable Cardiac Device industry have provided input such that the current DMIM and associated RMIM supports clinical messaging requirements for the industry.  </p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Follow-up" refIdentifier="POTD_RM000001UV02"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" refIdentifier="POTD_HD000001UV02"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="POTD_MT000001UV02-msg" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" refIdentifier="POTD_MT000001UV02"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2004-11-18T14:49:14"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p><emph role="strong">Therapeutic Devices Domain</emph></p><p>The therapeutic devices domain comprises the models, messages, and other artifacts that are needed to support messaging related to therapy delivery and observations made by a medical device.</p><p>Currently, the scope has been focused only on implantable cardiac devices (pacemakers, defibrillators, etc.).</p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-POTD_DO000001UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="dmims-POTD_DO000001UV-ic"><dmim identifier="POTD_DM000000UV" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Definition New" familiarName="Implantable Cardiac Device DMIM" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DM000000UV-rmi" sortPrefix="10|02|05|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" class="changed" lastEdit="2008-06-04T10:51:25"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_DM000000UV" name="Description" parent="POTD_DM000000UV-rmi" id="desc-POTD_DM000000UV-rmi" lastEdit="2008-06-04T10:51:25"><p><emph role="strong">Domain Message Information Models (D-MIM)</emph> 
Therapeutic Devices (POTD_DM000000) 
<emph role="strong">Overview</emph></p><p>The Therapeutic Devices domain comprises the models, messages, and other artifacts that are needed to support messaging related to therapy delivery and observations made by therapeutic medical devices. </p><p>The Therapeutic Devices D-MIM is a refined subset of the HL7 Reference Information Model (RIM) that includes the set of classes, attributes and relationships used to create messages for reporting information captured from these devices about patients and the device themselves.</p><p>Currently, the scope has been focused only on implantable devices (pacemakers, defibrillators, etc.), which explains the simple nature of this message model. However, over time, it is anticipated that this D-MIM will expand to support more device types and device messaging systems.</p><p>This walk-through examines the DMIM from two perspectives, the observed (the patient and their device), and the observer (the care giver, associated personnel, and the device used to interrogate the patient's device).</p><p><emph role="strong">Focal Classes</emph> 
The model is focused on the Observation class. For therapeutic devices, such Observations are also known as "interrogations"; however, this model was designed such that it will be applicable to a wide range of implantable therapeutic devices. This Observation leverages the MedicalDeviceAct class for Observation detail concerning the device settings, delivered therapies, as well as patient and device statuses.  
</p><p><emph role="strong">D-MIM Core Structure</emph> 
The core structure of the model is composed of the Observation act in the event mood. This core structure indicates how interrogations and observations are related, see figure: 
</p><graphic source="T-fig1.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Therapeutic Devices Domain Information Model Classes Observation</emph> 
This D-MIM focuses on the Observation-Act of a device interrogation. All the other classes shown are only interesting and relevant in relationship to this Observation-Act. The relevant information items, attributes, and associations have a consistent meaning for observation definitions for device interrogations.  
</p><p>
The reader should refer to the documentation for the HL7 Reference Information Model for a complete set of attribute descriptions. 
</p><p><graphic source="fig2.gif"></graphic></p><p><emph role="strong">Participations and Act Relationships</emph></p><p>
The following associations are defined for a therapeutic device observation. Each association describes the relationship between the observation act and an entity or act that plays a significant part in the observation event. 
</p><p><emph role="strong">Observed</emph></p><p>
From the 
<emph>Observed</emph> 
From the observed vantage point, the subject Act Relationship is involved in instantiating an observation with a Participation of recordTarget. The subject Act Relationship from the Observation act to the MedicalDeviceAct is only applicable when there is a patient bound to the particular device, as shown in this Figure: 
</p><p><graphic source="fig3.gif"></graphic></p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Observation - Represents the observation using a mandatory unique identifier and time stamp.</p></item><item><p>Patient - Contains patient demographics consisting of First Name, Last name, Middle Initial, Date of Birth, identification number, and gender. Patient attributes are defined in the R_Patient Common Message Element Type (CMET).</p></item><item><p>Medical Device Act (MedicalDeviceAct) - Describes the device interrogation that is performed (e.g., At Home device interrogation, In Office device interrogation, etc.)</p></item><item><p>Device - Details the therapeutic device being observed (e.g. Device Name, Device Model, Device Serial Number, Device Manufacturer). Device attributes are defined in the R_AssignedDevice CMET.</p></item></list><p><emph>Device and Patient Observation Acts</emph>The Device and Patient Observations are:
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Device Therapy Settings: The settings in a device that relate to delivering therapies to the Patient (e.g., setting type, setting value) </p></item><item><p>Device Therapy: The events that are captured when a device delivers a therapy to the Patient (e.g., date/time of event, event description)</p></item><item><p>Patients Observations: The observations that a Device has made about the owning patient (e.g., observation type, observation value) </p></item><item><p>Organizer: This Act changes the subject from patient to device</p></item><item><p>Device Observations: The observations that a Device has made about itself (e.g., observation type, observation value)</p></item></list><p>
The following Figure describes the device and patient observations: 
<graphic source="fig4.gif"></graphic><emph>Medical Device Act Relationships</emph> 
The Medical Device Act has the following Act Relationships for associating the device and patient message components with the Observation:  
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>controlVariable - associates the Device Therapy Settings with the Medical Device Act</p></item><item><p>component1 - associates the Organizer Act with the Medical Device Act</p></item><item><p>component2 - associates Patient Observations with the Medical Device Act</p></item><item><p>component3 - associates Device Therapy with the Medical Device Act</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Observer</emph></p><p>
From the 
<emph>observer</emph> 
vantage point, there are three Participations in the Observation as shown in the following Figure: 
<graphic source="T-fig5.gif"></graphic> 
These Participations are: 
</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>
Author - A party that has responsibility for the information given in the Act and ownership of this Act. <emph>Note: The Author does not necessarily have to be present when the act occurs, but is accountable for the action through the power to delegate and the duty to review actions with the performing actor after the fact. The Author attributes are defined in the R_AssignedEntity CMET.</emph></p></item><item><p>
Performer - Identifies the role assisting in the Observation. The Performer attributes are defined in the R_AssignedEntity CMET. 
</p></item><item><p>Reusable Device - Identifies the device used to perform the interrogation that is being observed. The Reusable Device attributes are currently limited to the ExternalCardiacInterrogationDevice role, the interrogationDevice entity (player), and the Organization (scoper).</p></item></list><p>
In addition, the Observation is a component of the A_Encounter CMET. This association enables information from this specific Observation event to be associated with other information from a patient encounter.
</p><p><emph role="strong">Conclusion</emph></p><p>In simple terms, we have a message model for describing an Observation of an interrogator at a physical location who is performing an interrogation of a therapeutic medical device (bound to a patient) using identifiable interrogation equipment.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="POTD_DM000000UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Topic" familiarName="Implantable Cardiac Device" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="10" baseClass="Implantable Cardiac Device" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2"><descriptive identifier="intro-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Introduction" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="intro-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" lastEdit="2005-07-21T14:42:02"><p>The Implantable Cardiac Device topic contains models, messages, and other artifacts that are needed to support messaging related to the life of an implanted cardiac device. These messages include: registration and association of implanted device with a patient; patient observation and episode information; current device therapy settings and adjustments of device therapy settings; device diagnostics; and tracking a device throughout its life.</p><p>Implanted Cardiac Devices operate within the human body in both monitoring and therapy delivery capacities. These devices are categorized as Pacemakers, Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillators (ICDs), and Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT) devices.  Each of these electronic devices delivers a controlled electric shock to the heart to return the heart back to a normal rhythm.</p><p>This topic is focused on developing messages to facilitate in the transfer of implanted cardiac device data:</p><p>Device Identification Data</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Manufacturer</p></item><item><p>Model</p></item><item><p>Serial Number</p></item></list><p>Device Therapy Settings</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Pacing settings</p></item><item><p>Defibrillation settings</p></item><item><p>Therapy tuning features</p></item><item><p>Arrhythmia Logging Data</p></item></list><p>Diagnostic Data</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Trended diagnostics on device functionality (e.g., lead impedance, pacing thresholds)</p></item><item><p>Diagnostic data for titration of patient therapy</p></item></list><p>Data from device follow-up testing</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Inductions</p></item><item><p>Various device status tests</p></item></list><p>The IDC project team plans to develop normative terminology and messaging standards for implantable cardiac devices to facilitate their integration into health care systems, electronic medical records, and a variety of applications.</p></descriptive><storydivn identifier="sbs-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Storyboards" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="sbs-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="sstop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="POTD_ST000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device" familiarName="Implantable Cardiac Device Follow-Up" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_ST000001UV02-str" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2005-07-21T17:11:50"><descriptive identifier="purp-POTD_ST000001UV02" name="Purpose" parent="POTD_ST000001UV02-str" id="purp-POTD_ST000001UV02-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2005-07-21T17:11:50"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the messaging related to the clinical review of implantable cardiac device status</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POTD_SN000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-up" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-up" parent="POTD_ST000001UV02-str" id="POTD_ST000001UV02-POTD_SN000001UV02-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" lastEdit="2005-11-14T12:19:28"><p>Adam Everyman presents at the electrophysiology (EP) follow-up clinic for his appointment. Adam will present for follow-up 7-10 days after implant and every 3-6 months thereafter, depending on the therapy protocol. </p><p>Dr. Ed Electrode, an Electrophysiologist - also referred to as a following physician, and Nancy Nightingale, an R.N., work in the electrophysiology (EP) follow-up clinic. </p><p>Note: In the area of Electrophysiology, a "programmer" is a commonly used term to describe a specialized computer that is capable of communicating with an implanted device. Programmers are used to interrogate implanted devices and "program", or make changes to, implanted cardiac device settings.</p><p>Nancy places a wand over the implant area. The wand is connected to a programmer that interrogates the device and extracts the data (e.g., settings, status, events) from the device. Nancy reviews the device data and captures the "current state" device data from the programmer screen and/or prints out the settings and/or uses an information transfer mechanism (e.g., floppy disk, analog cable, etc.) to transmit device data, which is in a proprietary format, to a translator system. </p><p>If the device data has been sent to the translator system, the clinician may desire to transmit data to the electronic health record (EHR). In this case, a necessary subset (pre-determined by the clinic and the entity responsible for the translator system) of the data that represents the device's 'summary data' is converted from the proprietary format and transmitted using HL7 messaging to the EP office electronic health record system (EHR). This summary data is considered to be a 'snapshot' of the device at a moment in time. </p><p>Dr. Ed Electrode reviews the device data and identifies appropriate changes to device settings. Nancy Nightingale makes these changes via the programmer. Nancy then captures the "final state" device data. Nancy then uses the information transfer mechanism to transmit device data, which is in a proprietary format, to a translator system, which again converts the data into an HL7 message and communicates the 'summary data' to the clinic's EHR. This second message will utilize the same HL7 message format as the first. </p><p>Note: In this storyboard the "initial state" and "final state"' are really subjective titles for device data at a moment in time. Therefore, there is no need to make a distinction between these two "states" in the message model.</p><p>It is important to note that a clinician can initiate one or two HL7 transmissions to the clinic's EHR. This choice is based on a given clinic's workflow. In either case the interaction is the same. </p><p>These reports are sent as unsolicited observation events. </p><p>A device summary report contains the following items:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p>Device Diagnostics - represented by the DeviceTherapy act in the message model</p></item><item><p>Events Counters - represented by the PatientObservation act in the message model</p></item><item><p>Device Observations (except electrocardiograms) - represented by the DeviceObservation act in the message model</p></item><item><p>Programmed Therapy Settings - represented by the DeviceTherapySetting act in the message model</p></item><item><p>Clinician Comments - represented by the PatientObservation act in the message model</p></item></list><p>Portions of the previous storyboard may also apply to Adam Everyman having his device followed remotely. Adam will present to a device located outside of the clinic (e.g., in Adams residence) which will capture the state of his implanted device and will transmit the information to a translator system. The translator system, converts the data into an HL7 message and communicates the 'summary data' to the clinic's EHR.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="POTD_ST000001UV02.gif"/><intref ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02" sequence="1"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Application Roles" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="roles-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="arop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><approle identifier="POTD_AR000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Order Completion Tracker" familiarName="Cardiac Interrogation Observation Tracker" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" sortPrefix="10|11|10|30|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" hidden="no" lastEdit="2005-08-08T18:00:04"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_AR000001UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" id="desc-POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" lastEdit="2005-08-08T18:00:04"><p>The Party that receives the interrogation notification, such as a medical records system</p></descriptive><arref role="parentrole" ref="POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Order Completion Tracker" refFamiliarName="Cardiac Interrogation Observation Tracker" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000001UV02"/><arref role="child" ref="POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Order Completion Tracker" refFamiliarName="Cardiac Interrogation Observation Tracker" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000001UV02"/><intref role="receives" ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02"/></approle><approle identifier="POTD_AR000010UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Creator Fulfiller" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Interrogation System" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" sortPrefix="10|20|15|10|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" hidden="no" lastEdit="2005-07-21T16:57:18"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_AR000010UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" id="desc-POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" lastEdit="2005-07-21T16:57:18"><p>An implantable cardiac device interrogation system acquires information that an implantable device has captured about itself, about the patient, and about the therapies that the device has delivered. This system then translates the data from the implantable device format and communicates it to clinical information systems</p></descriptive><arref role="parentrole" ref="POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Creator Fulfiller" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Interrogation System" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000010UV02"/><arref role="child" ref="POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Creator Fulfiller" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Interrogation System" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000010UV02"/><intref role="sends" ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Trigger Events" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="tes-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="teop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="POTD_TE000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_TE000001UV02-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="10|20|40||05|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2005-08-23T10:35:27"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_TE000001UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_TE000001UV02-te" id="desc-POTD_TE000001UV02-te" lastEdit="2005-08-23T10:35:27"><p>State transition from null to completed called complete.</p><p>Information from an Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-up is captured in an Implantable Cardiac Device Interrogation System. At the user's discretion, this information is sent to a Cardiac Interrogation Observation Tracker.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="rmims-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="rmop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="POTD_RM000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Event New" familiarName="Implantable Cardiac Device Follow-up" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" sortPrefix="10|20|05|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2005-07-21T16:46:38"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_RM000001UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" id="desc-POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" lastEdit="2005-07-21T16:46:38"><p>See DMIM description for details about this message.</p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="POTD_DM000000UV-rmi" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Definition New" refFamiliarName="Implantable Cardiac Device DMIM" class="changed" refIdentifier="POTD_DO000001UV"/><diagref ref="POTD_RM000001UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" refIdentifier="POTD_HD000001UV02"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="hmds-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="hdop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="POTD_HD000001UV02" name="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" parent="POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" id="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" sortPrefix="99IMPLANTED CARDIAC DEVICE|20|05|" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2004-07-21T13:59:51"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_HD000001UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" id="desc-POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" lastEdit="2004-07-21T13:59:51"><p>Message types based upon this HMD are to be used to communicate for Cardiac Device follow-up</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="POTD_HD000001UV02"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="POTD_RM000001UV02-rmi" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event New" refFamiliarName="Implantable Cardiac Device Follow-up" refIdentifier="POTD_RM000001UV02"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="POTD_MT000001UV02-msg" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event New" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" refIdentifier="POTD_MT000001UV02"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="msgs-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><msgtype identifier="POTD_MT000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Event New" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" parent="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" id="POTD_MT000001UV02-msg" sortPrefix="10|20|05|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2005-11-22T15:46:38"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="POTD_MT000001UV02"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="POTD_HD000001UV02-hmd" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" refIdentifier="POTD_HD000001UV02"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Interactions" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="ints-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice" name="Reference" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="inop-POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="POTD_IN000001UV02" name="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" familiarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ImplantableCardiacDevice-ic" id="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|20|40|05|" baseClass="ImplantableCardiacDevice" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="2" lastEdit="2005-08-12T14:20:52"><descriptive identifier="desc-POTD_IN000001UV02" name="Description" parent="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" id="desc-POTD_IN000001UV02-int" lastEdit="2005-08-12T14:20:52"><p>This interaction is used by the Implanted Device interrogation system to notify the receiving clinical information system of the observation results from the interrogation.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="POTD_AR000010UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Creator Fulfiller" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Interrogation System" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000010UV02"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="POTD_AR000001UV02-ar" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Order Completion Tracker" refFamiliarName="Cardiac Interrogation Observation Tracker" refIdentifier="POTD_AR000001UV02"/><teref role="trigger" ref="POTD_TE000001UV02-te" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" refIdentifier="POTD_TE000001UV02"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="POTD_MT000001UV02-msg" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implanted Cardiac Device Event New" refIdentifier="POTD_MT000001UV02"/><rcvrresp identifier="POTD_IN000001UV02_Resp1" name="Responsibility- 1" parent="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" id="POTD_IN000001UV02_Resp1-rsp"><teref role="responsetrigger" ref="POTD_TE000001UV02-te" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Follow-Up" refIdentifier="POTD_TE000001UV02"/><intref role="responseinteraction" ref="POTD_IN000001UV02-int" sectID="hmpotd" sectType="SB" refName="Implantable Cardiac Device Event Complete Notification" refFamiliarName="Implanted Cardiac Device Results Notification" refIdentifier="POTD_IN000001UV02"/></rcvrresp></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-POTD_DO000001UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="cindx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-POTD_DO000001UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="indx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-POTD_DO000001UV-ic" id="POTD_DO000001UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

