<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by andrew hinchley (HL7 Publications TC) -->
<!-- edited with XML Spy v4.0 (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Sandy Boyer -->
<div2 id="v3gmsgcomp">
	<head>Navigating around a message specification</head>
	<p>The HL7 Messaging Components section of the V3 Guide is provided to help readers of the V3 standards understand the messages and supporting content submitted by the technical committees. This information is contained in each of the domain chapters.</p>
	<p>V3 introduces a new approach to HL7 message development. To assist with the comprehension of this new approach, the domain chapters begin with a high-level overview and progressively drill down to lower levels of messaging detail (including storyboards, applications roles, trigger events, D-MIMs, R-MIMs, HMDs, message types, and interactions). The following is the structure of the table of contents for each of the domains.</p>
	<p>
		<graphic source="graphics/VG_3_1_02.gif"/>
	</p>
	<p>Each chapter begins with an overview of the domain and the scope of the messages defined there. Since a  "big picture" understanding of the particular domain is crucial to understanding the messages defined within it, each domain chapter provides a Storyboard section. This section contains both a narrative and a diagrammatic representation of the messages that will be exchanged and the types of healthcare applications that will exchange the messages defined in the chapter, and illustrates the overall flow of the messages between these applications, including the order of such information flows.</p>
	<p>The Message Design Element Navigation (below) provides a quick overview of the Message Types, HMDs and R-MIMs relationship to each other with hyperlinks to the actual artifact definitions within the chapter. The navigation display uses a "tree-view" control that allows the user to expand or collapse a hierarchy of elements.  If the symbol to the left of a row includes the plus sign ("+"), clicking on the row will expand the row to show its children.  Conversely, if the symbol at left is the minus sign ("-"), clicking on the row will hide the dependent, child rows below that row.  If the symbol at the left of a row is a dot, then the row has no children to be displayed.</p>
	<p>Within each domain the content has been revised from January 2004 to provide the following structure. First information that applies to the whole domain. This is defined in the next two paragraphs. This is followed by message definitions grouped by "topic".  Each topic is in fact covers all the definitions in a particular sub-domain. Topic names and the number of topics defined are left to each HL7 committee.</p>
	<p>The Domain Information Model (D-MIM) is presented first in each domain, providing a graphical and narrative detail of the scope of the domain. The D-MIM is the first in the series of information models presented in each domain chapter. The D-MIM provides a diagrammatic representation of only those classes, attributes and associations that are required for the messages defined by the domain. The D-MIM is a subset of the RIM but uses specific conventions to represent artifacts such as CMETs and various types of associations. Once the classes, attributes and associations for a particular domain have been isolated via the D-MIM, the next logical step is to extract, from the D-MIM, the set of classes, attributes and associations required for an HMD or set of HMDs that originate from the same root class. These extractions are referred to as R-MIMs (Refined Message Information Models), which are a subset of and use the same conventions as the domain D-MIM. </p>
	<p>The second element in the domain is one or more domain-level storyboards.  Each storyboard includes a diagrammatic representation, called an Interaction Diagram. This diagram depicts healthcare applications by the generic roles they play, such as Clinical Document Repository or Order Placer. These generic roles are known as application roles and are depicted in the diagram as vertical lines. Each information flow between two application roles is an interaction and identified on the Storyboard diagram as a horizontal, arrowed line. Interactions describe the purpose of information flow. Create Patient Billing Account and Delete Patient Billing Account are examples of interactions found in the HL7 V3 messaging standard. Once the overall picture of data exchange is presented, the Storyboard section continues with a narrative describing how the interactions might unfold in real life. Following the narrative is a description of each application role. Storyboards may be represented for the entire domain, or may be specific to a topic within the domain.</p>
	<p>All remaining material is grouped under a topic name. Some committees will define a large number of topic names. Other committees may have very few. It is completely up to a committee to decide. Within each topic, message specification is grouped under six headings. Each heading is decribed in the following paragraphs</p>
	<p>Storyboard: For each topic, one or more storyboards scope the specifications that follow</p>
	<p>Application Roles: The application roles applicable to this topic are defined.From the Application Role definitions, the reader can identify the purpose for information flow between two healthcare applications and the roles that those healthcare applications play in that exchange</p>
	<p>Trigger events: . The question of what prompts information exchange between two applications is answered by the trigger event.  This part of the topic specification is a list/description of the trigger events defined by the domain.</p>
	<p>The final products, the message types, are derived by the intersection of specific interactions, application roles, and trigger events. The remaining portions of the domain chapters show, through a series of information models, how the resulting message types are derived.</p>
	<p>The data represented in the R-MIM are ordered in a tabular format known as a Hierarchical Message Description (HMD). Each HMD produces a single base message template from which the specific message types are drawn. A message type represents a unique set of constraints applied against a particular HMD. Message types are presented in both grid and table view as well as an Excel spreadsheet. In addition, a link to the XML schema used to validate any message conforming to the message type is provided along with an XML example. The domain chapters close with a section that groups message data by interaction, giving the sending and receiving applications roles, trigger event and message type for each. </p>
	<p>In the final part of the domain specifications, the Common Message Elements Indexes list the CMETs derived from the domain's D-MIM and the CMETs referenced in each HMD defined within the D-MIM.  The index links to the Common Message Element Type Domain content. </p>
	<p>The Interaction Index is designed to provide useful cross-references between the documents.  The Interaction Indexes list the Interactions used against each Application Role, Trigger Event and Message Type.  </p>
	<p>The Domain Glossary contains terms that are defined in this domain, as well as terms that are common to all domains.</p>
	<div3 id="v3msgcompstruct">
		<head>Artifact Identification System</head>
		<p>Within the HL7 V3 standards the components that make up the documentation are each referred to as ‘artifacts’.  This includes, storyboards, application roles, trigger events, D-MIMs, R-MIMs, HMDs, message types and interactions are artifacts. Each artifact is submitted by a Technical Committee and given a unique identifier that is assigned by concatenating the Sub-Section, Domain and Artifact code with a 6-digit, non-meaningful number. </p>
		<p>The Sub-Section and Domain Codes assigned include:</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<emph role="strong">Health &amp; Clinical Management Domains</emph>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Operations (PO)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Clinical Document Architecture (POCD)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Clinical Genomics (POCG)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Public Health Reporting (PORR)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Regulated Products (PORP)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Regulated Studies (PORT)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Specimen (POSP)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Therapeutic Devices (POTD)
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Records	(RC)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Medical Records (RCMR)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<emph role="strong">Administrative Management Domains</emph>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Practice	(PR)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Patient Administration (PRPA)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Personnel Management (PRPM)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Scheduling (PRSC)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Financial	Management (FI)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Accounting &amp; Billing (FIAB)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Claims &amp; Reimbursement (FICR)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Reasoning (RE)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Care Provision (REPC)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Records (RC)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Medical Records (RCMR)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<emph role="strong">Specification Infrastructure</emph>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Message Control	(MC)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Message Control Infrastructure (MCCI)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Message Act Infrastructure (MCAI)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Master File (MF)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Master File Management Infrastructure (MFMI)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Query (QU)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Query Infrastructure	(QUQI)
				</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
					Subsection: Common Content	(CO)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Common Message Elements  (COCT)<br/>
					&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Domain: Common Message Content (COMT)
				</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>Each Health &amp; Clinical and Administrative Management domain may contain domain specified content for Query and Master File Subsections as well as general domain information. </p>
		<p>The following Artifact Codes have been assigned:</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Artifact</th>
					<th>Code</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Application Role</td>
					<td>AR</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>D-MIM (Domain Information Model)</td>
					<td>DM</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>HMD (Hierarchical Message Descriptor)</td>
					<td>HD</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Interaction</td>
					<td>IN</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Message Type</td>
					<td>MT</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>R-MIM (Refined Message Information Model)</td>
					<td>RM</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Storyboard</td>
					<td>ST</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Storyboard Narrative</td>
					<td>SN</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Trigger Event</td>
					<td>TE</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>The current version of HL7 3.x supports only one Realm identified as the “Universal Realm” with the code “UV”. </p>
		<p>The Version Number is assigned once an artifact successfully passes membership ballot.  Currently all artifacts are assigned the version 00 indicating that they are undergoing balloting. </p>
		<p>An application role submitted by the Patient Administration domain will have the following unique artifact identifier:</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<emph role="strong">PRPA_AR00001UV00</emph>
		</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Where:</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;PR = Subsection: Practice</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;PA = Domain: Patient Administration</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;AR = Artifact: Application Role</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;00001 = 6 digit non-meaningful number assigned by the TC to ensure uniqueness</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;UV = Realm (the only current value is UV for universal)</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;00 = Current version number</p>
		<p>As you browse through the ballot documents, you will notice that most artifact identifiers are hyperlinks that connect to the particular artifact in question.</p>
		<p>The remaining chapters of this section of the V3 Guide explain each of these artifacts.</p>
	</div3>
	<div3 id="v3msgartfsort">
		<head>Describing V3 message artifacts</head>
		<p> Unambiguous description of V3 artifacts is achieved by defining a “Structured Sort Name” for each artifact.  This unique structured name is used to identify the relationship of the artifact to others so that it is sorted appropriately in the publications database. which acts both as a repository and the basis on which specifications and ballot material can be presented in a logical order.</p>
		<p>Some types of artifacts also have a “Title Name” that is designed to be ‘human friendly’ and will appear in the table of contents and as the title for the artifact.  The title name is not guaranteed to be unique, but may be a handy ‘human understandable’ tool for identifying the artifact.   When a Title Name has also been defined for an artifact the Structured Sort Name is shown underneath the Title name for reference.  Artifacts that do not have separate title names will have the Structured Sort Name appear in the table of contents and in the title bar.</p>
		<p>Note that the Artifact Code, rather than the Structured Sort Name or Title Name, is always the best key to use when referencing an artifact as this will not change over time and is guaranteed to be unique. </p>
		<p>The following table provides the algorithm for defining the Structured Sort Name for each type of artifact:</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Artifact</th>
					<th>Structured Sort Name Algorithm</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Storyboard</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Free-Text]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Storyboard Narrative</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Free-Text]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Application Role - Unhidden</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Free-Text]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Application Role - Hidden</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood][Capability][Stereotype][Environment]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Application Role - Query</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifier] Query Placer or<br/>[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifier] Query Fulfiller</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Trigger Event</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [State Transition][Qualifier][Action] </td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Trigger Event - Query</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifier] Query or<br/>[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifier] Query Response</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>D-MIM</td>
					<td>[Domain name] Domain Model</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>R-MIM</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>HMD</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [State Transition]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Message Type</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [State Transition] [Environment]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Interaction</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [State Transition] [Action][Environment]</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Interaction - Query</td>
					<td>[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifiers] Query or[Base Class] [Mood] [Qualifiers] Query Response</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>The following table provides an explanation and the valid values and their sort order for each component of the Structured Sort Name:</p>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Base Class</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: Specified by the technical committee as a primary sort key to categorize the content of the domain. </p>
		<p>Sort Order: Defined by technical committees as appropriate for the domain. </p>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Free Text</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: The Structured Sort Name for some artifacts is only mandated for state transition-related names such as trigger events, allowing any technical committee to define a free text name for the artifact.  The Structured Sort Name must still be unique. Some technical committees are not following these rules for trigger events at present (which requires all but one name component to be present). As a result trigger event structured names are not as easily readable as they should be.</p>
		<p>Sort Order: Sorted alphabetically.</p>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Qualifiers</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: Uniquely identifies the query and will be based on the parameters and response payload within the query. </p>
		<p>Sort Order: Sorted alphabetically.</p>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Environment </emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	The technical committee may define the environment to be any value appropriate to the domain.</p>
		<p>Sort Order: Sorted alphabetically.</p>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Mood</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	This element is a further qualification of the base class, when the base class is an Act.  It refers to the value of the mood code (see RIM definition) for the base class.  The principal values are Event, Order, Intent and Proposal.</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>Proposal</item>
							<item>Order</item>
							<item>Intent</item>
							<item>Event</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Action</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	The Action is a qualifier of interactions. It reflects the specific type of communication involved in a particular Interaction.</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>Notification</item>
							<item>Fulfilment Request</item>
							<item>Confirmation</item>
							<item>Rejection</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Application Role Stereotypes</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	The term stereotype, which is extensively used in UML applications, is only currently used in HL7 V3 for application role stereotypes. The term is generally used to refer to a closely related group of items within a particular categorisation. In application roles, there are currently six stereotypes defined based upon the capability of one application to interact with another.  At the base level, applications simply send or receive notifications of events (Informer and Tracker).  At the next level applications expect an action and response from the application that receives the notification (Placer and Fulfiller). At the final level, applications are capable of handling confirmations of requests (Confirmer and Confirmation Receiver). Use of these standardised stereotype names is intended to assist in the definition and use of application roles generally. The stereotypes do not form an exclusive set of names for application roles.</p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>Placer: An application that is capable of notifying another application about a significant event, and expects the receiver to take action.</item>
							<item>Fulfiller: An application that is capable of receiving a request from a Placer application.</item>
							<item>Confirmer: An application that is capable of accepting a request from a Fulfiller application</item>
							<item>Confirmation Receiver: A role implemented by a placer indicating what types of confirmations it accepts.</item>
							<item>Informer: An application that is capable of notifying another application about a significant event (the status change of a focal class), but does not expect any action on the 	part 	of 	the receiver. Paired with 'Tracker'.</item>
							<item>Tracker: An application that is capable of receiving information about a significant event (the status change of a focal class), but is not expected by the receiver to perform 	any 		action.</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> State Transition</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	The values allowed in this component are derived from the RIM State Transition Models as defined by the HL7 harmonization process and documented in the RIM part of the standard. </p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>New</item>
							<item>Cancel</item>
							<item>Hold</item>
							<item>Release</item>
							<item>Activate</item>
							<item>Suspend</item>
							<item>Resume</item>
							<item>Abort</item>
							<item>Complete</item>
							<item>Reactivate</item>
							<item>Nullify</item>
							<item>Revise</item>
							<item>Replace</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Capability Related to Acts in Mood "Event"</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	Describes the functions that the application is capable of performing in terms of state transition if the artifact contains a mood code of Event as defined in the [Mood] component of the Structured Sort Name. </p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>Completion</item>
							<item>Existence</item>
							<item>Creator</item>
							<item>Cancellation</item>
							<item>Holder</item>
							<item>Revision</item>
							<item>Replacement</item>
							<item>Suspension</item>
							<item>Abortion</item>
							<item>Reactivation</item>
							<item>Nullification</item>
							<item>Comprehensive</item>
							<item>Global</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>
			<emph role="strong"> Capability Related to Acts in Moods Other Than "Event"</emph>
		</p>
		<p>Definition: 	Describes the functions that the application is capable of performing in terms of state transition if the artifact contains a mood code other than Event as defined in the [Mood] component of the Structured Sort Name.  </p>
		<table>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<th>Sort Order and Valid Values</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<list role="ordered">
							<item>Existence</item>
							<item>Completion</item>
							<item>Creator</item>
							<item>Cancellation</item>
							<item>Holder</item>
							<item>Revision</item>
							<item>Replacement</item>
							<item>Suspension</item>
							<item>Abortion</item>
							<item>Reactivation</item>
							<item>Nullification</item>
							<item>Comprehensive</item>
							<item>Global</item>
						</list>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p>Any Structured Sort Name components that do not follow the above guidelines or include invalid components will be sorted alphabetically. </p>
	</div3>
</div2>
