<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 2 (http://www.xmlspy.com) by andrew hinchley (HL7 Publications TC) -->
<div1 id="v3foreword">
	<head>Foreword</head>
	<p>HL7 as an organization, is re-orienting itself to become even more responsive to its members interests.  Since speed to market is of interest to many HL7 members, whether they are vendors or providers that implement the specifications, being more nimble is highly desirable.</p>
	<p>This means that HL7 may take on a task of developing specifications in an emerging messaging area where there are few actual implementations in place.  HL7 specifications become enablers of business processes that don't yet exist.  In many cases, consensus emerges to meet part of the requirements, but not yet all of the requirements.</p>
	<p>In other cases, the timing and workload of various Work Groups is such that only some of the Work Groups have had the opportunity to propose specifications that may eventually be considered valuable by other Work Groups.  In still other cases, a partial specification may be published in a ballot to solicit feedback from a wider audience on the practicality of the proposed solution.</p>
	<p>Managing the workload of the entire membership, across the many Work Groups working in parallel, is always a challenge.  When a specification release is due, specifications that are ready for a wider audience are assembled and published.  The intent is not only to provide specifications for implementation, but in some cases, to provide specifications that are the foundations for work-in-progress that will more fully emerge in future versions.  Early feedback from broader audiences and support for early adopters will improve the quality of all the specifications produced by HL7.</p>
	<p>HL7 is beginning to use the best practices of successful development groups, whether the product is software or specifications.  We are producing products in managed releases, using models during development to manage complexity and support coherence, using automation during the development process to improve productivity and quality, encouraging cross-organization communication, getting early feedback from our client community and being responsive to our clients' needs.</p>
	<div2 id="about">
		<head>About This Guide</head>
		<p>This HL7 V3 Guide was created for use by members of the Health Level Seven (HL7) Working Group as a companion to the V3 Standard. An earlier document the Message Development Framework contained additional supporting design and architecture material for V3. However the MDF has not been maintained in alignment with current V3 ballots and is therefore not recommended for use.  A new document the HDF, HL7 Development Framework  will in time provide the replacement for the MDF. However it contains changes  to the UML notations and approach which vary from this Ballot and in any case is still in draft form. Refer also  to the Glossary to clarify meaning of terms used in this document.</p>
		<p>The V3 Guide is divided into two sections, FOUNDATION COMPONENTS and MESSAGING COMPONENTS.  The FOUNDATION COMPONENTS section consists of chapters about information models, vocabulary, data types, and the Implementation Technology Specification (ITS), as used within the HL7 Version 3 specifications.  The MESSAGING COMPONENTS section provides guidance on the artifacts found in the Version 3 standard, such as storyboards, trigger events, interactions, etc., and is intended to help the reader understand how to read and use these artifacts. Readers of the V3 Guide will need a general understanding of both the foundation and messaging components to understand the V3 Specifications themselves.</p>
	</div2>
</div1>
